<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../XML/LetterSchema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<letter>
    
    <page num="1"><headLine></headLine>
       <p>
        <ln n="1"/>Monday. MerceDes busy with her work, so Gail ANd 
        <ln n="2"/>I started ot to purchase paint thigs.   Belgian CANN 
        <ln n="3"/>linen|anD Bockx oil colors. ENded up by getting 
        <ln n="4"/>$62.00 worth of materials- encluding palattes, bRUSH
        <ln n="5"/>rushes etc. Some for  gifts. Then to/Maria Roix'
        <ln n="6"/>for lace. (Had to get some, being in Belgium.)
        <ln n="7"/>A woman in the shop doing bobbin lace. Her fingeRS
        <ln n="8"/>flew like mad. She would only do it when a big
        <ln n="9"/>lot of tourists came in! Got lace &amp; a very nice laCE
        <ln n="10"/>lace tri mmed table cloth- about $20.00 for the ALICE 
        <ln n="11"/>fancy country suppers- hope she'll be pleased 
        <ln n="12"/>with it. Some lace vest affairs about $IO. each
        <ln n="13"/>for Frances (launndessme others) Also mats at $3 w
        <ln n="14"/>and so each.   Went across street to St Gudule
        <ln n="15"/>church.  NOt interesting- gaudy tapestries and n
        <ln n="16"/>not much else.We walked back- down hill somewhat.
        <ln n="17"/>buying dolls for Johnnie on the way. Later came 
        <ln n="18"/>M.G. and Clyde& M. with her Ford.We steeted over 
        <ln n="19"/>again to the beautifulPlace where we  sat outside
        <ln n="20"/>in the sun and had A\very excellent meal very cheAP 
        <ln n="21"/>All theresturants around the square seem to be
        <ln n="22"/>good, only some more fancy than others. Some are
        <ln n="23"/>very Flemish in style- with dark pannelling and
        <ln n="24"/>very fine brass, pewterand blue Delft plates .Bi 
        <ln n="25"/>brass plates and platters- all beautifullu
        <ln n="26"/>polished. Brass door knobs. I BOUGHT TINY POTTERY BUTTER DISHES
        <ln n="27"/>TWO ARE FOR ALICE
       </p>
        
        
        <p>
        <ln n="28"/>We had cockTAIls up|in M.G.'s room and waited sometime
        <ln n="29"/>for Mercedes after she finally arrived we went over
        <ln n="30"/>to the square where we had one last meal, andlook at /it
        </p>
       
       
       <drawing></drawing>
</page>
    
    
</letter>
