<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<hw1>
    
    <intro><link location="yale">Yale University</link>
    
    
    
  <tab>  <link>About Us</link>
    <link>Fellowships</link>
    <link>Events</link>
    <link>Douglass Book Prize</link>
    <link>Modern Slavery</link>
    <link>Digital Resources</link>
    <link>Donate</link></tab>
    <link>Home</link> > Harriet Jacobs: Selected Writings and Correspondence Documents</intro>
    
    <title>Harriet Jacobs: Selected Writings and Correspondence Documents </title>
    
<par>    The following documents represent just a few of the approximately 600 items gathered by Professor Yellin during her research on Harriet Jacobs. The Harriet Jacobs Papers Project is organizing these items into a two-volume documentary edition of papers by and about the 19th-century African-American author, abolitionist, and reformer Harriet Jacobs (1813-1897), to be published by the University of North Carolina Press.</par>
    
    <par>Biographical information relating to Harriet Jacobs’s principal correspondents, as well as more documentary materials and further information, is available at the <link>Harriet Jacobs Papers Projec</link>t website. Spelling and typographical errors in the manuscript have been retained in the transcripts. Editorial remarks have been set apart in brackets.
 </par>
<par date ="1835-06-04"> <subtitle><link>Advertisement for the capture of Harriet Jacobs. American Beacon, Norfolk Virginia, July 4, 1835</link></subtitle>
 
 Advertisement submitted by James Norcom for the capture of Harriet Jacobs after she went into hiding. <quote talker="James Norcom">As this girl absconded from the plantation of my son without any known cause or provocation, it is probable she designs to transport herself to the North.</quote>
    </par>
    <par date="1842-05-25"><subtitle><link>Joshua Coffin to Lydia Maria Child. June 25, 1842</link></subtitle>
        Coffin, a member of the American Anti-Slavery Society, writes to author and abolitionist Lydia Maria Child about Harriet Jacobs. <quote talker="Joshua Coffin">I hope you will call &amp; see, if she is now in the city, one of the most interesting cases of escape from slavery that you have ever seen.</quote></par>
   
   <par date="1846-05-04"><subtitle><link>John S. Jacobs to Sydney Howard Gay. June 4, 1846</link></subtitle>
    
    John S. Jacobs, Harriet’s brother, who had escaped from slavery in 1838 to become a noted antislavery lecturer, writes to the journalist and abolitionist Sydney Howard Gay about the efforts of the Norcom family to recapture Harriet Jacobs. <quote talker="John S. Jacobs">He sais that he dont wish to sell her at any price   he wants to get her to make ensample [example] of her for the good of the institution.</quote></par>
   <par dateafter= "1852-12-20" datebefore="1853-02-14"><subtitle> <link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. [After December 20, 1852, before February 14, 1853]</link></subtitle>
    
    Amy Kirby Post, abolitionist and women’s rights advocate, befriended Harriet and urged her to write her autobiography. In this letter Harriet expresses her reservations about telling of her ordeal. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">Your proposal to me has been thought over and over again but not with out some most painful rememberances.</quote></par>
   <par date="1853-02-14"> <subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. February 14, 1853</link></subtitle>
    
    Jacobs writes to Amy Post, reporting that she meant to approach the author Harriet Beecher Stowe about having Jacobs’s daughter Louise join her on her visit to England. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs"> I thought Louisa would be a very good representative of a Southern Slave   she has improved much in her studies and I think that she has energy enough to do something for the cause.</quote></par>
    <par date="1853-04-04"><subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. April 4, 1853</link></subtitle>
   
   In this letter to Amy Post, Jacobs angrily reports that Stowe had declined to have Louise accompany her to England. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">She was afraid that if her situation as a Slave should be known it would subject her to much petting and patronizing which would be more pleasing to a young Girl than useful.</quote></par>
    <par date="1853-03-??"><subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. March, 1854</link></subtitle>
    
    Jacobs writes of the difficulty she has had in finding time to write while working for Willis family. <quote>I have not written a single page by daylight   Mrs W dont know from my lips that I am writing for a Book</quote></par>
   <par date="1857-05-21"> <subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. June 21, 1857</link></subtitle>
    
    Jacobs relates to Amy Post of the difficulty in writing of her sexual oppression while enslaved. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">Woman can whisper—her cruel wrongs into the ear of a very dear friend—much easier than she can record them for the world to read.</quote></par>
  <par date="1960-07-13"><subtitle>  <link>Lydia Maria Child to Harriet Jacobs. August 13, 1860</link></subtitle>
    
    Child, a noted author of anti-slavery texts, agreed to write a preface to Jacobs’s work and edit the manuscript. <quote talker="Lydia Maria Child">I have very little occasion to alter the language, which is wonderfully good…</quote></par>
    <par date="1860-09-08"><subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Amy Post. October 8, 1860</link></subtitle>
   
   Harriet writes to Amy Post about the progress of her manuscript and Lydia Maria Child’s support. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">Mrs C is like your self a whole souled Woman—we soon found the way to each others heart.</quote></par>
    <par date="1861-04-13"><subtitle><link>Review of Incidents in the Life of a Slave Girl. The Weekly Anglo-African, April 13, 1861</link></subtitle>
    
    Incidents received a glowing review in the pages of the The Weekly Anglo-African. <quote  > In such volumes as this, the true romance of American life and history is to be found.</quote></par>
    <par date="1862-08-05"><subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs, <quote>Life Among the Contrabands.</quote> The Liberator, September 5, 1862</link></subtitle>
    
    Jacobs describes her relief work among the fugitives from slavery who had fled to Washington, D.C. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">I found men, women and children all huddled together, without any distinction or regard to age or sex. Some of them were in the most pitiable condition.</quote></par>
   <par date="1865-03-??"><subtitle> <link><quote>Jacobs School.</quote> The Freedmen’s Record, March, 1865</link></subtitle>
    
    The Freedmen’s Record reports on Jacobs’s work providing support for a free school in Alexandria, Virginia. <quote talker="The Freedmen’s Record">Was any dream of the night dearer and sweeter to her than the present reality?—her people freed, and the school-house, built mainly by her own exertions, named in her honor, and presided over by black and white teachers, working harmoniously together.</quote></par>
    <par date="1867-04-25"><subtitle><link>Harriet Jacobs to Ednah Dow Cheney. April 25, 1867</link></subtitle>
    
    While visiting her family home in Edenton, North Carolina, Jacobs writes to Ednah Dow Cheney of the New England Freedman’s Aid Society. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">Thank God, the bitter cup is drained of its last dreg. There is no more need of hiding places to conceal slave Mothers.</quote></par>
    <par date="1868-03-02"><subtitle><link><quote>Savannah Freedmen’s Orphan Asylum</quote>. (London) Anti-Slavery Reporter, March 2, 1868</link></subtitle>
        Harriet Jacobs’s appeal for aid for the Savannah Freedmen’s Orphan Asylum. Harriet and her daughter Louisa were active in educational and relief work in Savannah, Georgia. <quote talker="Harriet Jacobs">There are many thousand orphans in the Southern States.</quote></par>
   <credits> <link>Yale
    Accessibility at Yale</link> ·<link> Privacy policy </link>
    Copyright © 2020 Yale University · All rights reserved 
    <social act="facebook"><link>Facebook</link>
    <link act="twiter">Twitter</link>
    <link act="flicker">Flickr</link>
    <link act="itunes">iTunes</link>
    <link act="youtube">YouTube</link></social></credits>
    
</hw1>
