<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <subject>Letter from <person>Marian Baldwin</person>, <date><month>June</month> 30,
                <year>1917</year></date></subject>
<!-- 2022-09-07 ebb: Here's me making a comment on this awesome code! I like what you're doing with attributes here: this is a
    great example of how attributes can provide extra information about stuff in the text. -->
    <para>On Board <obj foreignlanguage="French" objType="boat">La Touraine</obj>,</para>

    <para>
        <date><month>June</month> 30th, <year>1917</year></date>.</para>

    <para>Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am actually off to
            <loc geo="country">France</loc> and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone.
        Everything has happened so quickly since the <org aka="A. F. F. W.">American Fund for French
            Wounded</org> found an opening for me in <loc geo="city">Paris</loc> that I suppose I am
        still somewhat dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and
        that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I
        have had a bit of a taste in <loc geo="city">New York</loc> of the work that the <org
            aka="American Fund for French Wounded">A. F. F. W.</org> is doing but its Headquarters
        in <loc geo="city">Paris</loc> will be different in some ways I fancy.</para>

    <para>I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few girls of my age
        are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me on my
        great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of late.</para>

    <para>As we drifted down <loc geo="water">the river</loc>, in the sunset glow with two absurd
            <obj objType="boat">tugs</obj> puffing alongside, I know that many eyes were moist and
        that the same thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that
        sky-line again! It was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded
        from the sky and one star after another appeared. I knew that you would be looking at those
        same stars down in <loc geo="city">Lakewood</loc> and that your thoughts and prayers were
        the same that filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, after
        all.</para>

    <para>We waited near the <obj objType="statue">Statue of Liberty</obj> until
            <time>midnight</time>—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This
        individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the party
        which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than the <org>Italian Mission</org>.
        Our spirits rose at once for, what with <person>Frank Sayre</person> on the boat and these
        distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so
        doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two <obj objType="boat">destroyer</obj>s
        following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side,
        and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in <event aka="WWI">this
            war</event> A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger for the
        first four or five days but that after that I might see some excitement. Here's
        hoping!</para>

    <para>I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a native of <loc
            geo="country">Haiti</loc>, voluble and very portly — has four large pieces of baggage in
        our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes countless
        thin cigarettes that smell like incense ! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room
        for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with
        my belongings! She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she
        didn't think we would fight and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join
        her son who has been fighting with the French since the beginning of <event aka="WWI">the
            war</event> but will never go back to <loc>the Front</loc> now, having lost
        some fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his
        fingers.</para>

    <workcited>Source: _Canteening Overseas_ 1917-1919, published 1920.</workcited>
</root>
