<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root> [Letter from Marian Baldwin, June 30, 1917]

On Board La Touraine,

<date when='6-30-1917'>June 30th, 1917.</date>

><paragraph num='1'>Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am actually off to<location> France</location>
and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone. Everything has happened so quickly since the 
<location>American</location> Fund for <location>French </location>Wounded found an opening for me in <location>Paris</location> that I suppose I am still somewhat 
dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I can't look ahead 
makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in New York 
of the work that the A. F. F. W. is doing but its Headquarters in <location>Paris </location>will be different in some ways I fancy.
</paragraph>
<paragraph>I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few <gender>girls</gender> of my age
are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me on my great 
adventure and <description>send me along a path</description> which has proved so dangerous of late.</paragraph>

<paragraph>As we drifted down the <description>river,</description> in the <description>sunset glow</description> with two absurd tugs puffing alongside, 
I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all our minds. How many 
of this ship's company will see that <description>sky-line</description> again! It was <description>very quiet</description>, no one spoke much, 
and, little by little, the glow faded from the <description>sky and one star</description> after another appeared. 
I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in<location> Lakewood</location> and that your thoughts
and prayers were the same that filled my <bodypart type='inner'>heart</bodypart> at that moment. Somehow distance does not separate, 
after all.
</paragraph>
<paragraph>We waited near the <location>Statue of Liberty</location> until midnight—a rumor had it that a "personage" was 
to come on board. This individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when it was given out 
that the party which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than the<location> Italian</location> Mission. 
Our spirits <flower>rose</flower> at once for, what with <name>Frank Sayre</name> on the boat and these distinguished <location>Italian</location> gentlemen, 
we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two 
destroyers following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, 
one on each side, and seem to be the same somber <color>gray</color> which all ships are affecting in this war. 
A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger for the first four or five days 
but that after that I might see some <feeling>excitement</feeling>. Here's hoping!
</paragraph>
<paragraph>I have a <location>small inside <place>cabin</place></location> and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a native of 
<nationally>Haiti</nationally>, voluble and very portly—has <description>four large pieces of baggage</description> in our tiny stateroom, 
wears a costume which resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes countless <description>thin cigarettes</description> that 
<description>smell like incense!</description> When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much <place>room</place> for me but, as she says, 
luckily I am small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really 
isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would fight and 
from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son who has been fighting with the 
<location>French </location>since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the Front now, having lost some 
<bodypart>fingers</bodypart> off each <bodypart>hand.</bodypart> She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his<bodypart> fingers.</bodypart> 
</paragraph>
[Source: _Canteening<location> Overseas</location>_: <date>1917-1919</date>, published <date>1920.</date>] </root>