<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="letter2schema-corrected.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<Letter>
    <para kind="info"><person name="Joshua Coffin">Coffin</person>, a member of the <org>American Anti-Slavery Society</org>, writes to author and abolitionist <person name="Lydia Maria Child">Lydia Maria Child</person>
about <person name="Harriet Jacobs">Harriet Jacobs</person>. "I hope you will call &amp; see, if she is now in the city, one of the most interesting
cases of escape from slavery that you have ever seen."
</para>


<date><loca>Phila.</loca> 25 June 1842</date>

<para>Esteemed Friend,
... I hope you will call &amp; see, if she is now in the city, one of the most interesting cases of
escape from slavery that you have ever seen. She was sent from this city yesterday morning &amp;
consigned to <person name = "Mr.Johnston">Mr. Johnston</person>. She is from <loca>N.C.</loca> was brought away by a sea captain. She was
sold by her master to the speculators &amp; to avoid being sent away she was hidden for 7 years!
in a small upper room of a house occupied by colored people &amp; within a hundred yards of her
master's house, who did not know she was there. She had not seen her boy, for 7 years till
within 3 days of her coming away. She has been shut up so long that she can hardly walk.
Another woman was brought away from<loca>Delaware</loca>, who was found tied to a tree. If <person name = "Mr.Johnston">Mr.
Johnston</person> was the man he ought to be, he would invite you occasionally to see some of these
remarkable cases, which are continually passing from <loca>Phil.</loca> to <loca>N.Y.</loca> The Vagrant what a queer
mistake. <org>The Vigilance Committee</org> of this city are doing a fine business in weakening &amp;
delapidating the edifice of slavery. Success to them...
    <person name = "Joshua Coffin">Joshua Coffin</person>
</para>

<para kind="info">Citation:
    Autograph letter, signed; Anti-Slavery Collection, Boston Public Library; <person name = "Lydia Maria Child">Lydia Maria</person>
    Child Papers, The Collected Correspondence of <person name = "Lydia Maria Child">Lydia Maria Child</person>, <date>1817-1880</date>, ed.
    <person name = "Patricia G. Holland">Patricia G. Holland</person> and <person name = "Milton Meltzer">Milton Meltzer.</person> <loca>Millwood, N.Y.</loca>: <person name = "Kraus Microfilm">Kraus Microfilm</person>, <date>1980</date>. 14:389
</para>

</Letter>