<?xml-model href="../sherlock.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <series>Series: Sherlock Holmes</series>
        <show>Show: The Adventure of the Tolling Bell</show>
        <date when="1947-04-07">Date: Apr 07 1947</date>
        <castList>CAST <cast xml:id="announcer">Announcer</cast>
            <cast xml:id="watson">Watson</cast>
            <cast xml:id="holmes">Holmes</cast>
            <cast xml:id="mary">Mary</cast>
            <cast xml:id="michol">Mrs. Michol</cast>
            <cast xml:id="gillian">Gillian (pronounced Gil'-ee-an)</cast></castList>
    </metadata>
    <script>
        <ln><music>INTRO</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker>Cramel Hair Tonic and Cramel Shampoo present the new
            adventures of <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>, starring Nigel Bruce as <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>, and Tom Conway as
            <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND UNDER</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker>Now once again it's time to keep that weekly appointment
            with our good friend and host, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. Good evening, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Good evening, Mr. Bell. As usual you're punctual to the minute.
            Pull up a chair and make yourself comfortable.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>BELL</speaker>Thank you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>That's it. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>BELL</speaker>I see that you have the old black, tin dispatch box out again,
            <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. I deduce that you were going over your notes on tonight's case.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Elementary my, dear boy. Among the records I came across some
            notes of some cases that I'd almost forgotten. The shocking death of Crosby the banker,
            the Adeltine tragedy, and some darter on the unusual contents of the ancient British
            pharaoh.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>BELL</speaker>Those stories sound pretty intriguing, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>I shall tell them to you some other evening, Mr. Bell. Tonight,
            I'm going to recount an adventure that took place in the heart of the beautiful English
            countryside. I call it, "The Adventure of the Tolling Bell."
                <stageDirect>NARRATING</stageDirect> Well that story began in a small country
            village of Conforth.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> had recently brought to a successful conclusion the affair
            of the Barrow and Furnace Wheelchair Murders. And we decided a few days rest in nearby
            Conforth would do us good before returning to our arduous life on Baker Street. We were
            staying in a small, but comfortable Inn. Only on the morning of the third day, I
            remember,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> and I were in our bedroom waiting for those two essentials without
            which an English country gentleman could not start his day -- an early morning cup of
            tea and a jug of hot water for shaving. As we sat there at the open window a nearby
            church bell was tolling a funeral nell. </ln>

        <ln><sound>Bell tolling in distance</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>There must be a funeral in the village,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>An astonishing deduction,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>There's no need to make fun of me. Impressing sound isn't
            it?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I suppose so. Has it ever occurred to you<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention> that the
            history of bells is full of romantic interest?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well, I can't say that I've thought much about it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Almost every historical event has been accompanied by the sound
            of bells. They summon soldiers to arms, as well as Christians to church. They sounded
            the alarm in 5 ? 2 Multan invasion. And many a bloody chapter in history has been rung
            in and out by bells.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well, you seem to be a mind of information on the subject.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. It's a fascinating subject.</ln>

        <ln><sound>KNOCK at DOOR</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Come in, come in. Good morning, my dear.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker><stageDirect>obvious upset about something</stageDirect> Pardon
            me, gentlemen, I brought your tea and your shaving water. Mrs. Michol said to say your
            breakfast will be ready in half an hour.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Splendid, Marian. Oh, ah, Mary, the church bell is tolling a
            funeral nell. Do you know who's being buried?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker><stageDirect>on the verge of tears</stageDirect> That I do, <mention ref="watson">sir</mention>.
            I wish it was me. It will be my turn soon.</ln>

        <ln><sound>Door CLOSES</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Poor little thing. I wonder what's the matter with her?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I have no idea.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Perhaps her father or mother just died. Or a young man, yes, I
            bet that's it. She's a pretty girl. She'd obviously been crying when she came in.
            Perhaps that's her fiance they're burying now.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker><mention ref="watson">Watson</mention>, you have the sentimental imagination of the true
            storyteller. But we've come here for a holiday. You must give your imagination a rest,
            too. So, drink your tea, remove your whiskers, and we'll go downstairs and investigate
            those kippers.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><sound>CUPS, SAUCERS and general BREAKFAST NOISES under the following.</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> You like your kippers, gentlemen?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Excellent, Mrs. Michol, excellent. Never eaten better.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes, indeed. By the way, Mrs. Michol, we heard the funeral bell
            tolling earlier on. Do you know who was being buried?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Yes, I do. Two souls were being buried. And one of them was a
            murderer.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>A murderer? Lord, in this peaceful village.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>What happened, Mrs. Michol?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Old Threadgold the corn merchant found out his wife had been gallivanting
            around with a young fellow from Bolton. Cut her throat, he did, and then hanged himself.
            More tea?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Thank you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Shocking! So the peaceful countryside is not as peaceful as
            it's made out to be,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Thank that I frequently had occasion to point out to you,
           <mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Has the morning post arrived yet, Mrs. Michol?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Here comes ol' Gilly up the path with it now. I'll see if he's got anything
            for you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>A murder. What do you make of it,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>What is there to make of it,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>? A jealous husband murders
            a faithfuless wife and then commits suicide. A tragic story, but a simple one.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Top of the morning to you, gentlemen.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good morning, Gillian. Any letters for me today?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Aye, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, two letters. One of them's got some newspaper
            clippings in it I think. And you got a postcard from a Mr. Lestrade, he wants you back
            in London bad <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. There you are. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Pardon myself, Gilly, you've been reading <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention> private
            correspondence.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Bless your heart, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. If I didn't read other people's
            correspondence, how would I know what's going on in the village?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Hmm, you were right, Gilly, it is newspaper clippings. And by
            the way, you heard about the murder of Mrs. Threadgold, I suppose?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Heard about it? I tolled the bell this morning at the
            funeral.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Did you say that you're the bell ringer as well as the
            postman?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Bless your heart, yes, <mention ref="watson">Doctor</mention>. President of the Choral
            Society, too, as well as being on the Perries council.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You're a busy man, Gillian.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>That I am, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>. Take this afternoon now. I'm to ring those
            bells again.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Not another funeral, surely?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>No, <mention ref="watson">sir</mention>. A wedding this time.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh, I'm glad to hear it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Young Saint Perry is marrying the Slater girl. And you might
            say I'm responsible for bringing them together. Got some of their letters mixed up I
            did. They looked each other up to exchange them, and, presto, before you know what's
            happening, they're getting married. Regular cupid you might say I am.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Be off with you, Gilly. Other people want their letters. <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention> doesn't
            want his kippers spoiled with your idle chatter.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>All right, Mrs. Crab-Apples-and-Vinegar. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Ahh.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>One of these fine days you'll smile, and the world will come
            to an end. Good day, gentlemen.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Talkative ol' busybody he is. Oh, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, Mrs. Lakland's in the hall.
            The poor old lady is most anxious to talk to you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Mrs. Lakland?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> She has the seamstress shop on the high street. Her only son ran away from
            home a few months back. I think that's what she wants to speak to you about.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh, but my friend's here for a rest, Mrs. Michol.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> I told her that <mention ref="watson">Dr</mention>, but she won't go away without seeing <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Oh, very well. Ask her to come in, please, Mrs. Michol.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MRS. MICHOL</speaker> Yes, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh, I do bother to see her,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>. Sounds like a trivial
            matter. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>The disappearance of an only son can never be a trivial
            matter.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well, I meant trivial for you, not for her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>This is <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, and <mention ref="watson">Doctor Watson</mention>, dear.</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: Thank you, Emmy. Good morning, <mention ref="holmes+watson">sirs</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Good morning.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good morning. Please sit down, Mrs. Lakland. That's it. Now
            what's the trouble?</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: It's Tom, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>. Me only son. He left me four months ago and I've not seen
            heir a night of him since.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You've had no message from him since he left?</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: Not one word, I'm fair out of me mind, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Have you any idea of his reason for leaving the village, Mrs.
            Lakland?</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: None, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>. He was a good boy and he worked hard, and he didn't fool around
            with those flibbity gibbit girls in the village. I think he's met with foul play
            gentlemen, and I want you to find out about him for me, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. I've heard say in
            the village that you're the greatest detective in England.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Mrs. Lakland, I'd be glad to help you, but you've given me no
            clues to work with. I'm afraid that I . . .</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: If it's money you want I've got twenty pounds in me poster savings. It's
            all yours if you can bring my Tommy home to me. Or at least tell me he's safe.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Mrs. Lakland, I wouldn't dream of accepting a fee. However I
            shall give your problem some thought. If I arrive at any conclusions, I'll get in touch
            with you at once.</ln>

        <ln>MRS. LAKLAND: God bless you, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. Good morning to you, <mention ref="holmes+watson">sirs</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good day.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Good morning, Mrs. Lakland. Poor old thing. I don't see how you
            can help her,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Nor do I -- at the moment. But a young man who has grown up in
            a small village like this may have led a life that his mother is totally unaware of. You
            said that you have to work on one of your stories today,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Yes I have a letter from the editor of the Strand magazine
            yesterday requesting a manuscript as soon as possible.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Splendid! Then you must stay at the Inn and work on your latest
            masterpiece, while I scour the village to see what may be found out about the missing
            young man.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><sound>Bells TOLLING in B/G</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>DOOR OPENS</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>There you are,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>! I was beginning to think you got
            lost.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Hello,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. I trust you had a profitable session with pen
            and paper?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>I got about half a chapter. I would have done more if it hadn't
            been for those infernal bells.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>The wedding ceremony that the worthy Gillian told us about this
            morning. Oh, I'm tired.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>What did you find out about Mrs. Lakland's son?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Among other things, that he had a secret love life unknown to
            his mother. And the object of his affections was none other than the maid who brought us
            our tea this morning.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Mary! Did you talk to her?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>No it's her half-day off and I was unable to find her. But I
            shall question her when she brings our tea tomorrow morning.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><sound>KNOCK AT DOOR</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>DOOR OPENS</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Come in, Mary. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh, Mrs. Michol!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>Good morning, gentlemen. Here's your tea and shaving
            water.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Where's Mary this morning?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>She didn't come to work. Must be ill again. Not a reliable
            girl, and no better than she ought to be if you ask me. It's no job for me to be
            carrying tea and hot water upstairs. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I hear the village bell tolling for another funeral. Does
            Conforth have a burial every morning? I really don't see how the population can run to
            it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>It's another suicide, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Another suicide! Good Lord!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>Old John Letterby, the baker. He was expecting some money from
            his son in Australia. It never came, and they foreclosed on his shop. And he hanged
            himself. Will you be wanting a couple of boiled eggs to your breakfast, gentlemen?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>No, no I haven't much of an appetite, thank you very much.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="watson">sir</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>That woman seems absolutely heartless. She almost smacks her
            lips when she tells us about these tragedies.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>, I noticed it. This peaceful village is beginning
            to seem strangely sinister to me. And since you have no appetite for breakfast, perhaps
            you'll join me in a little excursion as soon as you're dressed.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Of course. Where're we going?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>To see the maid, Mary. I'm anxious to talk to her before
            another funeral bell begins to toll.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><sound>CARRIAGE PULLING UP</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>This must be the cottage home. They said it was the one with
            honeysuckle over the gate.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes, and there's Mary sitting on the porch.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>She's got up, she's coming up the path to meet us.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good morning, Mary. I'm sorry you're not feeling well.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker><mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. Why've you come here? Not to ask about my
            health? Why should a servant girl matter to gentlemen like you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh, you misjudged us, my dear. I assure you that we . . .</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>No,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Let's be honest and admit we didn't come here
            because of our concern for Mary's health. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Then why did you come here, <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Mrs. Lakland asked me to try to find her son, Tom.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Tom?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes, Tom Lakland. I thought you might be able to help me,
            Marian.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>If I could help you, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, I'd be helping myself too. Here
            comes Gilly, the postman. </ln>

        <ln><sound>FOOTSTEPS on DIRT </sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Gilly, Gilly, is there a letter for me today?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>No, lass. There's nothing for you again.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>There must, be Gilly, there must be there.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>No, lass. If the letter would come, I'd bring it to you as
            fast as me legs would carry me, you know that. Morning, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. Left
            some letters at the Inn for you, Doctor. You had a letter from a lady.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>How did you know it was from a lady?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Reeked with the smell of violets, it did. And it was written
            in green ink on gray paper, <mention ref="watson">sir</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Amazing deduction.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>That sounds like your young friend from Daylis,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>How did you know about??. I mean, I don't have a young friend
            from Daylis<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Quite. Gilly, you tolled another funeral bell today, didn't
            you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Aye <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>, and a tragic thing it was. Old Letterby hanged
            himself because he didn't get money from his son in Australia. I found him, I did. I was
            the one to cut him down. And right in me post bag was the letter he was waiting for. The
            letter that would have saved his life.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Great Scott! What a ghastly piece of irony.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>That it was, <mention ref="watson">sir</mention>. That it was. Well, gentlemen, I'll be on my
            way. Good day. Good day, Mary. Perhaps that letter will arrive tomorrow.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>No. I'll never hear from Tom, now He's ashamed of me. That's why
            he deserted me.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Deserted you, Mary? You speak almost as if you were his
            wife.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>I am his wife. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>What?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>We were married secretly in Rochdale five months ago come
            Tuesday.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>And he never told his mother?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>He was afraid to. She thought I was beneath him. Tom said he'd go
            away and get a good job and then return here and fetch me back with him. He went away
            all right. But he never came back or sent me a word.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>When he left, did he give no clues to his destination? No hints
            of any kind, Mary?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Wait. He did once say "Mary, I'm gonna clear out to this puddle
            and make me fortune. Even if I have to bury it." And then he said, "Bury me fortune?
            Huh. That's a joke, isn't it?" I don't know what he meant by it.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I think I do, Mary.<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>, we're taking a short train journey
            as soon as possible.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Oh? Where are we going? May I ask?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>We're going to the town of Berry, in search of this young
            lady's husband.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>What makes you think Tom might be in Berry, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Because the famous Fortune Cotton Mills are in Berry. It would
            seem possible that when your husband joked of burying his fortune, he was talking of
            going to the mills there.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Wherever he's gone, he won't be coming back for me. I know
            that.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Now, now, now, now, don't talk like that, my dear. Remember you
            have friends, Mrs. Lakland.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><sound>FACTORY WHISTLE</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>How much longer is<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> going to be? He leaves me standing
            outside the factory gates as if I were a blasted coachman. Ah there he is, there he is!
           <mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>!<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Hello,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Permit me to introduce you to Mr. Tom Lakland.
            Tom, this is <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>How do you do <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>How do you do. Never mind how I do young fellow me lad. How do
            you do? Your behavior has been absolutely shocking. Shocking!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Now what are you talking about?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Leaving your dear old mother and deserting your pretty little
            bride, because you're ashamed of her. You're a scoundrel <mention ref="tome">sir</mention>. You deserve a good
            horsewhipping, and I have a good mind to give it to you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>I don't know what you're talking about <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>, but I don't
            like the words you use. And if it's violence you want, I don't mind telling you that I'm
            amateur heavyweight champion of the county.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>You are? Oh no need to become aggressive.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>No let's waste time on being acrimonious<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Let's get back
            to the station as fast as we can. The return of the prodigal is long overdue. We must
            give them every opportunity to kill the fatted calf.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Ah, there's Mary's house, I'm dying to see her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>And after this reunion, Tom, I suggest that you both go over
            and see your mother. I'm sure she'll forgive you. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, I'll do that.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Perhaps we should've warned her. Your sudden appearance may be
            something of a shock.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>I think it's a shock that Mary can handle. </ln>

        <ln><sound>KNOCKING at DOOR</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>She must be out. The door's locked.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Knock again if you don't mind. She may be asleep. </ln>

        <ln><sound>MORE KNOCKING</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>GUNSHOT </sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Great heavens, that was a revolver shot!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Come on<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>! Help me break in the door!</ln>

        <ln><sound>DOOR BEING BROKEN DOWN</sound></ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>BELL</speaker>Now, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>, that was a fine place to break off your story.
            You left me right on the edge of a cliff. Had the young girl shot herself?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>She'd shot at herself, Mr. Bell, but fortunately her last
            minute lack of courage had made her shot go wild. Homes and I and the young bridegroom
            burst into the house and rescued the smoking revolver from her hand. I must confess the
            reunion between the two young lovers was a touching sight. In fact, I felt considerably
            older than I was as<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention> and I stood there listening to Tom reassuring her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Mary, darling, it's all right. I'm here.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Oh, Tom ,you are. You did come back for me. I thought you never
            would. I tried to kill myself but I hadn't the courage.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Oh there, there, Mary. Everything's going to be all right
            now.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>It will be, Tom, won't it? Oh, I'm so tired.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>And now, Tom, I think the time has come to reassure Mary that
            you did write to her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Of course I did Mary, darling. I sent you money and told you that
            I'd be back here to take you to Berry as soon as I'd saved up enough.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>You wrote to me, Tom?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Twice a week. And I wrote to mother, too. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Then why didn't I get the letters?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>The answer to that should be obvious my dear. Gilly the postman
            deliberately withheld them from you.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Gilly?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Great heavens! Why?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I have my suspicions. Strong suspicions. But I have to get
            proof. Tell me Mary, the day before yesterday, Mr. Threadgold murdered his wife. Do you
            know how he learned of her infidelity?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MARY</speaker>Well, I'm not sure, but I did heard Mrs. Michol say it was
            through some letters that got mixed up. The letters addressed to her were delivered to
            his office instead of at the house.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Gilly again.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Precisely! Surely the whole terrible pattern begins to take
            shape. Tom?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I'm going to lay a trap. To spring it I shall need your
            assistance.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Of course, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, I'll do anything. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Wait here with Mary until darkness falls. Then muffle
            yourselves up and go to your mother's house. Wait there in hiding and let no outsiders
            see you until you hear from me.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Since you two love birds have been separated for four months I
            don't imagine that will be too unpleasant.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Quiet,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. You understand, Tom?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>TOM</speaker>Yes, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good. Come on,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>What's your plan,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I'll tell you as we go. One thing I can promise you. Before the
            sun is very high tomorrow I shall free this village from one of the most subtly evil
            powers I've ever come in contact with.</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>Good Morning, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Good morning, Mrs. Michol.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good morning.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>I always said that Mary was a no good girl. And now she's
            killed herself, but of course I had to come to her funeral.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>That's very chaitable, Mrs. Michol, I must say, in any case the
            vicar says that the poor girl was of unsound mind.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Yes, madam, you can't blame her.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>MICHOL</speaker>Well, I'll be getting into the church.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Holmes this farce is beginning to get on my nerves. What are we
            accomplishing by burying an empty coffin?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You'll soon see, <mention ref="watson">old chap</mention> Come on. Let's slip into the vestry.
            This way.</ln>

        <ln><sound>BELLS TOLLING throughout</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>DOOR OPENS</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>TWO SETS of FOOTSTEPS</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Where're we going, Homes?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Up the stairs that lead to the belfry. Here they are.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well supposing Gilly turns nasty when he finds out we know his
            secret.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Then we must handle him to the best of our ability,
           <mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well I must say I do not relish the thought of a tussle high in
            the belfry of a church. The man must be insane.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Obviously. That's why his power must be destroyed. This door
            apparently leads to the belfry. Keep your wits about you<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><sound>SQUEAKY DOOR OPENS</sound></ln>

        <ln><sound>BELLS GET LOUDER as they enter the belfry</sound></ln>

        <ln><stageDirect>they all shout over the bells</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Good morning, Gilly.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker><mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>. You've come to see me at work. That's
            nice of ya. Not often I get company up here. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>We haven't come up here to see you at work, Gilly. We know your
            diabolical work only too well.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Yes, Gilly, we know your secret.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>What secret's that?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You're mad with power, Gilly. You've tried to control the
            destiny of this village. In your position as postman you thought you have the power to
            give life and death.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>That I am <mention ref="holmes">sir</mention>, and it's a great power. It makes a man feel
            good. Almost like a god you might say.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>That's sacrilege you scoundrel. You were responsible for the
            murder of Mrs. Threadgold.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Aye <mention ref="gillian">sir</mention>. That I was, and for the old man hanging himself.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You were responsible for John Letterby's suicide weren't
            you?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>That I was. Letterby tried to vote me off the village council.
            I swore I'd make him pay for it. And I did.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Your reign is over Gillian. You'll never toll a bell again. The
            only one you'll hear will be a prison bell.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>You can't touch me, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. You've got no proof. There's
            nothing you can do.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Don't be too sure. I have enough influence to take your job
            away.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>You, you, You'd take me away from me bells? I live for these
            bells. You wouldn't take me away from them?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You couldn't live without the power they give you. Could you,
            Gilly?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>You're trying to destroy me. </ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You are already destroyed, Gilly.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Yes, you've already failed. Mary's alive.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>A-Alive? But the coffin they're burying down there?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Is full of stone. You'll be the laughing stock of the village,
            Gilly.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>They'll never laugh at Gilly. <stageDirect>fade off
                mic</stageDirect> You can't catch me, <mention ref="holmes">Mr. Holmes</mention>. I'm beyond you still!</ln>

        <ln><sound>Gilly running up a SQUEAKY LADDER</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>He's running up the ladder leading to the bell tower.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Come back, Gilly, come back!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>He's mad as a hatter.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Quite.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>What's he going to do up there? He might set fire to the
            steeple. Could make any madness. I'm going to fetch him,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>No,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. He drew a knife as he fled. And with that rickety
            staircase and the narrow opening leading into the bell chamber you'd never stand a
            chance. He'd get you on the first ledge.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>How're we going to get him down?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>There's only one way. He's in a tiny loft containing his
            beloved bells. We'll see how much he loves them at close quarters. I doubt if even he
            can stand the noise in that confined space. Where's that bell rope?</ln>

        <ln><sound>BELLS begin to TOLL LOUDLY</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Come down, Gilly. Come down from there.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Stop! Stop ringing me bell!</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>Not until you come down, Gilly.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>Stop ringing them! I can't stand it. You'll make me mad.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>You are mad, Gilly. Mad with power. Come down here I say.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>GILLIAN</speaker>I'm coming! <stageDirect>Gilly screams as he jumps from the
                tower</stageDirect></ln>

        <ln><sound>BODY THUD TO GROUND</sound></ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Great Heavens, he hurled himself out of the belfry.<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>, he
            hasn't the chance of surviving that fall.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>I had no intention of causing that unhappy man to jump to his
            death,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Though I can't help but feel that his poor, demented mind may find a
            happier oblivion this way rather than in the confines of an asylum.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Yes, you're probably right,<mention ref="holmes"> Holmes</mention>.</ln>

        <ln><speaker>HOLMES</speaker>It's been a shocking case,<mention ref="watson"> Watson</mention>. Shocking. And once again it
            proves the old saying that "violence does intrude recoil upon the violent." And, "the
            schemer falls into the pit which he digs for another."</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>BELL</speaker>Now, <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention>, what about next week?</ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>Well, now let me see, what's left in here. Next week I'll tell
            you a rather gruesome story about how <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention> saved the life and the sanity of a
            certain Count Ramanea. I call it "The Adventure of the Carpethean Horror."</ln>

        <ln><music>UP AND OUT</music></ln>

        <ln><speaker>ANNOUNCER</speaker>Tonight's new <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention> adventure was suggested by an
            incident in Sir Arthur Conan Doyle's story, The Golden Pince Nez. The <mention ref="holmes">Sherlock Holmes</mention>'s
            series is produced by Tom McNight with original music composed and conducted by Alex
            Steiner. This is Joseph Bell speaking for Cramel Hair Tonic and Cramel Shampoo, and
            inviting you to be with us next week at this same time when <mention ref="watson">Dr. Watson</mention> will tell us . .
            . </ln>

        <ln><speaker>WATSON</speaker>The Adventure of the Carpethean Horror.</ln>
    </script>
</xml>
