<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <movie>
            <title>Casablanca</title>
            <director>Michael Curtiz</director>
            <wrldPrem>Nov. 26 1942</wrldPrem>
            <loc>WB studios, Burbank, CA</loc>
            <loc>Van Nuys Airport, LA</loc>
            <producer>Hal B. Wallis</producer>
            <producer>Warner Bros</producer>
            <writer>Howard Koch</writer>
            <writer>Julius J. Epstein</writer>
            <writer>Philip G. Epstein</writer>
            <basedOn>Everybody Comes to Rick’s (stage play); written by Murray Burnett and Joan
                Alison</basedOn>
            <composer>Max Steiner</composer>
            <starring>Humphrey Bogart</starring>
            <starring>Ingrid Bergman</starring>
            <starring>Paul Henreid</starring>
            <starring>Conrad Veidt</starring>
            <starring>Claude Rains</starring>
            <cinematography>Arthur Edeson</cinematography>
            <editor>Owen Marks</editor>
        </movie>
        <script>
            <numScenes>77</numScenes>
            <url>https://app.studiobinder.com/company/580e85847e7982164664e844/collab/5eac35a683f7a90bfc3fc810/projects/5de590454f452c09a98e975b/document/5de5904f1fe52b06c2f4bd79/%5Bobject%20Object%5D?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=sb-app-link&amp;utm_campaign=script&amp;utm_term=casablanca-script-breakdown&amp;utm_content=full-script-pdf-download</url>
            <generatedBy>Brent Dunham</generatedBy>
            <date>Dec. 2</date>
            <publisher>StudioBinder Inc.</publisher>
            <website> https://www.studiobinder.com/</website>
        </script>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <scene n="22">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT Ilsa and Laszlo leave the cafe. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> A very puzzling fellow, this Rick. What sort is he? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa doesn't look at him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, I really can't say, though I saw him quite often in Paris.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They join Renault at the curb. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Tomorrow at ten at the Prefect's office. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We'll be there. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They get into a waiting cab, leaving Renault on the curb, smoking and looking
                bemused. The neon sign goes off and the doorway is now illuminated by the revolving
                beacon from the airport. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="23">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT The customers have all gone. The house
                lights are out. Rick sits alone at a table. There is a glass of bourbon on the table
                directly in front of him, and another empty glass on the table before an empty
                chair. Near at hand is a bottle. He fills his glass and drinks it quickly. Rick just
                sits. His face is entirely expressionless. The beacon light from the airport sweeps
                around the room creating a mood of unreality. Sam comes in and stands hesitantly
                beside Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Boss.</diag>
                <dir> No answer, as Rick drinks. </dir>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Boss! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Boss, ain't you going to bed? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Not right now.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam now realizes Rick is in a very grim mood. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>lightly</descr> Ain't you planning on going to bed in the near future?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> You ever going to bed? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I ain't sleepy either. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Good. Then have a drink. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> No. Not me, boss. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Then don't have a drink. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Boss, let's get out of here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>emphatically</descr> No, sir. I'm waiting for a lady. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>earnestly</descr> Please, boss, let's go. Ain't nothing but trouble for
                    you here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> She's coming back. I know she's coming back. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> We'll take the car and drive all night. We'll get drunk. We'll go fishing and
                    stay away until she's gone. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Shut up and go home, will you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>stubbornly</descr> No, sir. I'm staying right here.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam sits down at the piano and starts to play softly, improvising. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> They grab Ugarte and she walks in. Well, that's the way it goes. One in, one
                    out. Sam? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah, boss? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sam, if it's December 1941 in Casablanca, what time is it in New York?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Uh, my watch stopped. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I bet they're asleep in New York. I'll bet they're asleep all over America.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Suddenly he pounds the table and buries his head in his arms. Then he raises his
                head, trying to regain control. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Of all the gin joints in all the towns in all the world, she walks into
                    mine.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He holds his head in his hands. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> What's that you're playing? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Just a little something of my own. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, stop it. You know what I want to hear. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> No, I don't. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You played it for her and you can play it for me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I don't think I can remember it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> If she can stand it, I can. Play it! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, boss. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam starts to play "As Time Goes By." Rick just stares ahead as orchestra MUSIC
                slowly joins Sam's playing. </dir>
        </scene>
        <dir><camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera> MONTAGE - PARIS IN THE SPRING A) The Arc de Triomphe from
            a distance. B) Rick drives a small, open car slowly along the boulevard. He puts his arm
            around Ilsa. The background scenery changes to a country road as she snuggles close to
            him and puts her head on his shoulder. C) An excursion boat on the Seine. Rick and Ilsa
            stand at the rail of the boat. They seem to be transported by each other as Ilsa laughs. </dir>
        <scene n="25">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S PARIS APARTMENT - DAY Ilsa fixes flowers at the window while Rick
                opens champagne. She walks over and joins him. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Who are you really? And what were you before? What did you do and what did
                    you think? Huh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> We said "no questions." </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Here's looking at you, kid.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They drink. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="26">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. PARIS CAFE - NIGHT Inside a swank Paris cafe, Rick and Ilsa dance. They
                appear to be very much in love as the MUSIC plays. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="27">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. ILSA'S PARIS APARTMENT - DAY Ilsa flips a coin, then tosses it over to
                Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> A franc for your thoughts. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> In America they'd bring only a penny. I guess that's about all they're worth.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I'm willing to be overcharged. Tell me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And I was wondering. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why I'm so lucky. Why I should find you waiting for me to come along. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Why there is no other man in my life? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Uh huh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> That's easy. There was. He's dead. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry for asking. I forgot we said "no questions." </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Well, only one answer can take care of all our questions. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They kiss passionately.</dir>
        </scene>
        <dir><camera>CUT TO:</camera> MONTAGE - NEWSREEL FOOTAGE OF THE GERMAN OCCUPATION OF FRANCE.
            A) The rubble of a burned-out, demolished building. A sign with an arrow points to
            Paris. B) German troops crossing a river. C) Tanks rolling down the road toward Paris.
            D) German war planes overhead. </dir>
        <scene n="29">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. PARIS CAFE - DAY A man sells newspapers to people crowded around him.
                There is much excitement. Rick and Ilsa sit at a table. They buy a newspaper and
                begin to read it. Nearby, a group of frightened French people cluster around a
                loudspeaker on a wagon. A harsh voice barks out the tragic news of the Nazi push
                toward Paris. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Nothing can stop them now. Wednesday, Thursday at the latest, they'll be in
                    Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>frightened</descr> Richard, they'll find out your record. It won't be
                    safe for you here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm on their blacklist already, their roll of honor. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="30">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. LA BELLE AURORE - AFTERNOON A small cafe in the Montmartre. A shadow on
                the floor reflects the cafe sign "La Belle Aurore." Rick, at the bar, gets glasses
                and a bottle of champagne. He walks over to Ilsa and Sam at the piano. Sam plays "As
                Time Goes By." Ilsa seems unnerved. There is evidently something on her mind. Rick
                pours the champagne. His manner is wry, but not the bitter wryness we have seen in
                Casablanca. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Henri wants us to finish this bottle and then three more. He says he'll water
                    his garden with champagne before he'll let the Germans drink any of it.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam looks at his glass. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> This sort of takes the sting out of being occupied, doesn't it, Mr. Richard?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You said it! <dir>to Ilsa</dir> Here's looking at you, kid. </diag>
            </sp>
            <setting>Suddenly a loudspeaker BLARES out something in German.</setting>
            <dir>Rick and Ilsa look at each other, then hurry to the window.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My German's a little rusty. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It's the Gestapo. They say they expect to be in Paris tomorrow. They are
                    telling us how to act when they come marching in.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She smiles faintly. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> With the whole world crumbling, we pick this time to fall in love. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah. It's pretty bad timing. Where were you, say, ten years ago? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Ten years ago? Let's see-- <dir>pause as she thinks a bit</dir> --Yes. I was
                    having a brace put on my teeth. Where were you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Looking for a job.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa looks at him tenderly. Rick takes her in his arms, and kisses her hungrily.
                While they are locked in an embrace they hear the dull BOOM of cannons. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>frightened</descr> Was that cannon fire, or is it my heart pounding?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>grimly</descr> Ah, that's the new German 77. And judging by the sound,
                    only about thirty-five miles away. </diag>
            </sp>
            <setting> Another BOOM from the cannons.</setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And getting closer every minute. Here. Drink up. We'll never finish the other
                    three. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> The Germans'll be here pretty soon now, and they'll come looking for you. And
                    don't forget there's a price on your head.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa reacts to this worriedly. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I left a note in my apartment. They'll know where to find me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa looks at Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Strange. I know so very little about you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I know very little about you, just the fact that you had your teeth
                    straightened. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He chuckles. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> But be serious, darling. You are in danger and you must leave Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No, no, no, no. We must leave. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>seriously</descr> Yes, of course, we -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- The train for Marseilles leaves at five o'clock. I'll pick you up at your
                    hotel at four-thirty. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>quickly</descr> No, no. Not at my hotel. I, uh, I have things to do in
                    the city before I leave. I'll meet you at the station, huh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All right. At a quarter to five. <dir>a thought strikes him</dir> Say, why
                    don't we get married in Marseilles?</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick chuckles again. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>evasively</descr> That's too far ahead to plan. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I guess it is a little too far ahead. Well, let's see. What about the
                    engineer? Why can't he marry us on the train? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, darling! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Suddenly Ilsa turns away and starts to cry.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, why not? The captain on a ship can. It doesn't seem fair that-- Hey,
                    hey, what's wrong, kid? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I love you so much, and I hate this war so much. Oh, it's a crazy world.
                    Anything can happen. If you shouldn't get away, I mean, if, if something should
                    keep us apart, wherever they put you and wherever I'll be, I want you to know--
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She can't go on. She lifts her face to his. He kisses her gently. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Kiss me. Kiss me as if it were the last time.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He looks into her eyes, then he does kiss her as though it were going to be the
                last time. Her hand falls to the table and knocks over a glass. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="31">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. GARE DE LYON - NIGHT It's raining very hard at the train station. There is
                a hectic, fevered excitement, evident in the faces of the people that pass by. This
                is the last train from Paris. Rick appears in the crowd. He stops and puts his
                suitcase down and glances at his watch. A conductor calls out "All aboard, last
                train leaving in three minutes." Rain pours over his head and shoulders, but he
                doesn't seem to notice. He nervously checks his watch again. Suddenly Sam appears. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Where is she? Have you seen her? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> No, Mr. Richard. I can't find her. She checked out of the hotel. But this
                    note came just after you left.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam pulls an envelope from his pocket. Rick grabs it, opens it, and stares down at
                the letter. </dir>
            <dir>INSERT LETTER Richard, I cannot go with you or ever see you again. You must not ask
                why. Just believe that I love you. Go, my darling, and God bless you. Ilsa </dir>
            <setting> Raindrops pour down the letter, smudging the writing. </setting>
            <dir>BACK TO SCENE</dir>
            <setting> A whistle BLOWS. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>frantically</descr> That's the last call, Mr. Richard, do you hear me?
                    Come on, Mr. Richard. Let's get out of here. Come on, Mr. Richard, come
                    on.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam pulls a stunned, reluctant Rick to the train. The train starts to move just as
                he boards. From the steps he looks off into the distance, then crumbles the letter
                and tosses it away as the steam from the engine clouds over him. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="34">
            <camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Close-up of a glass on the table in the
                cafe. Rick's hand reaches for it and knocks it over. We now see Rick's face and he's
                very drunk. Sam walks over to the table to pick up the glass and a fallen chair.
                Just then the door opens and it's Ilsa. Rick stares at the doorway. Ilsa lingers a
                moment, then comes over to the table. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, I have to talk to you.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Her manner is a little uncertain, a little tentative, but with a quiet
                determination beneath it. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. I saved my first drink to have with you. Here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> No. No, Rick. Not tonight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Especially tonight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She sits down in the chair before the empty glass. Her eyes are searching his
                face, but there is no expression on it except a cold and impassive one. Rick reaches
                for the bottle, and pours himself another drink.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why did you have to come to Casablanca? There are other places. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I wouldn't have come if I had known that you were here. Believe me, Rick,
                    it's true. I didn't know. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It's funny about your voice, how it hasn't changed. I can still hear it.
                    "Richard dear, I'll go with you any place. We'll get on a train together and
                    never stop." </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Please don't. Don't, Rick. I can understand how you feel. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Huh! You understand how I feel. How long was it we had, honey? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I didn't count the days. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I did. Every one of them. Mostly I remember the last one. A wow finish.
                    A guy standing on a station platform in the rain with a comical look on his
                    face, because his insides had been kicked out. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He takes a drink.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Can I tell you a story, Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Has it got a wow finish? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I don't know the finish yet. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, go on, tell it. Maybe one will come to you as you go along. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It's about a girl who had just come to Paris from her home in Oslo. At the
                    house of some friends she met a man about whom she'd heard her whole life, a
                    very great and courageous man. He opened up for her a whole beautiful world full
                    of knowledge and thoughts and ideals. Everything she knew or ever became was
                    because of him. And she looked up to him and worshipped him with a feeling she
                    supposed was love. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, that's very pretty. I heard a story once. As a matter of fact, I've
                    heard a lot of stories in my time. They went along with the sound of a tinny
                    piano playing in the parlor downstairs, "Mister, I met a man once when I was a
                    kid," it'd always begin. Huh. I guess neither one of our stories was very funny.
                    Tell me, who was it you left me for? Was it Laszlo, or were there others in
                    between? Or aren't you the kind that tells? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa gets up and leaves. Rick's head slumps over the table. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="35">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RENAULT'S OFFICE - MORNING A sign on the door reads: Captain Renault,
                Prefect de Police. Strasser sits while Renault attends to some paperwork. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I strongly suspect that Ugarte left the letters of transit with Mr. Blaine. I
                    would suggest you search the cafe immediately and thoroughly. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> If Rick has the letters, he's much too smart to let you find them there.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You give him credit for too much cleverness. My impression was that he's just
                    another blundering American. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> But we mustn't underestimate American blundering. I was with them when they
                    "blundered" into Berlin in 1918. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Strasser looks at him.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> As to Laszlo, we want him watched twenty-four hours a day. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>reassuringly</descr> It may interest you to know that at this very moment
                    he is on his way here. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="36">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. PREFECTURE LOBBY - MORNING Laszlo and Ilsa make their way through the jam
                in the lobby of the Prefecture. Jan and Annina talk to an officer. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="off">OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Jan and Annina</dir> There's nothing we can do. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="37">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RENAULT'S OFFICE - MORNING Laszlo and Ilsa enter Renault's office. Renault
                bows to them both. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I am delighted to see you both. Did you have a good night's rest? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I slept very well. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> That's strange. Nobody is supposed to sleep well in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>coldly</descr> May we proceed with the business? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> With pleasure. Won't you sit down? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They take their seats. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>now as cold as Laszlo</descr> Very well, Herr Laszlo, we will not mince
                    words. You are an escaped prisoner of the Reich. So far you have been fortunate
                    enough in eluding us. You have reached Casablanca. It is my duty to see that you
                    stay in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Whether or not you succeed is, of course, problematical. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Not at all. Captain Renault's signature is necessary on every exit visa.
                        <dir>turns to Renault</dir> Captain, would you think it is possible that
                    Herr Laszlo will receive a visa? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I am afraid not. My regrets, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Well, perhaps I shall like it in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> And Mademoiselle? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You needn't be concerned about me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Is that all you wish to tell us? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Don't be in such a hurry. You have all the time in the world. You may be in
                    Casablanca indefinitely-- or you may leave for Lisbon tomorrow, on one
                    condition. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> And that is? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You know the leaders of the underground movement in Paris, in Prague, in
                    Brussels, in Amsterdam, in Oslo, in Belgrade, in Athens. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Even in Berlin. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, even in Berlin. If you will furnish me with their names and their exact
                    whereabouts, you will have your visa in the morning. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> And the honor of having served the Third Reich. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I was in a German concentration camp for a year. That's honor enough for a
                    lifetime. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You will give us the names? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> If I didn't give them to you in a concentration camp where you had more
                    "persuasive methods" at your disposal, I certainly won't give them to you now.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The passionate conviction in his voice now reveals the crusader.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> And what if you track down these men and kill them? What if you murdered all
                    of us? From every corner of Europe, hundreds, thousands, would rise to take our
                    places. Even Nazis can't kill that fast. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Herr Laszlo, you have a reputation for eloquence which I can now understand.
                    But in one respect you are mistaken. You said the enemies of the Reich could all
                    be replaced, but there is one exception. No one could take your place in the
                    event anything unfortunate should occur to you while you were trying to escape.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> You won't dare to interfere with me here. This is still unoccupied France.
                    Any violation of neutrality would reflect on Captain Renault. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur, insofar as it is in my power -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> -- Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> By the way, Monsieur, last night you evinced an interest in Signor Ugarte.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I believe you have a message for him? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Nothing important, but may I speak to him now? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You would find the conversation a trifle one-sided. Signor Ugarte is dead.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Close-ups of Ilsa, then Laszlo, reveal their disappointment. Strasser observes
                their reaction. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>softly</descr> Oh. Renault holds a report. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I am making out the report now. We haven't quite decided whether he committed
                    suicide or died trying to escape. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Are you quite finished with us? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> For the time being. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Good day.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault rings a buzzer and the door is opened for them. As Ilsa and Laszlo leave,
                an OFFICER comes in. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Undoubtedly their next step will be to the black market. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="off">OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> Excuse me, Captain. Another visa problem has come up. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Show her in. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="off">OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, sir.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault looks at himself in the mirror and straightens his tie. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="38">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. BLACK MARKET - DAY The black market is a cluttered Arab street of bazaars,
                shops and stalls. All kinds and races of people mill about the merchandise which
                native dealers have on outdoor display. Both men and women are dressed in tropical
                clothes. The canopies over the stalls give them some protection from the scorching
                sun. On the surface the atmosphere is merely languid, but underneath lies the
                sinister workings of illicit trade. A FRENCHMAN and a NATIVE huddle together and
                talk in low tones. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="nat">NATIVE</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry, Monsieur, we would have to handle the police. This is a job for
                    Signor Ferrari. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fre">FRENCHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Ferrari? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="nat">NATIVE</speaker>
                <diag> It can be most helpful to know Signor Ferrari. He pretty near has a monopoly
                    on the black market here. You will find him over there at the Blue Parrot.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fre">FRENCHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Thanks. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="39">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY Outside the cafe, a blue parrot sits on a perch.
            </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="40">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY The cafe is much less pretentious than Rick's, but
                well populated. Rick enters and walks through the cafe toward Ferrari's office just
                as Ferrari emerges with Jan and Annina, who look very disappointed. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> There, don't be too downhearted. Perhaps you can come to terms with Captain
                    Renault. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you very much, Signor. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Jan leads Annina away.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Ferrari.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Signor Ferrari turns around. He's pleased to see Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Ah, good morning, Rick.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They shake hands. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I see the bus is in. I'll take my shipment with me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> No hurry. I'll have it sent over. Have a drink with me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I never drink in the morning. And every time you send my shipment over, it's
                    always just a little bit short. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>chuckling</descr> Carrying charges, my boy, carrying charges. Here, sit
                    down. There's something I want to talk over with you, anyhow.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He hails a waiter. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> The bourbon. <dir>to Rick, sighing deeply</dir> The news about Ugarte upset
                    me very much. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You're a fat hypocrite. You don't feel any sorrier for Ugarte than I
                    do.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He eyes Rick closely. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Of course not. What upsets me is the fact that Ugarte is dead and no one
                    knows where those letters of transit are. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Practically no one. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> If I could lay my hands on those letters, I could make a fortune. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> So could I. And I'm a poor businessman. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> I have a proposition for whoever has those letters. I will handle the entire
                    transaction, get rid of the letters, take all the risk, for a small percentage.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And the carrying charges? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Naturally there will be a few incidental expenses. That is the proposition I
                    have for whoever has those letters. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>dryly</descr> I'll tell him when he comes in. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, I'll put my cards on the table. I think you know where those letters
                    are. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, you're in good company. Renault and Strasser probably think so,
                    too.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick looks out of the window and sees Ilsa at the linen bazaar, then Laszlo
                walking toward the cafe. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> That's why I came over here to give them a chance to ransack my place.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, don't be a fool. Take me into your confidence. You need a
                    partner.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick isn't listening to him. He looks through the open window in the direction of
                the linen bazaar. Rick gets up. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Excuse me, I'll be getting back. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="41">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY Laszlo reaches the entrance to the cafe as Rick
                comes out. He stops and addresses Rick politely. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Good morning. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Signor Ferrari is the fat gent at the table.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> As he exits, Laszlo looks after him with a puzzled expression. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="42">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. BLACK MARKET - DAY At the linen stall, Ilsa examines a tablecloth which an
                Arab vendor is endeavoring to sell. He holds a sign which reads "700 francs." </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="arab">ARAB</speaker>
                <diag> You will not find a treasure like this in all Morocco, Mademoiselle. Only
                    seven hundred francs.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick walks up behind Ilsa. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You're being cheated.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She looks briefly at Rick, then turns away. Her manner is politely formal. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It doesn't matter, thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="arab">ARAB</speaker>
                <diag> Ah, the lady is a friend of Rick's? For friends of Rick we have a small
                    discount. Did I say seven hundred francs? You can have it for two
                    hundred.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Reaching under the counter, he takes out a sign reading "200 francs", and replaces
                the other sign with it. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry I was in no condition to receive you when you called on me last
                    night. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It doesn't matter. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="arab">ARAB</speaker>
                <diag> Ah, for special friends of Rick's we have a special discount. One hundred
                    francs. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He replaces the second sign with a third which reads "100 francs." </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Your story had me a little confused. Or maybe it was the bourbon. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="arab">ARAB</speaker>
                <diag> I have some tablecloths, some napkins -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> -- Thank you. I'm really not interested. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="arab">ARAB</speaker>
                <diag> Please, one minute. Wait! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The Arab hurriedly exits. Ilsa pretends to examine the goods on the counter.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why did you come back? To tell me why you ran out on me at the railway
                    station? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, you can tell me now. I'm reasonably sober. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I don't think I will, Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why not? After all, I got stuck with a railway ticket. I think I'm entitled
                    to know. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Last night I saw what has happened to you. The Rick I knew in Paris, I could
                    tell him. He'd understand. But the one who looked at me with such hatred-- well,
                    I'll be leaving Casablanca soon and we'll never see each other again. We knew
                    very little about each other when we were in love in Paris. If we leave it that
                    way, maybe we'll remember those days and not Casablanca, not last night. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Did you run out on me because you couldn't take it? Because you knew what it
                    would be like, hiding from the police, running away all the time? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You can believe that if you want to. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I'm not running away any more. I'm settled now, above a saloon, it's
                    true, but-- walk up a flight. I'll be expecting you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa turns her head away. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All the same, someday you'll lie to Laszlo. You'll be there. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> No, Rick. No, you see, Victor Laszlo is my husband-- and was, even when I
                    knew you in Paris.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She walks away into the cafe as Rick stares after her in stunned disbelief. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="43">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY Ilsa and Laszlo sit with Ferrari. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> I was just telling Monsieur Laszlo that, unfortunately, I am not able to help
                    him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> You see, my dear, the word has gone around. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Ilsa</dir> As leader of all illegal activities in Casablanca, I am an
                    influential and respected man. It would not be worth my life to do anything for
                    Monsieur Laszlo. You, however, are a different matter. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Signor Ferrari thinks it might just be possible to get an exit visa for you.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You mean for me to go on alone? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> And only alone. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I will stay here and keep on trying. I'm sure in a little while -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> -- We might as well be frank, Monsieur. It will take a miracle to get you out
                    of Casablanca. And the Germans have outlawed miracles. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> We are only interested in two visas, Signor. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Please, Ilsa, don't be hasty. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>firmly</descr> No, Victor, no. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> You two will want to discuss this. Excuse me. I'll be at the bar. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ferrari gets to his feet and walks away.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> No, Ilsa, I won't let you stay here. You must get to America. And believe me,
                    somehow I will get out and join you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> But, Victor, if the situation were different, if I had to stay and there were
                    only a visa for one, would you take it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>not very convincingly</descr> Yes, I would. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa smiles faintly. She doesn't believe it for even a moment.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I see. When I had trouble getting out of Lille, why didn't you leave me
                    there? And when I was sick in Marseilles and held you up for two weeks and you
                    were in danger every minute of the time, why didn't you leave me then? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I meant to, but something always held me up. I love you very much,
                    Ilsa.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She smiles again. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Your secret will be safe with me. Ferrari is waiting for our answer. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>At the bar Ferrari talks to a waiter.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Not more than fifty francs though. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa and Laszlo walk up to him.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We've decided, Signor Ferrari. For the present we'll go on looking for two
                    exit visas. Thank you very much. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Well, good luck. But be careful. <dir>a flick of his eyes in the direction of
                        the bazaar</dir> You know you're being shadowed? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo glances in the direction of the bazaar. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Of course. It becomes an instinct. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ferrari looks shrewdly at Ilsa.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> I observe that you in one respect are a very fortunate man, Monsieur. I am
                    moved to make one more suggestion, why, I do not know, because it cannot
                    possibly profit me, but, have you heard about Signor Ugarte and the letters of
                    transit? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, something. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Those letters were not found on Ugarte when they arrested him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> There's a moments pause as this sinks in.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Do you know where they are? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Not for sure, Monsieur, but I will venture to guess that Ugarte left those
                    letters with Monsieur Rick.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa's face darkens. Laszlo quietly observes. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> He is a difficult customer, that Rick. One never knows what he'll do or why.
                    But it is worth a chance. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you very much. Good day. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Goodbye, thank you for your coffee, Signor. I shall miss that when we leave
                    Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ferrari bows.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> It was gracious of you to share it with me. Good day, Mademoiselle, Monsieur.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Good day.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> As Ilsa and Laszlo leave the cafe, Ferrari nonchalantly swats a fly on a table.
            </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="44">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT Outside Rick's cafe, the sign is lit up and MUSIC
                filters out into the air. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="45">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT At the bar, the European has found another
                TOURIST. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Here's to you, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="tou">TOURIST</speaker>
                <diag> Er, good luck, yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> I'd better be going. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="tou">TOURIST</speaker>
                <diag> Er, my check, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> I have to warn you, sir. I beseech you--</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The European picks his pocket. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> This is a dangerous place, full of vultures. Vultures everywhere! Thanks for
                    everything. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The tourist laughs.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="tou">TOURIST</speaker>
                <diag> Er, goodbye, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> It has been a pleasure to meet you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He dashes off and collides with Carl.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, I'm sorry. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As the European hurries away, Carl checks all his pockets to make sure nothing is
                missing. Sam and Corina play a number, accompanied by the orchestra. Strasser and
                his crowd enter the cafe and pass Rick's table. Carl brings Rick a bottle and glass. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick, you are getting to be your best customer. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Carl leaves. As Rick lights a cigarette, Renault shows up.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, Ricky. I'm very pleased with you. Now you're beginning to live like a
                    Frenchman. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> That was some going-over your men gave my place this afternoon. We just
                    barely got cleaned up in time to open.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He pours a drink for Renault. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I told Strasser he wouldn't find the letters here. But I told my men to
                    be especially destructive. You know how that impresses Germans?<dir> taking a
                        sip</dir> Rick, have you got these letters of transit? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Louis, are you pro-Vichy or Free French? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Serves me right for asking a direct question. The subject is closed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, it looks like you're a little late. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Huh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick gazes at Yvonne and a GERMAN OFFICER approaching the bar.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> So Yvonne's gone over to the enemy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Who knows? In her own way she may constitute an entire second front. I think
                    it's time for me to flatter Major Strasser a little. I'll see you later, Rick.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault gets up and strolls away. At the bar, Yvonne and the German officer place
                their orders. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Sacha! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="goff">GERMAN OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> French seventy-fives. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Yvonne is somewhat drunk already.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Put up a whole row of them, Sacha-- starting here and ending here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She indicates with her hand where she wants them.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="goff">GERMAN OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> We will begin with two. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> A FRENCH OFFICER at the bar makes a remark to Yvonne.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> Say, you, you are not French to go with a German like this!
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> What are you butting in for? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> I am butting in -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>breaking in, in French </dir>-- It's none of your business! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="goff">GERMAN OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French </dir>No, no, no, no! One minute! <dir>in English</dir> What did
                    you say? Would you kindly repeat it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> What I said is none of your business! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="goff">GERMAN OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> I will make it my business! They begin to fight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> Stop! I beg of you! I beg of you, stop! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>There are exclamations from people nearby. German officers at a nearby table rise,
                ready to join in. Rick walks up and separates the two men. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to the German</dir> I don't like disturbances in my place. Either lay off
                    politics or get out. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> Dirty Boche. Someday we'll have our revenge! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault, Strasser and the other officers sit down again.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You see, Captain, the situation is not as much under control as you believe.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> My dear Major, we are trying to cooperate with your government, but we cannot
                    regulate the feelings of our people. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Strasser eyes him closely. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Renault, are you entirely certain which side you're on? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I have no conviction, if that's what you mean. I blow with the wind, and the
                    prevailing wind happens to be from Vichy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> And if it should change? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He smiles. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Surely the Reich doesn't admit that possibility? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault lights a cigarette and puffs away.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> We are concerned about more than Casablanca. We know that every French
                    province in Africa is honey-combed with traitors waiting for their chance,
                    waiting, perhaps, for a leader. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>casually</descr> A leader, like Laszlo? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Uh, huh. I have been thinking. It is too dangerous if we let him go. It may
                    be too dangerous if we let him stay. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>thoughtfully</descr> I see what you mean. Carl, bottle in hand,
                    approaches the table of a middle-aged German couple, the LEUCHTAGS. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in German</dir> I brought you the finest brandy. Only the employees drink
                    it here.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He pours a drink for each of them.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG </speaker>
                <diag>Thank you, Carl.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>as he pours</dir> For Mrs. Leuchtag. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrsl">MRS. LEUCHTAG </speaker>
                <diag>Thank you, Carl.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> For Mr. Leuchtag. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <diag>Carl, sit down. Have a brandy with us. MRS. LEUCHTAG beaming with happiness To
                    celebrate our leaving for America tomorrow. Carl sits down.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you very much. I thought you would ask me, so I brought the good brandy
                    and a third glass.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He produces a glass from a back pocket. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrsl">MRS. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <diag>At last the day has come.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <diag> Frau Leuchtag and I are speaking nothing but English now.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrsl">MRS. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <diag>So we should feel at home ven ve get to America.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> A very nice idea.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG </speaker>
                <dir>raising his glass</dir>
                <diag> To America.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Mrs. Leuchtag and Carl repeat "To America." They clink glasses and drink.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <diag>Liebchen, uh, sweetness heart, what watch?</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> She glances at her wristwatch.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrsl">MRS. LEUCHTAG </speaker>
                <diag>Ten watch.</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="mrl">MR. LEUCHTAG</speaker>
                <descr>surprised</descr>
                <diag> Such much?</diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Er, you will get along beautifully in America, huh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Annina meets Renault in the hallway as she leaves the gambling room,</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> How's lady luck treating you? Aw, too bad. You'll find him over there.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Annina sees Rick and goes to his table.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Could I speak to you for just a moment, please? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick looks at her.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How did you get in here? You're under age. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> I came with Captain Renault. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>cynically</descr> I should have known. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> My husband is with me, too. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> He is? Well, Captain Renault's getting broadminded. Sit down. Will you have a
                    drink? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Annina shakes her head. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No, of course not. Do you mind if I do? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick pours himself a drink</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick, what kind of man is Captain Renault? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, he's just like any other man, only more so. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> No, I mean, is he trustworthy? Is his word -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Now, just a minute. Who told you to ask me that? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> He did. Captain Renault did. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I thought so. Where's your husband? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> At the roulette table, trying to win enough for our exit visa. Well of
                    course, he's losing. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick looks at her closely.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How long have you been married? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Eight weeks. We come from Bulgaria. Oh, things are very bad there, Monsieur.
                    A devil has the people by the throat. So, Jan and I, we, we do not want our
                    children to grow up in such a country. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>wearily</descr> So you decided to go to America. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, but we have not much money, and travelling is so expensive and
                    difficult. It was much more than we thought to get here. And then Captain
                    Renault sees us and he is so kind. He wants to help us. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I'll bet. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> He tells me he can give us an exit visa, but we have no money. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Does he know that? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And he is still willing to give you a visa? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And you want to know -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> -- Will he keep his word? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> He always has.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> There is a silence. Annina is very disturbed. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, Monsieur, you are a man. If someone loved you very much, so that your
                    happiness was the only thing that she wanted in the whole world, but she did a
                    bad thing to make certain of it, could you forgive her? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stares off into space. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Nobody ever loved me that much. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> And he never knew, and the girl kept this bad thing locked in her heart? That
                    would be all right, wouldn't it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>harshly</descr> You want my advice? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, yes, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go back to Bulgaria. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, but if you knew what it means to us to leave Europe, to get to America!
                    Oh, but if Jan should find out! He is such a boy. In many ways I am so much
                    older than he is. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, well, everybody in Casablanca has problems. Yours may work out. You'll
                    excuse me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick abruptly rises. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>tonelessly</descr> Thank you, Monsieur.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He quickly goes off, leaving Annina alone at the table. She remains seated, too
                demoralized to move. While Rick checks the reservation list, Ilsa and Laszlo enter
                the cafe. In the background we hear Sam playing, ironically enough, "It Had to Be
                You." Rick greets Ilsa and Laszlo.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Good evening. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Good evening. You see, here we are again. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I take that as a great compliment to Sam. <dir>to Ilsa</dir> I suppose he
                    means to you Paris of, well, happier days. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo looks around. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>quietly</descr> He does. Could we have a table close to him? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> And as far away from Major Strasser as possible. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, the geography may be a little difficult to arrange.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick snaps his fingers for the headwaiter. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Paul! Table thirty! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hea">HEADWAITER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Ilsa and Laszlo</dir> Yes, sir. Right this way, if you please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag><dir> to Ilsa</dir> I'll have Sam play "As Time Goes By." I believe that's
                    your favorite tune. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>smiling</descr> Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Two cognacs, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks over to Sam and whispers something to him. Sam stops what he is playing
                and begins "As Time Goes By." He shakes his head as Rick leaves. A waiter appears at
                Ilsa and Laszlo's table.</dir>
        </scene>

        <scene n="46">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - GAMBLING ROOM - NIGHT Jan sits at the roulette table. He has
                only three chips left and seems bewildered. As Rick comes up the croupier speaks to
                Jan. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Do you wish to place another bet, sir? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> No, no, I guess not. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stands behind Jan.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Jan</dir> Have you tried twenty-two tonight? I said, twenty-two. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Jan looks at Rick, then at the chips in his hand. He pauses, then puts the chips on
                twenty-two. Rick and the croupier exchange looks. The croupier understands what Rick
                wants him to do. He spins the wheel. Carl follows the proceedings, fascinated. The
                wheel stops spinning. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>in French</dir> Twenty-two, black, twenty-two. A winner. Renault, at a
                    nearby table, takes notice of what is happening. The croupier pushes a pile of
                    chips onto twenty-two and Jan reaches for it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>not even looking at Jan</dir> Leave it there. Jan hesitates, then withdraws
                    his hands. Carl continues to watch. The wheel spins. Nobody speaks while it
                    spins. It stops. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Twenty-two, black. Another winner. The croupier shoves a pile of chips toward
                    Jan. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Jan</dir> Cash it in and don't come back. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Jan rises to go to the cashier. A CUSTOMER complains to Carl.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cus">CUSTOMER</speaker>
                <diag> Say, are you sure this place is honest? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>fervently</descr> Honest! As honest as the day is long! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Meanwhile, Rick has walked over to the croupier. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How we doing tonight? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Well, a couple of thousand less than I thought there would be.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick smiles slightly and goes toward the door. Annina runs up to him and hugs him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick, I -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- He's just a lucky guy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>solicitously</descr> Monsieur Rick, may I get you a cup of coffee?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No thanks, Carl. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault, seeing that Jan has won, gets up from his table to follow Rick. Jan and
                Annina stop him on the way.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Renault, may I -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> -- Oh, not here, please. Come to my office in the morning. We'll do
                    everything business-like. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> We'll be there at six. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I'll be there at ten. I am very happy for both of you. Still, it's very
                    strange that you won. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He looks over and sees Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, maybe not so strange. I'll see you in the morning. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you so much, Captain Renault. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="47">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT At the bar, Carl whispers in Sacha's ear.
                Sacha says "No!" and runs to Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Boss, you've done a beautiful thing. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He kisses Rick on both cheeks.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go away, you crazy Russian!</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Carl pours a brandy for Rick. Pretending not to do so, Rick glances in Ilsa's
                direction. Renault comes up to him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> As I suspected, you're a rank sentimentalist. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah? Why? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>chidingly</descr> Why do you interfere with my little romances? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Put it down as a gesture to love. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>good-naturedly</descr> Well, I forgive you this time. But I'll be in
                    tomorrow night with a breathtaking blonde, and it will make me very happy if she
                    loses. Uh huh! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He smiles and walks away. Laszlo comes up to Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Blaine, I wonder if I could talk to you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go ahead. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Well, isn't there some other place? It's rather confidential, what I have to
                    say. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My office. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Right. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
    </body>
</xml>
