<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <movie>
            <title>Casablanca</title>
            <director>Michael Curtiz</director>
            <wrldPrem>Nov. 26 1942</wrldPrem>
            <loc>WB studios, Burbank, CA</loc>
            <loc>Van Nuys Airport, LA</loc>
            <producer>Hal B. Wallis</producer>
            <producer>Warner Bros</producer>
            <writer>Howard Koch</writer>
            <writer>Julius J. Epstein</writer>
            <writer>Philip G. Epstein</writer>
            <basedOn>Everybody Comes to Rick’s (stage play); written by Murray Burnett and Joan
                Alison</basedOn>
            <composer>Max Steiner</composer>
            <starring>Humphrey Bogart</starring>
            <starring>Ingrid Bergman</starring>
            <starring>Paul Henreid</starring>
            <starring>Conrad Veidt</starring>
            <starring>Claude Rains</starring>
            <cinematography>Arthur Edeson</cinematography>
            <editor>Owen Marks</editor>
        </movie>
        <script>
            <numScenes>77</numScenes>
            <url>https://app.studiobinder.com/company/580e85847e7982164664e844/collab/5eac35a683f7a90bfc3fc810/projects/5de590454f452c09a98e975b/document/5de5904f1fe52b06c2f4bd79/%5Bobject%20Object%5D?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=sb-app-link&amp;utm_campaign=script&amp;utm_term=casablanca-script-breakdown&amp;utm_content=full-script-pdf-download</url>
            <generatedBy>Brent Dunham</generatedBy>
            <date>Dec. 2</date>
            <publisher>StudioBinder Inc.</publisher>
            <website> https://www.studiobinder.com/</website>
        </script>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <scene n="0">
            <camera>FADE IN: LONG SHOT — REVOLVING GLOBE</camera>
            <setting> A revolving globe. When it stops revolving it turns briefly into a contour map
                of Europe, then into a flat map. Superimposed over this map are scenes of refugees
                fleeing from all sections of Europe by foot, wagon, auto, and boat, and all
                converging upon one point on the tip of Africa -- Casablanca. Arrows on the map
                illustrate the routes taken as the voice of a NARRATOR describes the
                migration.</setting>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="narr">NARRATOR</speaker>
                <diag>With the coming of the Second World War, many eyes in imprisoned Europe turned
                    hopefully, or desperately, toward the freedom of the Americas. Lisbon became the
                    great embarkation point. But not everybody could get to Lisbon directly, and so,
                    a tortuous, roundabout refugee trail sprang up. Paris to Marseilles, across the
                    Mediterranean to Oran, then by train, or auto, or foot, across the rim of Africa
                    to Casablanca in French Morocco. Here, the fortunate ones, through money, or
                    influence, or luck, might obtain exit visas and scurry to Lisbon, and from
                    Lisbon to the New World. But the others wait in Casablanca -- and wait -- and
                    wait -- and wait. The narrator's voice fade away...</diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="1">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. OLD MOORISH SECTION OF THE CITY - DAY At first only the turrets and
                rooftops are visible against a torrid sky. The facades of the Moorish buildings give
                way to a narrow, twisting street crowded with the polyglot life of a native quarter.
                The intense desert sun holds the scene in a torpid tranquility. Activity is
                unhurried and sounds are muted.</setting>

        </scene>
        <scene n="2">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. POLICE STATION - DAY A POLICE OFFICER takes a piece of paper from the
                typewriter, turns to a microphone, and reads.</setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="pol">POLICE OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>To all officers! Two German couriers carrying important official documents
                    murdered on train from Oran. Murderer and possible accomplices headed for
                    Casablanca. Round up all suspicious characters and search them for stolen
                    documents. Important!</diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="3">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. A STREET IN THE OLD MOORISH SECTION - DAY An officer BLOWS his whistle
                several times. There is pandemonium as native guards begin to round up people. A
                police car, full of officers, with SIREN BLARING, screams through the street and
                stops in the market. Some try to escape but are caught by the police and loaded into
                a police wagon. At a street corner TWO POLICEMEN stop a white CIVILIAN and question
                him. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="pol1">FIRST POLICEMAN</speaker>
                <diag> May we see your papers? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="civ">CIVILIAN</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>nervously</descr> I don't think I have them on me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="pol1">FIRST POLICEMAN</speaker>
                <diag> In that case, we'll have to ask you to come along. </diag>
            </sp>
            <descr>The civilian pats his dir. </descr>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="civ">CIVILIAN</speaker>
                <diag> Wait. It's just possible that I -\- Yes, here they are. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He brings out his papers. The second policeman examines them. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="pol2">SECOND POLICEMAN</speaker>
                <diag> These papers expired three weeks ago. You'll have to come along. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Suddenly the civilian breaks away and starts to run wildly down the street. The
                policeman SHOUTS "Halt", but the civilian keeps going. JAN and ANNINA BRANDEL, a
                very young and attractive refugee couple from Bulgaria, watch as the civilian
                passes. They've been thrust by circumstances from a simple country life into an
                unfamiliar and hectic world. A shot RINGS out, and the man falls to the ground.
                Above him, painted on the wall, is a large poster of Marshal Petain, which reads:
                "Je tiens mes promesses, meme celles des autres." The policeman frantically searches
                the body, but only finds Free French literature. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="4">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. PALAIS DE JUSTICE - DAY We see an inscription carved in a marble block
                along the roofline of the building: "Liberte, Egalite, Fraternite" We see the the
                facade, French in architecture, then the high-vaulted entrance which is inscribed
                "Palais de Justice". At the entrance the arrested suspects are led in by the police.
            </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="5">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. SIDEWALK CAFE - DAY A middle-aged ENGLISH COUPLE sit at a table just off
                the square, and observe the commotion across the way in front of the Palais de
                Justice. The police van pulls up. The rear doors are opened and people stream out. A
                EUROPEAN man, sitting at a table nearby, watches the English couple more closely
                than the scene on the street. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engw">ENGLISHWOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> What on earth's going on there? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> I don't know, my dear. The European walks over to the couple. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Pardon, pardon, Monsieur, pardon Madame, have you not heard? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> We hear very little, and we understand even less. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Two German couriers were found murdered in the desert -\- the unoccupied
                    desert. This is the customary roundup of refugees, liberals, and uh, of course,
                    a beautiful young girl for Monsieur Renault, the Prefect of Police. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="6">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. PALAIS DE JUSTICE - DAY Suspects are herded out of the van, and into the
                Palais de Justice. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="7">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Unfortunately, along with these unhappy refugees the scum of Europe has
                    gravitated to Casablanca. Some of them have been waiting years for a visa.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He puts his left arm compassionately around the Englishman, and reaches behind the
                man with his right hand. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> I beg of you, Monsieur, watch yourself. Be on guard. This place is full of
                    vultures, vultures everywhere, everywhere. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The Englishman seems to be taken aback by this sudden display of concern. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Ha, ha, thank you, thank you very much. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="eur">EUROPEAN</speaker>
                <diag> Not at all. Au revoir, Monsieur. Au revoir, Madame.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He leaves. The Englishman, still a trifle disconcerted by the European's action,
                watches him as he leaves. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Au revoir. Amusing little fellow. Waiter! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As he pats both his breast and pants pockets he realizes there is something
                missing. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. How silly of me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engw">ENGLISHWOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> What, dear? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engm">ENGLISHMAN</speaker>
                <diag> I've left my wallet in the hotel. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="engw">ENGLISHWOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Suddenly the Englishman looks off in the direction of the departed European, the
                clouds of suspicion gathering. Interrupting overhead is the DRONE of a low flying
                airplane. They look up.</dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="8">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. OVERHEAD SHOT - DAY An airplane cuts its motor for landing. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="9">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. PALAIS DE JUSTICE - DAY Refugees wait in line outside the Palais de
                Justice. Their upturned gaze follows the flight of the plane. In their faces is
                revealed one hope they all have in common, and the plane is the symbol of that hope.
                Jan and Annina look up at the plane. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>wistfully</descr> Perhaps tomorrow we'll be on that plane. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="10">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. OVERHEAD SHOT - DAY The plane SWOOPS down past a sign atop a building at
                the edge of the airport. The sign reads "Rick's Cafe Americain." </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="11">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. AIRFIELD - DAY As the plane lands a swastika on its tail is clearly
                visible. It taxis to a stop as a group of officers march into formation in front of
                it. Behind them stand a detail of native soldiers keeping guard. In the group is
                CAPTAIN LOUIS RENAULT, a French officer appointed by Vichy as Prefect of Police in
                Casablanca. He is a handsome, middle-aged Frenchman, debonair and gay, but withal a
                shrewd and alert official. With him are HERR HEINZE, the German consul, CAPTAIN
                TONELLI, an Italian officer, and LIEUTENANT CASSELLE, Renault's aide. When the plane
                door opens, the first passenger to step out is a tall, middle-aged, pale German with
                a smile that seems more the result of a frozen face muscle than a cheerful
                disposition. On any occasion when MAJOR STRASSER is crossed, his expression hardens
                into iron. Herr Heinze steps up to him with upraised arm. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> Heil Hitler. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Heil Hitler. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They shake hands.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> It is very good to see you again, Major Strasser. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Heinze introduces Strasser to Renault.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> May I present Captain Renault, Police Prefect of Casablanca. Major Strasser.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault salutes.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Unoccupied France welcomes you to Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>in perfect English, smiling</descr> Thank you, Captain. It's very good to
                    be here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Major Strasser, my aide, Lieutenant Casselle. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As they acknowledge each other, Captain Tonelli barges in front of Casselle and
                salutes Strasser.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ton">TONELLI</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Tonelli, the Italian service, at your command, Major. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> That is kind of you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>But Tonelli gets no further than that as Strasser turns again to Renault. They walk
                away from the plane, Heinze following, with Casselle and Tonelli bringing up the
                rear, engaged in a heated exchange of words. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Renault">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> You may find the climate of Casablanca a trifle warm, Major. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, we Germans must get used to all climates, from Russia to the Sahara. But
                    perhaps you were not referring to the weather. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>sidesteps the implication with a smile</descr> What else, my dear Major?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>casually</descr> By the way, the murder of the couriers, what has been
                    done? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Realizing the importance of the case, my men are rounding up twice the usual
                    number of suspects. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> We already know who the murderer is. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Good. Is he in custody? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, there is no hurry. Tonight he'll be at Rick's. Everybody comes to Rick's.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I have already heard about this cafe, and also about Mr. Rick himself.
                </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="12">
            <camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT The neon sign above the door is brightly lit.
                Customers arrive and go in through the front door. From inside we hear sounds of
                MUSIC and LAUGHTER. The song is "It Had to Be You." Again we isolate on the neon
                sign. INSERT SIGN: "Rick's Cafe Americain". We follow a group of customers
                inside.</setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="13">
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick's is an expensive and chic nightclub
                which definitely possesses an air of sophistication and intrigue. SAM, a middle-aged
                Negro, sits on a stool before a small, salmon-colored piano on wheels, playing and
                singing while accompanied by a small orchestra. All about him there is the HUM of
                voices, CHATTER and LAUGHTER. The occupants of the room are varied. There are
                Europeans in their dinner jackets, their women beautifully begowned and bejeweled.
                There are Moroccans in silk robes. Turks wearing fezzes. Levantines. Naval officers.
                Members of the Foreign Legion, distinguished by their kepis. Two men sit at a table. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="man">MAN</speaker>
                <diag> Waiting, waiting, waiting. I'll never get out of here. I'll die in
                    Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>His companion seems uninterested in his dilemma. Sympathy is evidently in short
                supply in Casablanca. At another table a very well-dressed WOMAN talks to a MOOR.
                She has a bracelet on her wrist. No other jewelry.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="wom">WOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> But can't you make it just a little more? Please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="moor">MOOR</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry, Madame, but diamonds are a drug on the market. Everybody sells
                    diamonds. There are diamonds everywhere. Two thousand, four hundred. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="wom">WOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> All right. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> On to another table where two CONSPIRATORS talk.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="con">CONSPIRATOR</speaker>
                <diag> The trucks are waiting, the men are waiting. Everything is -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He stops abruptly as two German officers walk by. A REFUGEE and another MAN
                converse at another table. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="man">MAN</speaker>
                <diag> It's the fishing smack Santiago. It leaves at one tomorrow night, here from
                    the end of La Medina. Third boat. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ref">REFUGEE</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you, oh, thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="man">MAN</speaker>
                <diag> And bring fifteen thousand francs in cash. Remember, in cash. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> On the way to the bar we pass several tables and hear a Babel of foreign tongues.
                Here and there we catch a scattered phrase or sentence in English. SACHA, a friendly
                young Russian bartender, hands a drink to a customer with the Russian equivalent of
                "Bottoms Up." The customer answers with "Cheerio." CARL, the waiter, is a fat,
                jovial German refugee with spectacles. He walks, tray in hand, to a private door,
                over which ABDUL, a large, burly man, stands guard.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Open up, Abdul. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="abd">ABDUL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>respectfully</descr> Yes, Herr Professor. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Abdul opens the door and Carl goes into the gambling room. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="14">

            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - GAMBLING ROOM - NIGHT Their is much activity at the various
                tables. At one table TWO WOMEN and a MAN play cards. They glance at another table.
                One of them calls to Carl. </setting>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="wom1">FIRST WOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Uh, waiter. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Madame? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="wom1">FIRST WOMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Will you ask Rick if he'll have a drink with us? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Madame, he never drinks with customers. Never. I have never seen him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="wom2">SECOND WOMAN</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>disappointedly</descr> What makes saloon-keepers so snobbish? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="man">MAN</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Carl</dir> Perhaps if you told him I ran the second largest banking
                    house in Amsterdam. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> The second largest? That wouldn't impress Rick. The leading banker in
                    Amsterdam is now the pastry chef in our kitchen. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="man">MAN</speaker>
                <diag> We have something to look forward to. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> And his father is the bellboy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Carl laughs. The overseer walks up to a table with a paper in his hand. Then we see
                a drink and a man's hand, but nothing more. The overseer places a check on the
                table. The hand picks up the check and writes on it, in pencil, "Okay-Rick." The
                overseer takes the check. We now see RICK, sitting at a table alone playing
                solitaire chess. Rick is an American of indeterminate age. There is no expression on
                his face, complete deadpan. There is a commotion at the door as people attempt to
                come into the gambling room. He nods approval to Abdul. Then a GERMAN appears in the
                doorway. Abdul looks to Rick who glances back toward the open door and nods "no".
                Abdul starts to close the door on the man. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="abd">ABDUL</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry sir, this is a private room. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ger">GERMAN</speaker>
                <diag> Of all the nerve! Who do you think -- I know there's gambling in there!
                    There's no secret. You dare not keep me out of here!</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The man tries to push his way through the door as Rick walks up. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>coldly</descr> Yes? What's the trouble? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="abd">ABDUL</speaker>
                <diag> This gentleman -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The German interrupts and waves his card. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ger">GERMAN</speaker>
                <diag> I've been in every gambling room between Honolulu and Berlin and if you think
                    I'm going to be kept out of a saloon like this, you're very much
                    mistaken.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> At this moment UGARTE, a small, thin man with a nervous air, tries to squeeze
                through the doorway blocked by the German. If he were an American, Ugarte would look
                like a tout. He gets through and passes Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Uh, excuse me, please. Hello, Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>softly</descr> Hello Ugarte. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick looks at the German calmly, takes the card out of his hand, and tears it
                up.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Your cash is good at the bar. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ger">GERMAN</speaker>
                <diag> What! Do you know who I am? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Ric">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I do. You're lucky the bar's open to you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ger">GERMAN</speaker>
                <diag> This is outrageous. I shall report it to the Angriff!</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The German storms off, tossing the pieces of his card into the air behind him.
                Rick meets Ugarte on his way back to his table. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>fawning</descr> Huh. You know, Rick, watching you just now with the
                    Deutsches Bank, one would think you'd been doing this all your life. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>stiffening</descr> Well, what makes you think I haven't? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>vaguely</descr> Oh, nothing. But when you first came to Casablanca, I
                    thought -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>coldly</descr> -- You thought what? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Fearing to offend Rick, Ugarte laughs. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> What right do I have to think? Ugarte pulls out a chair at Rick's table.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> May I? Too bad about those two German couriers, wasn't it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>indifferently</descr> They got a lucky break. Yesterday they were just
                    two German clerks. Today they're the 'Honored Dead'. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> You are a very cynical person, Rick, if you'll forgive me for saying so.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ugarte sits down.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> shortly I forgive you. A waiter comes up to the table with a tray of drinks.
                    He places one before Ugarte. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. <dir>to Rick</dir> Will you have a drink with me please? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> I forgot. You never drink with -- <dir>to waiter</dir> I'll have another,
                    please. <dir>to Rick, sadly </dir>You despise me, don't you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>indifferently</dir> If I gave you any thought, I probably would. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> But why? Oh, you object to the kind of business I do, huh? But think of all
                    those poor refugees who must rot in this place if I didn't help them. That's not
                    so bad. Through ways of my own I provide them with exit visas. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> For a price, Ugarte, for a price. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> But think of all the poor devils who cannot meet Renault's price. I get it
                    for them for half. Is that so parasitic? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I don't mind a parasite. I object to a cut-rate one. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Well, Rick, after tonight I'll be through with the whole business, and I am
                    leaving finally this Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Who did you bribe for your visa? Renault or yourself? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>ironically</descr> Myself. I found myself much more reasonable. He takes
                    an envelope from his pocket and lays it on the table. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Look, Rick, do you know what this is? Something that even you have never
                    seen. Letters of transit signed by General de Gaulle. Cannot be rescinded, not
                    even questioned. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick appears ready to take them form Ugarte. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> One moment. Tonight I'll be selling those for more money than even I have
                    ever dreamed of, and then, addio Casablanca! You know, Rick, I have many friends
                    in Casablanca, but somehow, just because you despise me you're the only one I
                    trust. Will you keep these for me? Please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> For how long? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Perhaps an hour, perhaps a little longer. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I don't want them here overnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Don't be afraid of that. Please keep them for me. Thank you. I knew I could
                    trust you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick takes them. Ugarte leaves the table just as the waiter comes up.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, waiter. I'll be expecting some people. If anybody asks for me, I'll be
                    right here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Waiter">WAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The waiter leaves. Ugarte turns to Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, I hope you are more impressed with me now, huh? If you'll forgive me,
                    I'll share my good luck with your roulette wheel. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He starts across the floor.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Just a moment. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ugarte stops as Rick comes up to him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah, I heard a rumor that those German couriers were carrying letters of
                    transit. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ugarte hesitates for a moment.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Huh? I heard that rumor, too. Poor devils. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick looks at Ugarte steadily.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>slowly</descr> Yes, you're right, Ugarte. I am a little more impressed
                    with you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick leaves the gambling room and goes into the main room. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="15">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick makes his way over to Sam, who plays
                and sings the "Knock Wood" number, accompanied by the orchestra. The cafe is in
                semi-darkness. The spotlight is on Sam, and every time the orchestra comes in on the
                "Knock Wood" business, the spotlight swings over to the orchestra. During one of the
                periods when the spotlight is on the orchestra, Rick slips the letters of transit
                into the piano. FERRARI, owner of the Blue Parrot, a competing night spot, comes
                into the cafe, sits down, and watches Sam. Then he sees Rick and they smile at each
                other. At the end of the number Ferrari goes to the bar to speak to Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Ferrari. How's business at the Blue Parrot? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Fine, but I would like to buy your cafe. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It's not for sale. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> You haven't heard my offer. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It's not for sale at any price. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> What do you want for Sam? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I don't buy or sell human beings. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> That's too bad. That's Casablanca's leading commodity. In refugees alone we
                    could make a fortune if you would work with me through the black market. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Suppose you run your business and let me run mine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Suppose we ask Sam. Maybe he'd like to make a change. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Suppose we do. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> My dear Rick, when will you realize that in this world today isolationism is
                    no longer a practical policy? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick and Ferrari walk over to the piano.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sam, Ferrari wants you to work for him at the Blue Parrot. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> I like it fine here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> He'll double what I pay you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah, but I ain't got time to spend the money I make here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sorry. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Apparently satisfied, Ferrari walks away. Back at the bar, YVONNE, an attractive
                young French woman, sits on a stool drinking brandy. Sacha, who looks at her with
                lovesick eyes, fills her tumbler. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> The boss's private stock. Because, Yvonne, I loff you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>morosely</descr> Oh, shut up. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>fondly</descr> All right, all right. For you, Yvonne, I shot opp,
                    because, Yvonne, I loff you. Uh oh. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick saunters over and leans on the bar, next to Yvonne. He pays no attention to
                her. She looks at him bitterly, without saying a word.s</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, Monsieur Rick, Monsieur Rick. Some Germans, boom, boom, boom, boom, gave
                    this check. Is it all right?</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick looks the check over and tears it up. Yvonne has never taken her eyes off
                Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Where were you last night? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> That's so long ago, I don't remember. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Will I see you tonight? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>matter-of-factly</descr> I never make plans that far ahead. Yvonne turns,
                    looks at Sacha, and extends her glass to him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Give me another. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sacha, she's had enough. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Don't listen to him, Sacha. Fill it up. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Yvonne, I loff you, but he pays me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Yvonne wheels on Rick with drunken fury.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, I'm sick and tired of having you -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Sacha, call a cab. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, boss. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick takes Yvonne by the arm.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Come on, we're going to get your coat. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Take your hands off me! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He pulls her along toward the door.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No. You're going home. You've had a little too much to drink. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="16">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT Sacha stands at the curb on the street in front of
                Rick's and signals for a cab. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Taxi! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Soon one pulls up. Rick and Yvonne come out of the cafe. He puts a coat over her
                shoulders and she objects violently.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Who do you think you are, pushing me around? What a fool I was to fall for a
                    man like you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick and Yvonne approach the waiting cab. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Sacha</dir> You'd better go with her, Sacha, to be sure she gets home.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, boss. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And come right back. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>his face falling</descr> Yes, boss. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stands and looks up at the revolving beacon light from the airport. It
                intermittently sheds its light on Rick's face. Renault sits at a table on the cafe
                terrace, watching this evening's performance. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick walks over to him.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Louis. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> How extravagant you are, throwing away women like that. Someday they may be
                    scarce. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick sits down at the table.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>amused</descr> You know, I think now I shall pay a call on Yvonne, maybe
                    get her on the rebound, eh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> When it comes to women, you're a true democrat. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> As they talk, Captain Tonelli and Lieutenant Casselle walk by toward the entrance
                of the cafe. Casselle talks non-stop and Tonelli tries. They both stop, salute
                Renault, and walk into the cafe.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> If he gets a word in it'll be a major Italian victory. Rick laughs. Rick and
                    Renault look up when they hear the BUZZ of a plane taking off from the adjacent
                    airfield. The plane flies directly over their heads. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> The plane to Lisbon. <dir>pause</dir> You would like to be on it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>curtly</descr> Why? What's in Lisbon? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> The clipper to America. Rick doesn't answer. His look isn't a happy one.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick doesn't answer. His look isn't a happy one.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I have often speculated on why you don't return to America. Did you abscond
                    with the church funds? Did you run off with a senator's wife? I like to think
                    you killed a man. It's the romantic in me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick still looks in the direction of the airport.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It was a combination of all three. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> And what in heaven's name brought you to Casablanca? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My health. I came to Casablanca for the waters. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Waters? What waters? We're in the desert. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I was misinformed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Huh! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> EMIL, the croupier, comes out of the cafe and walks over to Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="emil">EMIL</speaker>
                <diag> Excuse me, Monsieur Rick, but a gentleman inside has won twenty thousand
                    francs. The cashier would like some money. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, I'll get it from the safe. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="emil">EMIL</speaker>
                <diag> I am so upset, Monsieur Rick. You know I can't understand -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Forget it, Emil. Mistakes like that happen all the time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="emil">EMIL</speaker>
                <diag> I'm awfully sorry. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The three men enter the cafe. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="17">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT They pass Sam at the piano. He's playing
                "Baby Face". Rick pats Sam on the shoulder. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, there's going to be some excitement here tonight. We are going to make
                    an arrest in your cafe. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>somewhat annoyed</descr> What, again? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> This is no ordinary arrest. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> A murderer, no less. Rick's eyes react. Involuntarily, they glance toward the
                gambling room. Renault catches the look.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> If you are thinking of warning him, don't put yourself out. He cannot
                    possibly escape. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I stick my neck out for nobody. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> A wise foreign policy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>They start upstairs to Rick's office, passing Casselle who is still haranguing
                Tonelli.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> You know, Rick, we could have made this arrest earlier in the evening at the
                    Blue Parrot, but out of my high regard for you we are staging it here. It will
                    amuse your customers. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Our entertainment is enough. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>They go inside the office.</dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="18">
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT Rick opens up the safe in a small, dark room
                just off the office. Only Rick's shadow can be seen getting the money out. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, we are to have an important guest tonight, Major Strasser of the Third
                    Reich, no less. We want him to be here when we make the arrest. A little
                    demonstration of the efficiency of my administration. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick moves out of the shadows and into view.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I see. And what's Strasser doing here? He certainly didn't come all the way
                    to Casablanca to witness a demonstration of your efficiency. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Perhaps not. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He gives the money to Emil.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Here you are. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="emil">EMIL</speaker>
                <diag> It shall not happen again, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> That's all right.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Emil departs. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Louis, you've got something on your mind. Why don't you spill it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick closes the door to the office, then goes over to close the safe. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> How observant you are. As a matter of fact, I wanted to give you a word of
                    advice. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah? Have a brandy? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. Rick, there are many exit visas sold in this cafe, but we know
                    that you have never sold one. That is the reason we permit you to remain open.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I thought it was because we let you win at roulette. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> That is another reason. There is a man who's arrived in Casablanca on his way
                    to America. He will offer a fortune to anyone who will furnish him with an exit
                    visa. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah? What's his name? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Victor Laszlo. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Victor Laszlo? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault watches Rick's reaction.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, that is the first time I have ever seen you so impressed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, he's succeeded in impressing half the world. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> It is my duty to see that he doesn't impress the other half. Rick, Laszlo
                    must never reach America. He stays in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It'll be interesting to see how he manages. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Manages what? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> His escape. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, but I just told you. -\\- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Stop it. He escaped from a concentration camp and the Nazis have been
                    chasing him all over Europe. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> This is the end of the chase. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Twenty thousand francs says it isn't.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> They sit down to discuss the matter in earnest. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Is that a serious offer? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I just paid out twenty. I'd like to get it back. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Make it ten. I am only a poor corrupt official. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Okay. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Done. No matter how clever he is, he still needs an exit visa, or I should
                    say, two. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why two? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> He is traveling with a lady. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> He'll take one. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I think not. I have seen the lady. And if he did not leave her in Marseilles,
                    or in Oran, he certainly won't leave her in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Maybe he's not quite as romantic as you are. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> It doesn't matter. There is no exit visa for him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Louis, whatever gave you the impression that I might be interested in helping
                    Laszlo escape? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Because, my dear Ricky, I suspect that under that cynical shell you're at
                    heart a sentimentalist.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick makes a face. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, laugh if you will, but I happen to be familiar with your record. Let me
                    point out just two items. In 1935 you ran guns to Ethiopia. In 1936, you fought
                    in Spain on the Loyalist side. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And got well paid for it on both occasions. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> The winning side would have paid you much better. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Maybe. Well, it seems you are determined to keep Laszlo here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I have my orders. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, I see. Gestapo spank. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault stands up.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> My dear Ricky, you overestimate the influence of the Gestapo. I don't
                    interfere with them and they don't interfere with me. In Casablanca I am master
                    of my fate. I am captain of my -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He stops short as his AIDE enters.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="aide">AIDE</speaker>
                <diag> -- Major Strasser is here, sir.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault starts to leave. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah, you were saying? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>hurriedly</descr> Excuse me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He hurries away. Rick smiles cynically. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="19">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Renault walks up to Carl. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Carl, see that Major Strasser gets a good table, one close to the ladies.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> I have already given him the best, knowing he is German and would take it
                    anyway.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault walks over to one of his officers. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Take him quietly. Two guards at every door. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="off">OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, sir. Everything is ready, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The officer salutes and goes off to speak to the guards. Renault walks over to
                Strasser's table as Rick comes down the stairs.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Good evening, gentlemen. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Good evening, Captain. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> Won't you join us?</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault sits down. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. It is a pleasure to have you here, Major. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to the waiter</dir> Champagne and a tin of caviar. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> May I recommend Veuve Cliquot '26, a good French wine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Waiter">WAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Very well, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> A very interesting club. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Especially so tonight, Major. In a few minutes you will see the arrest of the
                    man who murdered your couriers. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I expected no less, Captain. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="20">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - GAMBLING ROOM - NIGHT Ugarte stands at the roulette table.
                Two gendarmes approach him from behind. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Ugarte? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ugarte looks around.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker>
                <diag> Will you please come with us. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Certainly. May I first please cash my chips? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> The officer nods. They follow Ugarte to the cashier's window. Ugarte puts his
                chips through the window to the CASHIER.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Pretty lucky, huh? Two thousand, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Two more guards station themselves at the door in case there is trouble.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cas">CASHIER</speaker>
                <diag> Two thousand. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ugarte starts to walk out, followed by the gendarmes. When he reaches the doorway
                he suddenly rushes through and slams the door behind himself. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="21">
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT By the time the gendarmes manage to get
                the door open again, Ugarte has pulled a gun. He FIRES at the doorway. The SHOTS
                bring on pandemonium in the cafe. As Ugarte runs through the hallway he sees Rick,
                appearing from the opposite direction, and grabs him. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Rick! Rick, help me! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Don't be a fool. You can't get away. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, hide me. Do something! You must help me, Rick. Do something! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Guards and gendarmes rush in and grab Ugarte. Rick stands impassively as they drag
                Ugarte off.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="uga">UGARTE</speaker>
                <diag> Rick! Rick! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>We move to Strasser's table, who has witnessed the event.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Excellent, Captain. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Back to Rick, still standing where he was, as a CUSTOMER walks by.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cus">CUSTOMER</speaker>
                <diag> When they come to get me, Rick, I hope you'll be more of a help. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I stick my neck out for nobody. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick comes out to the middle of the floor. An air of tense expectancy pervades the
                room. A few customers are on the point of leaving. Rick speaks in a very calm voice. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry there was a disturbance, folks, but it's all over now. Everything's
                    all right. Just sit down and have a good time. Enjoy yourself.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick glances toward Sam. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All right, Sam. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam nods and begins to play. Renault, Strasser, and Heinze sit calmly at their
                table after witnessing the arrest. Rick walks by.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>calling to Rick</dir> Oh, Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stops and comes over to their table. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Rick, this is Major Heinrich Strasser of the Third Reich. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> How do you do, Mr. Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, how do you do? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> And you already know Herr Heinze of the Third Reich.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick nods to Strasser and Heinze. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Please join us, Mr. Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick sits down with them.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> We are very honored tonight, Rick. Major Strasser is one of the reasons the
                    Third Reich enjoys the reputation it has today. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You repeat "Third Reich" as though you expected there to be others. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, personally, Major, I will take what comes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Rick</dir> Do you mind if I ask you a few questions? Unofficially, of
                    course. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Make it official, if you like. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> What is your nationality? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>pokerfaced</descr> I'm a drunkard. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> That makes Rick a citizen of the world. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I was born in New York City if that'll help you any. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I understand you came here from Paris at the time of the occupation. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> There seems to be no secret about that. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Are you one of those people who cannot imagine the Germans in their beloved
                    Paris? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It's not particularly my beloved Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hei">HEINZE</speaker>
                <diag> Can you imagine us in London? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> When you get there, ask me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Ho, diplomatist! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> How about New York? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, there are certain sections of New York, Major, that I wouldn't advise
                    you to try to invade. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Aha. Who do you think will win the war? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I haven't the slightest idea. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Rick is completely neutral about everything. And that takes in the field of
                    women, too. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You weren't always so carefully neutral. We have a complete dossier on you.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Strasser takes a little black book from his pocket and turns to a certain
                page.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> "Richard Blaine, American. Age, thirty-seven. Cannot return to his country."
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Strasser looks up from the book </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> The reason is a little vague. We also know what you did in Paris, Mr. Blaine,
                    and also we know why you left Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick reaches over and takes the book from Strasser's hand. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Don't worry. We are not going to broadcast it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick looks up from the book.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Are my eyes really brown? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You will forgive my curiosity, Mr. Blaine. The point is, an enemy of the
                    Reich has come to Casablanca and we are checking up on anybody who can be of any
                    help to us. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>glances toward Renault</dir> My interest in whether Victor Laszlo stays or
                    goes is purely a sporting one. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> In this case, you have no sympathy for the fox, huh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Not particularly. I understand the point of view of the hound, too. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Victor Laszlo published the foulest lies in the Prague newspapers until the
                    very day we marched in, and even after that he continued to print scandal sheets
                    in a cellar. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Of course, one must admit he has great courage. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I admit he is very clever. Three times he slipped through our fingers. In
                    Paris he continued his activities. We intend not to let it happen again. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick gets up.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You'll excuse me, gentlemen. Your business is politics. Mine is running a
                    saloon. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Good evening, Mr. Blaine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks away toward the gambling room.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> You see, Major, you have nothing to worry about Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Perhaps. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>A couple comes in the front door. They are VICTOR LASZLO, the Czech resistance
                leader, and a very pretty young woman wearing a simple white gown, MISS ILSA LUND.
                She is so beautiful, in fact, that people turn to stare. The HEADWAITER comes up to
                them. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hea">HEADWAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I reserved a table. Victor Laszlo. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="hea">HEADWAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur Laszlo. Right this way.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> As the headwaiter takes them to a table they pass by the piano, and the woman
                looks at Sam. Sam, with a conscious effort, keeps his eyes on the keyboard as they
                go past. He appears to know this woman. After she has gone by Sam steals a look in
                her direction. BERGER, a slight, middle-aged man, observes the couple from a
                distance. The headwaiter seats Ilsa. Laszlo takes the chair opposite and surveys the
                room. Strasser and Renault look up at them from their table. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Two cointreaux, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Waiter">WAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Ilsa</dir> I saw no one of Ugarte's description. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Victor, I, I feel somehow we shouldn't stay here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> If we would walk out so soon, it would only call attention to us. Perhaps
                    Ugarte's in some other part of the cafe. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Berger walks up to their table.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Excuse me, but you look like a couple who are on their way to America.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Well? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Berger takes a ring from his finger.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> You will find a market there for this ring. I am forced to sell it at a great
                    sacrifice. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you, but I hardly think -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> -- Then perhaps for the lady. The ring is quite unique. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He holds it down for their view. Carefully lifting up the stone, he reveals--
                INSERT - a gold plate in the setting underneath, an impression of the Lorraine Cross
                of General de Gaulle. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, yes, I'm very interested. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Berger sits down with them.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Good. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>lower voice</descr> What is your name? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Berger, Norwegian, and at your service, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault approaches the table from behind Laszlo. Ilsa tries to warn him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Victor-- </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo understands.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>in a low voice</descr> I'll meet you in a few minutes at the bar. <descr>in
                        a louder voice</descr> I do not think we want to buy the ring. But thank you
                    for showing it to us. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Berger, taking the cue, sighs and puts the ring away.s</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Such a bargain. But that is your decision? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sorry. It is.. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Berger gets up and leaves as Renault moves to the table</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Laszlo, is it not? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I am Captain Renault, Prefect of Police. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. What is it you want? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>amiably</descr> Merely to welcome you to Casablanca and wish you a
                    pleasant stay. It is not often we have so distinguished a visitor. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. I hope you'll forgive me, Captain, but the present French
                    administration has not always been so cordial. May I present Miss Ilsa Lund?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I was informed you were the most beautiful woman ever to visit Casablanca.
                    That was a gross understatement. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa's manner is friendly and reserved, her
                voice low and soft.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You are very kind. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Won't you join us? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He sits down.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> If you will permit me. <dir>calls to the waiter</dir> Oh, Emil. Please, a bottle of your
                    best champagne, and put it on my bill. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="emil">EMIL</speaker>
                <diag> Very well, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> No, Captain, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> No. Please, Monsieur, it is a little game we play. They put it on the bill, I
                    tear the bill up. It is very convenient. 
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa glances off in Sam's direction.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Captain, the boy who is playing the piano, somewhere I have seen him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Sam? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> He came from Paris with Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Rick? Who's he? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>smiling</descr> Mademoiselle, you are in Rick's and Rick is -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> -- Is what? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, Mademoiselle, he's the kind of a man that, well, if I were a woman and
                    I-- <dir>taps his chest</dir> were not around, I should be in love with Rick. But what a
                    fool I am talking to a beautiful woman about another man.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault jumps to his
                feet as Strasser enters. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Excuse me. Ah, Major. Mademoiselle Lund, Monsieur Laszlo, may I present Major
                    Heinrich Strasser.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Strasser bows and smiles pleasantly. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> How do you do. This is a pleasure I have long looked forward to.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>There is not
                the slightest recognition from either Ilsa or Laszlo. Strasser waits to be asked
                to seat himself.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I'm sure you'll excuse me if I am not gracious, but you see, Major Strasser,
                    I'm a Czechoslovakian. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You were a Czechoslovakian. Now you are a subject of the German Reich! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo
                stands. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I've never accepted that privilege, and I'm now on French soil. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> I should like to discuss some matters arising from your presence on French
                    soil. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> This is hardly the time or the place. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>hardening</descr> Then we shall state another time and another place. Tomorrow at ten
                    in the Prefect's office, with Mademoiselle. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Renault, I am under your authority. Is it your order that we come to
                    your office? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>amiably</descr> Let us say that it is my request. That is a much more pleasant word.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Very well.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Renault and Strasser bow shortly. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Mademoiselle. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Mademoiselle. Renault and Strasser walk away. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> A very clever tactical retreat, Major.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Strasser looks at Renault sharply, but
                sees only a noncommittal smile on Renault's face. Laszlo remains standing at the
                table as Strasser and Renault leave.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> This time they really mean to stop me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Victor, I'm afraid for you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We have been in difficult places before, haven't we?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa smiles back at him,
                but her eyes are still troubled. On the floor, CORINA strums a guitar and begins
                her number. Meanwhile, Laszlo looks about with apparent casualness. He sees
                Strasser and Renault whispering together, then notices Berger at the bar.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I must find out what Berger knows. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Be careful. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I will, don't worry.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He rises and goes off. We see Ilsa's troubled profile.
                While Corinna sings, Sam gives a worried glance in Ilsa's direction. Ilsa
                watches him. At the bar, Berger sips a drink. Laszlo walks up and casually takes
                a place at the bar next to Berger.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Mr. Berger, the ring, could I see it again? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Monsieur. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to Sacha</dir> A champagne cocktail, please. 
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo takes the ring and looks at it.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag><descr> in a low voice</descr> I recognize you from the news photographs, Monsieur Laszlo.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> In a concentration camp, one is apt to lose a little weight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> We read five times that you were killed in five different places. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>smiles wryly </descr>As you see, it was true every single time. Thank heaven I found
                    you, Berger. I am looking for a man by the name of Ugarte. He is supposed to
                    help me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Berger shakes his head. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Ugarte cannot even help himself, Monsieur. He is under arrest for murder. He
                    was arrested here tonight.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Laszlo absorbs the shock quietly. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I see. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>with intense devotion</descr> But we who are still free will do all we can. We are
                    organized, Monsieur, underground like everywhere else. Tomorrow night there is a
                    meeting at the Caverne du Bois. If you would come-- </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He stops when Sacha brings
                the drink to Laszlo. Corina finishes her song, and the crowd applauds quite
                enthusiastically. Ilsa sits alone at her table.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to waiter</dir> Will you ask the piano player to come over here, please? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Waiter">WAITER</speaker>
                <diag> Very well, Mademoiselle. 
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault comes up to the bar near Berger and Laszlo.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> How's the jewelry business, Berger? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Er, not so good. to Sacha May I have my check, please? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Too bad you weren't here earlier, Monsieur Laszlo. We had quite a bit of
                    excitement this evening, didn't we, Berger? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ber">BERGER</speaker>
                <diag> Er, yes. Excuse me, gentlemen. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> My bill. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> No. Two champagne cocktails, please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, sir.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam wheels in the piano to Ilsa's table. On his face is that funny
                fear. Ilsa herself is not as self-possessed as she tries to appear. There is
                something behind this, some mystery. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Sam. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Miss Ilsa. I never expected to see you again.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He sits down and is
                ready to play.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It's been a long time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, ma'am. A lot of water under the bridge. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Some of the old songs, Sam. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, ma'am.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Sam begins to play a number. He is nervous, waiting for anything.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Where is Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>evading</descr> I don't know. I ain't seen him all night. . </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Sam looks very
                uncomfortable</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> When will he be back? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Not tonight no more. He ain't coming. Uh, he went home. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Does he always leave so early? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, he never-- well-- <descr>desperately</descr> he's got a girl up at the Blue Parrot. He
                    goes up there all the time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You used to be a much better liar, Sam. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Leave him alone, Miss Ilsa. You're bad luck to him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Play it once, Sam, for old time's sake. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> I don't know what you mean, Miss Ilsa. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Play it, Sam. Play "As Time Goes By." </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> Oh I can't remember it, Miss Ilsa. I'm a little rusty on it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Of course he
                can. He doesn't want to play it. He seems even more scared now.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I'll hum it for you.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa starts to hum. Sam begins to play it very softly.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Sing it, Sam.</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> And Sam sings. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> You must remember this, A kiss is just a kiss, A sigh is just a sigh, The
                    fundamental things apply, As time goes by. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The door to the gambling room opens.
                Rick comes swinging out. He's heard the music and he's livid. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sam">SAM</speaker>
                <diag> And when two lovers woo, They both say I love you, On that you can rely, No
                    matter what the future brings, As time goes by. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks briskly up to the
                piano. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sam, I thought I told you never to play--</diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> As he sees Ilsa he stops short.
                Sam stops playing. Two close-ups reveal Ilsa and Rick seeing each other. Rick
                appears shocked. For a long moment he just looks at her. Sam prepares to move
                the piano away. Renault and Laszlo approach the table from the bar. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to Ilsa</dir> Well, you were asking about Rick and here he is. Mademoiselle, may I
                    present -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Hello, Ilsa. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Hello, Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, you've already met Rick, Mademoiselle? 
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>There's no answer from either.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well then, perhaps you also --- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> -- This is Mr. Laszlo. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> How do you do? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How do you do? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> One hears a great deal about Rick in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And about Victor Laszlo everywhere. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Won't you join us for a drink? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> <descr>laughing</descr> Oh, no, Rick never -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Thanks. I will. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Rick sits down.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well! A precedent is being broken. Er, Emil! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> This is a very interesting cafe. I congratulate you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And I congratulate you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> What for? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Your work. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. I try. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> We all try. You succeed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I can't get over you two. She was asking about you earlier, Rick, in a way
                    that made me extremely jealous. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to Rick</dir> I wasn't sure you were the same. Let's see, the last time we met --
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- It was "La Belle Aurore." </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> How nice. You remembered. But of course, that was the day the Germans marched
                    into Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Not an easy day to forget. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I remember every detail. The Germans wore gray, you wore blue. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. I put that dress away. When the Germans march out, I'll wear it again.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Ricky, you're becoming quite human. I suppose we have to thank you for that,
                    Mademoiselle. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Ilsa, I don't wish to be the one to say it, but it's late. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>glancing at his wristwatch</dir> So it is. And we have a curfew here in Casablanca.
                    It would never do for the Chief of Police to be found drinking after hours and
                    have to fine himself. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick and Ilsa look at each other. Laszlo signals the
                waiter </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I hope we didn't overstay our welcome. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Not at all. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="Waiter">WAITER</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to Laszlo</dir> Your check, sir. Rick takes the check. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> <dir>to waiter</dir> Oh, it's my party. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Another precedent gone. This has been a very interesting evening. I'll call
                    you a cab. Gasoline rationing, time of night.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault leaves.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We'll come again. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Any time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Say goodnight to Sam for me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I will. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> There's still nobody in the world who can play "As Time Goes By" like Sam.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> He hasn't played it in a long time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Ilsa smiles.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight.  </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick and Laszlo nod goodnight to each other. Laszlo and Ilsa start
                to the door as Rick sits down again and stares off in their direction.</dir>
        </scene>

    </body>
</xml>
