<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <metadata>
        <movie>
            <title>Casablanca</title>
            <director>Michael Curtiz</director>
            <wrldPrem>Nov. 26 1942</wrldPrem>
            <loc>WB studios, Burbank, CA</loc>
            <loc>Van Nuys Airport, LA</loc>
            <producer>Hal B. Wallis</producer>
            <producer>Warner Bros</producer>
            <writer>Howard Koch</writer>
            <writer>Julius J. Epstein</writer>
            <writer>Philip G. Epstein</writer>
            <basedOn>Everybody Comes to Rick’s (stage play); written by Murray Burnett and Joan
                Alison</basedOn>
            <composer>Max Steiner</composer>
            <starring>Humphrey Bogart</starring>
            <starring>Ingrid Bergman</starring>
            <starring>Paul Henreid</starring>
            <starring>Conrad Veidt</starring>
            <starring>Claude Rains</starring>
            <cinematography>Arthur Edeson</cinematography>
            <editor>Owen Marks</editor>
        </movie>
        <script>
            <numScenes>77</numScenes>
            <url>https://app.studiobinder.com/company/580e85847e7982164664e844/collab/5eac35a683f7a90bfc3fc810/projects/5de590454f452c09a98e975b/document/5de5904f1fe52b06c2f4bd79/%5Bobject%20Object%5D?utm_source=blog&amp;utm_medium=sb-app-link&amp;utm_campaign=script&amp;utm_term=casablanca-script-breakdown&amp;utm_content=full-script-pdf-download</url>
            <generatedBy>Brent Dunham</generatedBy>
            <date>Dec. 2</date>
            <publisher>StudioBinder Inc.</publisher>
            <website> https://www.studiobinder.com/</website>
        </script>
    </metadata>
    <body>
        <scene n="46">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - GAMBLING ROOM - NIGHT Jan sits at the roulette table. He has
                only three chips left and seems bewildered. As Rick comes up the croupier speaks to
                Jan. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Do you wish to place another bet, sir? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> No, no, I guess not.</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stands behind Jan. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <dir>to Jan</dir> Have you tried twenty-two tonight? I said, twenty-two. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Jan looks at Rick, then at the chips in his hand. He pauses, then puts the chips on
                twenty-two. Rick and the croupier exchange looks. The croupier understands what Rick
                wants him to do. He spins the wheel. Carl follows the proceedings, fascinated. The
                wheel stops spinning.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag><dir> in French</dir> Twenty-two, black, twenty-two. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>A winner. Renault, at a nearby table, takes notice of what is happening. The
                croupier pushes a pile of chips onto twenty-two and Jan reaches for it. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <dir>not even looking at Jan</dir>
                <diag>Leave it there.</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Jan hesitates, then withdraws his hands. Carl continues to watch. The wheel spins.
                Nobody speaks while it spins. It stops.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Twenty-two, black. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Another winner. The croupier shoves a pile of chips toward Jan. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>to Jan</descr> Cash it in and don't come back. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Jan rises to go to the cashier. A CUSTOMER complains to Carl. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cus">CUSTOMER</speaker>
                <diag> Say, are you sure this place is honest? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> fervently Honest! As honest as the day is long!</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Meanwhile, Rick has walked over to the croupier. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How we doing tonight? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Well, a couple of thousand less than I thought there would be. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick smiles slightly and goes toward the door. Annina runs up to him and hugs him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick, I -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- He's just a lucky guy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>solicitously</descr> Monsieur Rick, may I get you a cup of coffee?
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No thanks, Carl. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Rick!</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir> Renault, seeing that Jan has won, gets up from his table to follow Rick. Jan and
                Annina stop him on the way.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Renault, may I -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> -- Oh, not here, please. Come to my office in the morning. We'll do
                    everything business-like. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="jan">JAN</speaker>
                <diag> We'll be there at six. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I'll be there at ten. I am very happy for both of you. Still, it's very
                    strange that you won.</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He looks over and sees Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Well, maybe not so strange. I'll see you in the morning. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ann">ANNINA</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you so much, Captain Renault. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="47">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT At the bar, Carl whispers in Sacha's ear.
                Sacha says "No!" and runs to Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="sac">SACHA</speaker>
                <diag> Boss, you've done a beautiful thing.</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He kisses Rick on both cheeks.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go away, you crazy Russian!</diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Carl pours a brandy for Rick. Pretending not to do so, Rick glances in Ilsa's
                direction. Renault comes up to him. \</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> As I suspected, you're a rank sentimentalist. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yeah? Why? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>chidingly</descr> Why do you interfere with my little romances? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Put it down as a gesture to love. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>good-naturedly</descr> Well, I forgive you this time. But I'll be in
                    tomorrow night with a breathtaking blonde, and it will make me very happy if she
                    loses. Uh huh! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He smiles and walks away. Laszlo comes up to Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Blaine, I wonder if I could talk to you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go ahead. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Well, isn't there some other place? It's rather confidential, what I have to
                    say. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My office. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Right. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="48">
            <camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT Rick and Laszlo sit and discuss Laszlo's
                dilemma. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> You must know it's very important I get out of Casablanca. It's my privilege
                    to be one of the leaders of a great movement. You know what I have been doing.
                    You know what it means to the work, to the lives of thousands and thousands of
                    people that I be free to reach America and continue my work. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm not interested in politics. The problems of the world are not in my
                    department. I'm a saloon keeper. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> My friends in the underground tell me that you have quite a record. You ran
                    guns to Ethiopia. You fought against the fascists in Spain. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> What of it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Isn't it strange that you always happened to be fighting on the side of the
                    underdog? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. I found that a very expensive hobby, too. But then I never was much of a
                    businessman. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick gets up, as does Laszlo.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Are you enough of a businessman to appreciate an offer of a hundred thousand
                    francs? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I appreciate it, but I don't accept it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I'll raise it to two hundred thousand. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> My friend, you could make it a million francs, or three, my answer would
                    still be the same. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> There must be some reason why you won't let me have them. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> There is. I suggest that you ask your wife. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I beg your pardon? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I said, ask your wife. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> My wife?</diag>
                <dir>Laszlo looks at him, puzzled. </dir> </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick and Laszlo hear MALE VOICES singing downstairs. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="49">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT A group of German officers stand around
                the piano singing the "Wacht am Rhein." </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="50">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - NIGHT Rick stands at the balcony outside his
                office and watches the Germans below. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="51">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT At the bar, Renault watches with raised
                eyebrow. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="52">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - NIGHT Laszlo's lips are very tight as he listens
                to the song. He starts down the step. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="53">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Laszlo passes the table where Ilsa sits
                and goes straight to the orchestra. Yvonne, sitting at a table with her German
                officer, stares down into her drink. Laszlo speaks to the orchestra. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Play the Marseillaise! Play it! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Members of the orchestra glance toward the steps, toward Rick, who nods to them.
                Laszlo and Corina sing as they start to play. Strasser conducts the German singing
                in an attempt to drown out the competition. People in the cafe begin to sing the
                "Marseillaise." After a while, Strasser and his officers give up and sit down. The
                "Marseillaise" continues, however. Yvonne jumps up and sings with tears in her eyes.
                Ilsa, overcome with emotion, looks proudly at Laszlo, who sings with passion.
                Finally the whole cafe stands, singing, their faces aglow. The song finishes on a
                high, triumphant note. Yvonne's face is exalted. She deliberately faces the alcove
                where the Germans are watching. She SHOUTS at the top of her lungs.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="yvo">YVONNE</speaker>
                <diag> Vive La France! Vive la democracie! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROWD</speaker>
                <diag> Vive La France! Vive la democracie! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>People clap and cheer. Strasser is very angry. He strides across the floor toward
                Renault who is standing at the bar.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> You see what I mean? If Laszlo's presence in a cafe can inspire this
                    unfortunate demonstration, what more will his presence in Casablanca bring on? I
                    advise that this place be shut up at once. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>innocently</descr> But everybody's having such a good time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, much too good a time. The place is to be closed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> But I have no excuse to close it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>snapping</descr> Find one. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Several French officers surround Laszlo, offering him a drink. Renault thinks a
                moment, then blows a loud BLAST on his whistle. The room grows quiet, all eyes turn
                toward Renault.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>loudly</descr> Everybody is to leave here immediately! This cafe is
                    closed until further notice! Clear the room at once! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>An angry murmur starts among the crowd. People get up and begin to leave. Rick
                comes quickly up to Renault.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How can you close me up? On what grounds? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I am shocked, shocked to find that gambling is going on in here! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>This display of nerve leaves Rick at a loss. The croupier comes out of the gambling
                room and up to Renault. He hands him a roll of bills.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="cro">CROUPIER</speaker>
                <diag> Your winnings, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. Thank you very much. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He turns to the crowd again.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Everybody out at once! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir> As the cafe empties, Strasser approaches Ilsa. His manner is abrupt but
                cordial.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Mademoiselle, after this disturbance it is not safe for Laszlo to stay in
                    Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> This morning you implied it was not safe for him to leave Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> That is also true, except for one destination, to return to occupied France.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Occupied France? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Uh huh. Under a safe conduct from me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>with intensity</descr> What value is that? You may recall what German
                    guarantees have been worth in the past. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> There are only two other alternatives for him. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> What are they? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> It is possible the French authorities will find a reason to put him in the
                    concentration camp here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> And the other alternative? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> My dear Mademoiselle, perhaps you have already observed that in Casablanca,
                    human life is cheap. Good night, Mademoiselle. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>She looks at him, understanding what he means. He bows and exits as Laszlo arrives
                at the table. They start out of the cafe.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> What happened with Rick? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We'll discuss it later. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="54">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. HOTEL HALLWAY - NIGHT Ilsa and Laszlo walk to their room. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="55">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. HOTEL ROOM - NIGHT Laszlo switches on the light as they enter. While Ilsa
                takes off some jewelry he walks to the window and peers out into the darkeness.
                Below and across the street, a man stands under an arch. Laszlo watches him, then
                draws down the shade. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Our faithful friend is still there. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Victor, please, don't go to the underground meeting tonight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>soberly</descr> I must. Besides, it isn't often that a man has a chance
                    to display heroics before his wife. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He crosses to a table, takes a cigarette from a box, and strikes a match.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Don't joke. After Major Strasser's warning tonight, I am frightened. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> To tell you the truth, I am frightened too. Shall I remain here in our hotel
                    room hiding, or shall I carry on the best I can? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He lights the cigarette.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Whatever I'd say, you'd carry on. Victor, why don't you tell me about Rick?
                    What did you find out? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Apparently he has the letters. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> But no intention of selling them. One would think if sentiment wouldn't
                    persuade him, money would. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa is now noticeably uncomfortable. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Did he give any reason? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> He suggested I ask you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Ask me? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. He said, "Ask your wife." I don't know why he said that. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo turns off the light. Ilsa walks over to the couch and sits down. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Well, our friend outside will think we've retired by now. I'll be going in a
                    few minutes. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He sits down on the couch next to her. A silence falls between them. It grows
                strained. Finally. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Ilsa, I -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> -- Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> When I was in the concentration camp, were you lonely in Paris? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa still cannot look at him.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Victor, I was. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>sympathetically</descr> I know how it is to be lonely. <descr>very
                        quietly </descr>Is there anything you wish to tell me? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> s<descr>peaking low</descr> No, Victor, there isn't. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I love you very much, my dear. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa finally turns to look at Laszlo. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, Yes I know. Victor, whatever I do, will you believe that I, that --
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> -- You don't even have to say it. I'll believe. Goodnight, dear. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He bends down and kisses her cheek.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>She watches him go. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Victor! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>She gets up and follows him to the door. He opens it. In the slit of light from the
                hall we see Ilsa's face, now strained and worried. She hesitates for a moment, then. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Be careful. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Of course, I'll be careful. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He kisses her on the cheek and goes out the door. She stands there for a few
                seconds, then crosses to look out of the window. The figure in the archway is gone.
                She sees Victor walking down the street and closes the blind again. Ilsa gets a
                cloak from the bedroom, and leaves the hotel room. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="56">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick and Carl sit by the bar and look over
                ledgers. Carl is busy figuring. He looks up at Rick. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Well, you are in pretty good shape, Herr Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How long can I afford to stay closed? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, two weeks, maybe three. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Maybe I won't have to. A bribe has worked before. In the meantime, everybody
                    stays on salary. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, thank you, Herr Rick. Sacha will be happy to hear it. I owe him money.
                </diag>
                <dir>Carl laughs. </dir>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Now you finish locking up, will you, Carl? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> I will. Then I am going to the meeting of the -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>interrupting</descr> -- Don't tell me where you're going. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> I won't. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Goodnight, Monsieur Rick. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks up the stairs to his apartment.</dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="57">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT Rick opens the door and goes inside the
                dark room. Light from the hall reveals a figure by the window. He lights a small
                lamp. Ilsa faces him, her face white but determined. Rick pauses for a moment in
                astonishment. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> How did you get in? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> The stairs from the street. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa comes over to meet him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I told you this morning you'd come around, but this is a little ahead of
                    schedule. Well, won't you sit down? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Richard, I had to see you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You use "Richard" again? We're back in Paris. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Your unexpected visit isn't connected by any chance with the letters of
                    transit? It seems that as long as I have those letters I'll never be lonely.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You can ask any price you want, but you must give me those letters. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I went through all that with your husband. It's no deal. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I know how you feel about me, but I'm asking you to put your feelings aside
                    for something more important. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Do I have to hear again what a great man your husband is? What an important
                    cause he's fighting for? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It was your cause, too. In your own way, you were fighting for the same
                    thing. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm not fighting for anything anymore, except myself. I'm the only cause I'm
                    interested in. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He walks over to the window and Ilsa follows. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Richard, Richard, we loved each other once. If those days meant anything at
                    all to you -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>interrupting, harshly</descr> -- I wouldn't bring up Paris if I were you.
                    It's poor salesmanship. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Please. Please listen to me. If you knew what really happened, if you only
                    knew the truth -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>cutting in</descr> -- I wouldn't believe you, no matter what you told me.
                    You'd say anything now to get what you want. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks over to a table and opens a cigarette box, but finds it empty.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> You want to feel sorry for yourself, don't you? With so much at stake, all
                    you can think of is your own feelings. One woman has hurt you, and you take
                    revenge on the rest of the world. You're a, you're a coward, and a weakling. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>There are tears in her eyes now. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> No. Oh, Richard, I'm sorry. I'm sorry, but, but you, you are our last hope.
                    If you don't help us, Victor Laszlo will die in Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> What of it? I'm going to die in Casablanca. It's a good spot for it. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He turns away to light a cigarette, then back to Ilsa. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Now if you -- </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He stops short as he sees Ilsa holding a small revolver in her hand. It's pointed
                directly at him.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> -- All right. I tried to reason with you. I tried everything. Now I want
                    those letters. Get them for me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I don't have to. I've got them right here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Put them on the table. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>shaking his head</descr> No. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> For the last time, put them on the table. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> If Laszlo and the cause mean so much to you, you won't stop at anything. All
                    right, I'll make it easier for you. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He moves closer to her.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Go ahead and shoot. You'll be doing me a favor. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Her hand drops down, and there are tears in her eyes again. She turns and walks
                away from him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Richard, I tried to stay away. I thought I would never see you again, that
                    you were out of my life. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick follows her and takes her in his arms. He presses her tight to him. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> The day you left, if you knew what I went through! If you knew how much I
                    loved you, how much I still love you! </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick kisses her passionately. She is lost in his embrace. </dir>

        </scene>
        <scene n="58">
            <camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - LATER From his window, Rick watches the
                revolving beacon light at the airport. Ilsa sits on the couch. On a table before her
                rests a bottle of champagne along with two half-filled glasses. Rick walks over to
                her. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And then? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> It wasn't long after we were married that Victor went back to Czechoslovakia.
                    They needed him in Prague, but there the Gestapo were waiting for him. Just a
                    two-line item in the paper: "Victor Laszlo apprehended. Sent to concen-tration
                    camp." I was frantic. For months I tried to get word. Then it came. He was dead,
                    shot trying to escape. I was lonely. I had nothing. Not even hope. Then I met
                    you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Why weren't you honest with me? Why did you keep your marriage a secret? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick sits down with Ilsa. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, it wasn't my secret, Richard. Victor wanted it that way. Not even our
                    closest friends knew about our marriage. That was his way of protecting me. I
                    knew so much about his work, and if the Gestapo found out I was his wife it
                    would be dangerous for me and for those working with me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> When did you first find out he was alive? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Just before you and I were to leave Paris together. A friend came and told me
                    that Victor was alive. They were hiding him in a freight car on the outskirts of
                    Paris. He was sick, he needed me. I wanted to tell you, but I, I didn't care. I
                    knew, I knew you wouldn't have left Paris, and the Gestapo would have caught
                    you. So I-- well, well, you know the rest. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Huh. But it's still a story without an ending. What about now? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Now? I don't know. I know that I'll never have the strength to leave you
                    again. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And Laszlo? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, you'll help him now, Richard, won't you? You'll see that he gets out?
                    Then he'll have his work, all that he's been living for. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All except one. He won't have you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa puts her head on Rick's shoulder. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I can't fight it anymore. I ran away from you once. I can't do it again. Oh,
                    I don't know what's right any longer. You'll have to think for both of us, for
                    all of us. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All right, I will. Here's looking at you, kid. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> I wish I didn't love you so much. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>She snuggles closer to Rick. </dir>

        </scene>
        <scene n="59">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT Laszlo and Carl make their way through the darkness
                toward a side entrance of Rick's. They run inside the entryway. The headlights of a
                speeding police car sweep toward them. They flatten themselves against a wall to
                avoid detection. The lights move past them. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> I think we lost them. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes. I'm afraid they caught some of the others. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Come inside. Come. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="60">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Laszlo and Carl enter and cross toward the
                bar, out of breath from their exertion. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Come inside. I will help you. Come in here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Carl goes behind the bar.</dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> I will give you some water. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="61">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT/EXT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT Rick and Ilsa hear voices below. Rick
                crosses to the door. He opens it just enough to see below, and turns off the light.
                Ilsa stands just in back of him. She makes a move as if to go out to the balcony but
                Rick's pushes her back. She withdraws behind the door. Rick walks out to the balcony
                railing. </setting>
        </scene>
            <scene n="62">
                <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - BALCONY - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick sees Carl attending to
                    Laszlo, who appears to be injured. </setting>
                <sp>
                    <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                    <diag> Carl, what happened? </diag>
                    <dir>Both Carl and Laszlo look up. </dir>
                </sp>
           <!--  </scene>
           ebb: This close-tag seemed out of place so I commented it out.
           Just double-check where scene 62 ends in your source? 
           -->
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>excitedly</descr> The police break up our meeting. Herr Rick! We escaped
                    in the last moment. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Come up here a minute. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Carl looks up wonderingly, then starts toward the stairway. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I come. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I want you to turn out the light in the rear entrance. It might attract the
                    police. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> But Sacha always puts out that light -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Tonight he forgot. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I come, I will do it. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Carl climbs the stairs.</dir>

        </scene>
        <scene n="63">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - APARTMENT - NIGHT Carl enters Rick's apartment and sees
                Ilsa. He looks at Rick and says nothing. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>in a low voice</descr> I want you to take Miss Lund home. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="carl">CARL</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, sir. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="64">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick comes down the stairs. Laszlo wraps
                one of the small bar towels around his cut wrist. Rick looks questioningly at the
                injured hand. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> It's nothing. Just a little cut. We had to get through a window. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick walks to the bar, picks up a bottle, and pours a drink. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, this might come in handy. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Had a close one, eh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, rather. Laszlo takes a drink. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Don't you sometimes wonder if it's worth all this? I mean what you're
                    fighting for? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> We might as well question why we breathe. If we stop breathing, we'll die. If
                    we stop fighting our enemies, the world will die. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> What of it? Then it'll be out of it's misery. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick reaches in his jacket for his cigarette case, opens it, and takes out a
                cigarette. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> You know how you sound, Monsieur Blaine? Like a man who's trying to convince
                    himself of something he doesn't believe in his heart. Each of us has a destiny,
                    for good or for evil. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I get the point. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick lights his cigarette.</dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I wonder if you do. I wonder if you know that you're trying to escape from
                    yourself and that you'll never succeed. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You seem to know all about my destiny. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I know a good deal more about you than you suspect. I know, for instance,
                    that you are in love with a woman. It is perhaps strange that we both should be
                    in love with the same woman. The first evening I came here in this cafe, I knew
                    there was something between you and Ilsa. Since no one is to blame, I, I demand
                    no explanation. I ask only one thing. You won't give me the letters of transit.
                    All right. But I want my wife to be safe. I ask you as a favor to use the
                    letters to take her away from Casablanca. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You love her that much? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Apparently you think of me only as the leader of a cause. Well, I am also a
                    human being. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He looks away for a moment. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I love her that much. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Suddenly there is a CRASH at the door of the cafe, followed by the forced entry of
                several gendarmes. A French officer walks in and addresses Laszlo. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> Mr. Laszlo? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Yes? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> You will come with us. We have a warrant for your arrest. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> On what charge? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="foff">FRENCH OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag> Captain Renault will discuss that with you later. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It seems that destiny has taken a hand. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo looks for a moment at Rick, then in dignified silence crosses to the
                officer. Together they walk toward the door. Rick's eyes follow them, but his
                expression reveals nothing of his feelings. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="65">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RENAULT'S OFFICE - MORNING Renault sits at his desk and smokes while Rick
                nervously fingers his hat. They're interrupted by an orderly. Renault hands some
                forms to the orderly, who then exits, and the conversation continues. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> But you haven't any actual proof, and you know it. This isn't Germany or
                    occupied France. All you can do is fine him a few thousand francs and give him
                    thirty days. You might as well let him go now. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Ricky, I'd advise you not to be too interested in what happens to Laszlo. If
                    by any chance you were to help him escape -- </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- What makes you think I'd stick my neck out for Laszlo? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Because one, you've bet ten thousand francs he'd escape. Two, you have the
                    letters of transit, now don't bother to deny it. And, well, you might do it
                    simply because you don't like Strasser's looks. As a matter of fact, I don't
                    like him either. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, they're all excellent reasons. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Don't count too much on my friendship, Ricky. In this matter I'm powerless.
                    Besides, I might lose ten thousand francs. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You're not very subtle, but you are effective. I, I get the point. Yes, I
                    have the letters, but I intend using them myself. I'm leaving Casablanca on
                    tonight's plane, the last plane. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Huh? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And I'm taking a friend with me. One you'll appreciate. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> What friend? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Ilsa Lund. <descr>pause</descr> That ought to put your mind to rest about my
                    helping Laszlo escape. The last man I want to see in America. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> You didn't come here to tell me this. You have the letters of transit. You
                    can fill in your name and hers and leave any time you please. Why are you
                    interested in what happens to Laszlo? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Renault gets out of his chair and crosses to the front of his desk. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'm not. But I am interested in what happens to Ilsa and me. We have a legal
                    right to go, that's true. But people have been held in Casablanca in spite of
                    their legal rights. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault retrieves a fresh cigarette from a box on his desk. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> What makes you think we want to hold you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault chain-lights his new cigarette with the old one. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Ilsa is Laszlo's wife. She probably knows things that Strasser would like to
                    know. Louis, I'll make a deal with you. Instead of this petty charge you have
                    against him, you can get something really big, something that would chuck him in
                    a concentration camp for years. That would be quite a feather in your cap,
                    wouldn't it? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> It certainly would. Germany-- Vichy would be very grateful. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Then release him. You be at my place a half hour before the plane leaves. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Renault sits back down in his chair. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'll arrange to have Laszlo come there to pick up the letters of transit, and
                    that'll give you the criminal grounds on which to make the arrest. You get him,
                    and we get away. To the Germans that last will be just a minor annoyance.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>puzzled</descr> There's still something about this business I don't quite
                    understand. Miss Lund, she's very beautiful, yes, but you were never interested
                    in any woman. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, she isn't just any woman. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick stares at the floor, then looks back up at Renault. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I see. How do I know you'll keep your end of the bargain? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I'll make the arrangements right now with Laszlo in the visitor's pen.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Ricky, I'm going to miss you. Apparently you're the only one in Casablanca
                    who has even less scruples than I. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, thanks. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Go ahead, Ricky. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Renault presses a button on his desk, triggering a BUZZER. The door to Renault's
                office opens. Rick rises to go.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And by the way, call off your watchdogs when you let him go. I don't want
                    them around this afternoon. I'm taking no chances, Louis, not even with you.
                </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="66">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. THE BLUE PARROT - DAY A waiter brings tea to Rick and Ferrari, who sit
                alone at a table in a secluded nook off the main room. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Shall we draw up the papers, or is our handshake good enough? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> It's certainly not good enough. But since I'm in a hurry, it'll have to do.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ferrari pours a cup for Rick, who takes a sip. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Ah, to get out of Casablanca and go to America! You're a lucky man. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, by the way, my agreement with Sam's always been that he gets twenty-five
                    percent of the profits. That still goes. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Hmmm. I happen to know that he gets ten percent. But he's worth twenty-five.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> And Abdul and Carl and Sacha, they stay with the place, or I don't sell.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> Of course they stay. Rick's wouldn't be Rick's without them. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Well, so long. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick gets up, followed by Ferrari. They shake hands to seal the deal. He walks to
                the door, then stops and turns around. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Don't forget, you owe Rick's a hundred cartons of American cigarettes.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="fer">FERRARI</speaker>
                <diag> I shall remember to pay it-- to myself. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Rick leaves. Ferrari picks up a fly swatter from the table and swats at a fly.
            </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="67">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHT A car pulls quickly to a stop just outside the cafe.
                On the door a huge placard reads: CLOSED By Order of the Prefect of Police
            </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="68">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT Rick sits at a table inside and reads the
                letters of transit. He hears a KNOCK on the door and puts them away in his pocket.
                He opens the door and Renault walks in. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> You're late. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I was informed just as Laszlo was about to leave the hotel, so I knew I'd be
                    on time. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I thought I asked you to tie up your watchdogs. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, he won't be followed here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault looks around the empty cafe. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> You know, this place will never be the same without you, Ricky. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I know what you mean, but I've already spoken to Ferrari. You'll still
                    win at roulette. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Is everything ready? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick points at his breast pocket. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I have the letters right here. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Tell me, when we searched the place, where were they? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Sam's piano. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Serves me right for not being musical. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>They hear the CRUNCH of tires as a car pull up. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh. Here they are. You'd better wait in my office. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault walks up the stairs to Rick's office. </dir>

        </scene>
        <scene n="69">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. RICK'S CAFE - NIGHTLaszlo pays the cab driver. Ilsa quickly walks toward
                the entrance. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>to driver</descr> Here. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="70">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHTRick opens the door. Ilsa rushes in. Her
                intensity reveals the strain she is under. Rick grabs her by both arms and pulls her
                close. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Richard, Victor thinks I'm leaving with him. Haven't you told him? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> No, not yet. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa"> ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> But it's all right, isn't it? You were able to arrange everything? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Everything is quite all right. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, Rick! She looks at him with a vaguely questioning look. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> We'll tell him at the airport. The less time to think, the easier for all of
                    us. Please trust me. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa pauses and looks at Rick, unsure for a moment. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker>
                <diag> Yes, I will. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Laszlo comes in and closes the door behind himself.</dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> Monsieur Blaine, I don't know how to thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, save it. We've still lots of things to do. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>They all walk towards the bar. Laszlo deposits his hat on a a nearby table. </dir>
        </scene>
        <scene n="70">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - OFFICE - NIGHT Renault opens the office door and peers down
                at the proceedings. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="72">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. RICK'S CAFE - MAIN ROOM - NIGHT </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> I brought the money, Monsieur Blaine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Keep it. You'll need it in America. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> But we made a deal. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>cutting him short</descr> Oh, never mind about that. You won't have any
                    trouble in Lisbon, will you? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker>
                <diag> No. It's all arranged. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Good. I've got the letters right here, all made out in blank. He takes out
                    the letters. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> All you have to do is fill in the signatures. He hands them to Laszlo, who
                    takes them gratefully. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Victor Laszlo! </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>All three hear footsteps and turn to see Renault walking towards them from the
                bottom of the stairs. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Victor Laszlo, you are under arrest -- <descr>as he walks toward them</descr>
                    on a charge of accessory to the murder of the couriers from whom these letters
                    were stolen. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Ilsa and Laszlo are both caught completely off guard. They turn towards Rick,
                bewildered. Horror is in Ilsa's eyes. Renault takes the letters. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Oh, you are surprised about my friend Ricky? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Obviously the situation delights Renault. He smiles as he turns toward Rick. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> The explanation is quite simple. Love, it seems, has triumphed over virtue.
                    Thank -- </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Suddenly the smile fades. In Rick's hand is a gun, which he levels at
                Renault.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> -- Not so fast, Louis. Nobody's going to be arrested. Not for a while yet.
                </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Have you taken leave of your senses? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I have. Sit down over there. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Put that gun down. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Renault then walks toward Rick. Rick puts out his arm to stop him. </dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Louis, I wouldn't like to shoot you, but I will, if you take one more step. </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>Renault halts for a moment and studies Rick.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Under the circumstances, I will sit down. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He walks to a table and sits. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>sharply</descr> Keep your hands on the table. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He takes out a cigarette case. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> I suppose you know what you're doing, but I wonder if you realize what this
                    means? </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> I do. We've got plenty of time to discuss that later. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> Call off your watch-dogs you said. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker>
                <diag> Just the same, you call the airport and let me hear you tell them. And
                    remember, this gun's pointed right at your heart. </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag> That is my least vulnerable spot. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As Renault picks up the phone and dials, Rick takes back the letters. </dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>into phone </descr> Hello, is this the airport? This is Captain Renault
                    speaking. There'll be two letters of transit for the Lisbon plane. There's to be
                    no trouble about them. Good. </diag>
            </sp>
        </scene>
        <scene n="73">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>INT. GERMAN CONSULATE - NIGHT Strasser is on the phone. </setting>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> Hello? Hello? </diag>

            </sp>
            <dir>He hangs up the receiver and presses a BUZZER on his desk. An officer quickly
                enters.</dir>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>to officer</descr> My car, quickly! </diag>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker who="off">OFFICER</speaker>
                <diag>
                    <descr>saluting</descr> Zu Befehl, Herr Major. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The officer exits and Strasser resumes on the telephone.</dir>

            <sp>
                <speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker>
                <diag> This is Major Strasser. Have a squad of police meet me at the airport at
                    once. At once! Do you hear? </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>He hangs up the receiver and, grabbing for his cap, hurriedly exits. </dir>

        </scene>
        <scene n="74">
            <camera>DISSOLVE TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. AIRPORT - NIGHT he entire airport is surrounded by a heavy fog. The
                outline of the transport plane is barely visible. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="75"><camera>CUT TO:</camera> <setting>INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT</setting> <dir>A uniformed
                ORDERLY uses a telephone near the hangar door. On the airfield a transport plane is
                being readied.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ord">ORDERLY</speaker>
                <diag> Hello. Hello, radio tower? Lisbon plane taking off in ten minutes. East
                    runway. Visibility: one and one half miles. Light ground fog. Depth of fog:
                    approximately 500. Ceiling: unlimited. Thank you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> He hangs up and moves to a car that has just pulled up outside the hangar. Renault
                gets out while the orderly stands at attention. He's closely followed by Rick, right
                hand in the pocket of his trench coat, covering Renault with a gun. Laszlo and Ilsa
                emerge from the rear of the car. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>indicating the orderly</descr> Louis, have your man go with Mr. Laszlo
                    and take care of his luggage. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>bowing ironically</descr> Certainly Rick, anything you say. <descr>to
                        orderly</descr> Find Mr. Laszlo's luggage and put it it on the plane.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ord">ORDERLY</speaker><diag> Yes, sir. This way please. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The orderly escorts Laszlo off in the direction of the plane. Rick takes the
                letters of transit out of his pocket and hands them to Renault, who turns and walks
                toward the hangar.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> If you don't mind, you fill in the names.
                    That will make it even more official. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> You think of everything, don't you?
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>quietly</descr> And the names are Mr. and Mrs. Victor Laszlo. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault stops dead in his tracks, and turns around. Both Ilsa and Renault look at
                Rick with astonishment.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> But why my name, Richard? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Because you're getting on that plane.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>confused</descr> I don't understand. What about you? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> I'm staying here with him 'til the plane
                    gets safely away. <dir>Rick's intention suddenly dawns on Ilsa.</dir>
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> No, Richard, no. What has happened to you?
                    Last night we said -- </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> -- Last night we said a great many things.
                    You said I was to do the thinking for both of us. Well, I've done a lot of it
                    since then and it all adds up to one thing. You're getting on that plane with
                    Victor where you belong. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>protesting</descr> But Richard, no, I, I -- </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> -- You've got to listen to me. Do you have
                    any idea what you'd have to look forward to if you stayed here? Nine chances out
                    of ten we'd both wind up in a concentration camp. Isn't that true, Louis?
                </diag>
            </sp><dir>Renault countersigns the papers. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> I'm afraid Major Strasser would insist.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> You're saying this only to make me go.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> I'm saying it because it's true. Inside of
                    us we both know you belong with Victor. You're part of his work, the thing that
                    keeps him going. If that plane leaves the ground and you're not with him, you'll
                    regret it. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> No. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Maybe not today, maybe not tomorrow, but
                    soon, and for the rest of your life. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> But what about us? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> We'll always have Paris. We didn't have,
                    we'd lost it, until you came to Casablanca. We got it back last night.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> And I said I would never leave you.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> And you never will. But I've got a job to
                    do, too. Where I'm going you can't follow. What I've got to do you can't be any
                    part of. Ilsa, I'm no good at being noble, but it doesn't take much to see that
                    the problems of three little people don't amount to a hill of beans in this
                    crazy world. Someday you'll understand that. Now, now-- </diag>
            </sp><dir>Ilsa's eyes well up with tears. Rick puts his hand to her chin and raises her
                face to meet his own. ]</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Here's looking at you, kid.
            </diag></sp></scene>
        <scene n="76">
            <camera>CUT TO:</camera>
            <setting>EXT. ROAD - NIGHT Major Strasser drives at break-neck speed towards the
                airport. He HONKS his horn furiously. </setting>
        </scene>
        <scene n="77"><camera>CUT TO:</camera><setting> INT/EXT. AIRPORT HANGAR - NIGHT </setting><dir>Laszlo returns.
                Rick walks into the hangar and Renault hands him the letters. He walks back out to
                Laszlo.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag> Everything in order? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> All except one thing. There's something you
                    should know before you leave. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>sensing what is coming</descr> Monsieur Blaine, I don't ask you to
                    explain anything. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> I'm going to anyway, because it may make a
                    difference to you later on. You said you knew about Ilsa and me. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag> Yes. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> But you didn't know she was at my place
                    last night when you were. She came there for the letters of transit. Isn't that
                    true, Ilsa? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>facing</descr> Laszlo Yes. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>forcefully</descr> She tried everything to get them, and nothing worked.
                    She did her best to convince me that she was still in love with me, but that was
                    all over long ago. For your sake, she pretended it wasn't, and I let her
                    pretend. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag> I understand. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Here it is. </diag>
            </sp><dir>Rick hands the letters to Laszlo. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag> Thanks. I appreciate it. </diag>
            </sp><dir>Laszlo extends his hand to Rick, who grasps it firmly. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="las">LASZLO</speaker><diag> And welcome back to the fight. This time I
                    know our side will win. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>On the airfield the airplane engine TURNS OVER and the propellers start turning.
                They all turn to see the plane readying for take-off. Ilsa looks at Rick and he
                returns her stare with a blank expression. He then glances at Laszlo, as does Ilsa.
                Then Laszlo breaks the silence. </dir> <sp><speaker who="las"
                    >LASZLO</speaker><diag> Are you ready Ilsa? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ilsa">ILSA</speaker><diag> Yes, I'm ready. <descr>to Rick</descr>
                    Goodbye, Rick. God bless you. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> You better hurry, or you'll miss that
                    plane. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Rick watches as Ilsa and Laszlo walk very deliberately towards the plane.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Well I was right. You are a
                    sentimentalist. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Stay where you are. I don't know what
                    you're talking about.</diag>
            </sp><dir>Rick puts a cigarette in his mouth. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> What you just did for Laszlo, and that
                    fairy tale that you invented to send Ilsa away with him. I know a little about
                    women, my friend. She went, but she knew you were lying. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Anyway, thanks for helping me out.
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> I suppose you know this isn't going to be
                    pleasant for either of us, especially for you. I'll have to arrest you of
                    course. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> As soon as the plane goes, Louis. </diag>
            </sp><dir>The door to the plane is closed by an attendant and it slowly taxies down the
                field. Suddenly a speeding car comes to a stop outside the hangar. Strasser alights
                from the car and runs toward Renault. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker><diag> What is the meaning of that phone call?
                </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Victor Laszlo is on that plane. </diag>
            </sp><dir>Renault nods toward the field. Strasser turns to see the plane taxiing towards
                the runway. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker><diag> Why do you stand here? Why don't you
                    stop him? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Ask Monsieur Rick. </diag>
            </sp><dir>Strasser looks briefly at Rick, then makes a step towards the telephone just
                inside the hangar door. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Get away from that phone. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Strasser stops in his tracks, looks at Rick, and sees that he is armed.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker><diag>
                    <descr>steely</descr> I would advise you not to interfere. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> I was willing to shoot Captain Renault, and
                    I'm willing to shoot you. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir> Strasser watches the plane in agony. His eyes dart towards the telephone. He runs
                toward it and desperately grabs the receiver.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="str"> STRASSER</speaker><diag> Hello? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Put that phone down! </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="str">STRASSER</speaker><diag> Get me the Radio Tower! </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Put it down! </diag>
            </sp><dir>Strasser, one hand holding the receiver, pulls out a pistol with the other
                hand, and SHOOTS quickly at Rick. The bullet misses its mark. Rick now SHOOTS at
                Strasser, who crumples to the ground. At the sound of an approaching car both men
                turn. A police car SPEEDS in and comes to a stop near Renault. Four gendarmes
                hurriedly jump out. In the distance the plane turns onto the runway. The gendarmes
                run to Renault. The first one hurriedly salutes him. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker><diag> Mon Capitaine! </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Major Strasser's been shot. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>Renault pauses and looks at Rick. Rick returns Renault's gaze with expressionless
                eyes.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Round up the usual suspects. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="gen">GENDARME</speaker><diag> Oui, mon Capitaine. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The gendarmes take Strasser's body away and then drive off. Renault walks inside
                the hangar, picks up a bottle of Vichy water, and opens it. </dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Well, Rick, you're not only a
                    sentimentalist, but you've become a patriot. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Maybe, but it seemed like a good time to
                    start. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> I think perhaps you're right. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>As he pours the water into a glass, Renault sees the Vichy label and quickly DROPS
                the bottle into a trash basket which he then KICKS over. He walks over and stands
                beside Rick. They both watch the plane take off, maintaining their gaze until it
                disappears into the clouds. Rick and Louis slowly walk away from the hangar toward
                the runway.</dir>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> It might be a good idea for you to
                    disappear from Casablanca for a while. There's a Free French garrison over at
                    Brazzaville. I could be induced to arrange a passage. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> My letter of transit? I could use a trip.
                    But it doesn't make any difference about our bet. You still owe me ten thousand
                    francs. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> And that ten thousand francs should pay
                    our expenses. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Our expenses? </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="ren">RENAULT</speaker><diag> Uh huh. </diag></sp>
            <sp><speaker who="rick">RICK</speaker><diag> Louis, I think this is the beginning of a
                    beautiful friendship. </diag>
            </sp>
            <dir>The two walk off together into the night. FADE OUT: THE END </dir></scene>

    </body>
</xml>
