<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Letters.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <letter n="5"> No one drives very fast- quite the opposite in fact, if another car is coming <corr type="spell err">t owrd</corr> us one or the other drive will quickly look the situation over and back up into a place wide enough so the other car can pass. Many tourists from these countries and <corr type="overlap" what="g/l"><place name="Eng">Englland</place></corr> etc seem to travel the sturdy little <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr> steamers and between <corr type="spell err" aka="fjords">fjoyds</corr> by bus. The Belgians build a smallish red bus with a good deal of glass- high wide windows and glass over the roof- where shirred <corr type="spell err" aka="curtains">curtaions</corr> can be pulled over when the sun is too hot.
BUT the great HUGE busses go skimmimg
along over these hair-raising <corr type="cross out">t</corr>roads as well. The steamer pick up and carry along, all sorts of merchandise for the people living in the small villages. Also all mail as well as <corr type="spell err" aka="supplies">suppies</corr> for the hotels and little inns are del<corr type="miss text"/>livered in this manner. At <pen type="handwrit"><place name="Kaup">Kaupanger</place> 2.30</pen> had a sort of lunch in a <corr type="miss text" aka="brand">bran</corr> new lunch room,<corr type="spell err">iwith</corr> a porch on second floor where the tourists were busy with coffee etc. In a little shop below I got some post cards also a funny wooden hook(to copy for the bazaar in Greenwich' )Took funny little ferry</letter>
    <letter n="6"><place name="Sog">Sogndal</place> to <place name="Loft">Loftsnes</place>- about 5 minutes across
Run attached to wire cables. <pen type="doodle">Doodle of figure, presumably a girl, holding something in her arms is featured on the right side of the page.</pen>
A bridge is BEING
built across this narrow place. A little girl was selling plums in tiny paper<corr type="miss text"/>cornicopias.
Very sweet and good.
after continuing
<corr type="spell err" aka="along">alo ng</corr> the "river" we took the larger steamer on which were sandwiched in about a dozen cars plus a lot of people - and proceeded up the big <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fioyd</corr>. Grand views at <corr type="spell err" aka="every">erevy</corr> turn. And
of course many waterfalls. <pen type="doodle">The left side of the page features a doodle of a factory chimney with the caption "Curious factory chimney by the way."</pen>This is the
deepest and largest <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr> as before mentioned'
Arrived at <place name="Gud">Gudvangen</place>
end of <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr>- that is, end of this "arm" of it.There was some excitement in untangling the motor cars and trucks. Then we started UP THE GRADE to the Stalheim
hotel-way on top of an especially high spot.
A red building sprawled all over the place.A Mrs Maxwell and her brother Mr Clothier were also <corr type="spell err" aka="stopping">st opp</corr>
same hotel So we saw<corr type="miss text"/>them later and discussed "DOONERS"
The funny feather lined puffs that are used on ALL beds everywhere around here. These are just laid on the beds and not tucked in.
Rugs all around walls in dining room
a great ski place.maps of the runs all <corr type="spell err" aka="around">adound</corr> the rooms. <pen type="doodle">The bottom of the page features a doodle of a person laying in bed with a blanket over them. The caption reads "The 'dooner' Pull it up &amp; feet stick out!" </pen></letter></root>

