<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Letters.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <letter n="1">
        <pen type="handwrit">Left Loen for Balestrand Aug 22</pen> Departed from
        Loen about 9. With a picnic. Went <corr type="miss text">Ea_t</corr>for a few miles - Toward the glacier where we
        were yesterday. Then north and east around the end of the Nord Fjord passing little clusters
        ofhouses. Edges of bright orange seaweed along the edges of the water. The water is a bit
        (line cuts off) salt and sea gulls skim about. Even tho it is many miles from the Sea.
        Beautiful vista- across the water. <pen type="doodle">(image on side of
            page)</pen> Road winding <corr type="spell err">allng</corr> the
            <corr type="spell err">wates</corr> edge. Thro Utvik Went high up thro pine
        forrest and then had to turn back- event<corr type="miss text">(cuts off)</corr> further
        back then where we photograped<corr type="spell err">(photographed)</corr> the cream colored
        pony- to the place at the turn where we photo. the view. and THERE were my glasses exactly
        where I had dropped the from my lap as I got out ofthe car to take a <corr type="miss text">pictu_e ofth</corr> 
        lovely view. VERY ,lucky!! Beautiful ground cover
        under thepines- heather in big clumps.)(Steamersdo not come in to Loen since several
        diasters- great chunks of the mountainzides<corr type="spell err">(mountainsides)</corr>
        sliding down into the fjord and killing manypeople- there is a tablet on the way to the
        glacierto <corr type="spell err">commerate</corr> onesuch happening. <corr
            type="miss text">S__ow</corr> <corr type="spell err">cappee</corr> mountains.
        Stopped at a little village by a rushing frothy river, and bought some soft drinks from a
        pretty round faced girl Again went very high over a mountain range- with grand views Carpets
        of fern. Photographed a very WIDE waterfall At the summit we got out and waited <corr type="spell err">zwhile</corr> until
        the spark plugs were cleaned. It was a sort of rest place People having coffeein the sun.
        Some of the old farms were of intereest- 16 more or less- buildings in a group Clear
        reflections in the river. Like glass and yet it is always moving. Often great rocks in the
        river bed where teh river rushes <corr type="spell err">noisiluy</corr> thdough. Brilliant green iin the bumpy meadows-
        like fairy moss. Several cream colored ponies stopped us in the road- we got out and fed
        them biscuts '<corr type="spell err">Luch</corr> by the roadside from the Hotel Alexandra's nice picnic. A_ter an hourwe
        continued Magnificent views. Before us the Sojne <corr type="spell err">fjoyd</corr> surrounded by snow capped mountains.
    </letter>
</root>
