<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <letter n="3" part="1">
        <pen type="handwrit"><date when="1955-08-25">AUGUST 25th</date> LEAVING <place name="stalheim">STALHEIM FOR ULVICK</place></pen>
        <corr type="miss text">Deci ed</corr> that, if we could get rooms at <place name="Ulvick">Ulvick</place> we <corr type="spell err">woud</corr>
        <corr>le ve</corr> <place name="Stalheim">Stalheim</place> and go on. As nothing much to do here
        except look at the views <corr type="spell err">nd</corr> CLIMB about. Had the usual
        heary laden <corr type="spell err">Smorgesbrod</corr>-but this time with <corr type="spell type">nohest</corr> to
        goodness electric toaster- so we had TOAST. We strolled
        around and went into the 'pill box" the Germans had
        built in a spot overlooking everything. Peeked into the
        so called museum- three little wooden houses grass roofs.
        filled with old wooden farm shovels, , buckets etc.It <corr type="spell err">wou ld</corr>
        <corr type="spell err">notbe</corr> open until 11 and anyway we have, by now, seen a
        number of these museums and <corr type="spell err">somemvery</corr> fine ones.
        Sat on the terrace and talked with <person name="Mrs. Maxwell">Mrs. Maxwell</person>- <person name="Mr. Clothier">Mr
        Clothier</person> was out for a walk with three sturdy English girl
        girls.These girls walked 7 miles yesterday
        So we departed with a lunch, about noon. Southward.
        Huge blue busses were continuely wheeling up to the
        hotel before we left. Some having met the steamers
        and others coming over the roads from quite some distance.
        Along by the edge of the <corr name="spell err">fjoyd</corr> we stopped to fish and
        to have out lunch. The lunch was HORRIBLE bad meat. I hope
        we don't catch anything from the one bite.Also no, fish.
        But a lovely place near some low water falls.
        But the little Sunkist oranges were all right
        I my pocket I had some crackers snitched_from the
        <corr type="spell err">breaffast</corr> table'A, 2 o'clock
        stopped to photograph the beautiful Twindefoss Falls.
        <corr type="spell err">T thi nk</corr> Twin Falls'!!F om here 45 kilometres to Ulvick.The distances <corr type="spell err">ar</corr> not great but           the roads are
        narrow and winding- so one drives slowly therefore to go a few miles takes awhile
        People in the fields raking up the hay.
        They do it three in a row and rake in unison. Smart , Voss, where we turned
        South.
        Quite a town
        Many neat new cement
        buildings and some industries.
        Snow ploughs
        along the road sides all neatly painted- ready for the winter. <corr type="spell err">Smallchildren</corr>
        on skis	2 to 3 years start to pratice First hey just stand on them then take a few slides etc
        <corr type="miss text">S uth</corr> from Voss passing a sort of minig project. WE stopped to ask about it. Slate for the roofs.
    </letter>
</root>
