<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Letters.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root><letter n="5"><pen type="handwrit"><place name="Bal">BALESTRAND</place><corr type="cross out"> TO <place name="Stal">STALHEIM</place></corr>
<date when="1955-08-23">AUGUST 23rd</date> </pen>
At breakfast a HUGE Smorgesbrot
Everything <corr type="spell err" aka="imaginable">imagineable</corr> <corr type="miss text">onthe</corr> big
table.Even <corr type="miss text">picklescheese</corr>, <corr type="spell err" aka="jellies">jelliez</corr>, salads. cold cuts <corr type="miss text">etc e</corr> 
I painted a little on my glacier'<corr type="spell err"/> Went along the dock
and up the road to Anna Mundel's after seeing her sign 
<corr type="spell err" aka="Handwork">Handwerk</corr>. 8 mts. 8 minutes. I get a sweater and two wool 
<corr type="spell err" aka="scarves">scarbes</corr>. Then we returned- stopping at an artists pretty 
house- things for <corr type="overlap" what="a/l">sale</corr> in the studio.Cards folders etc.
A very noisy dog- white Spitz with bad manners barked at us.<pen type="doodle">Doodle depicting a figure, presumed Gail, diving into water</pen>
<person name="GailWilde">Gail</person> then went swimming. Pretty
<corr type="spell err" aka="cold">cocold</corr>. But she said it was wonderful And
went in and out several <corr type="miss text" aka="times">imes</corr>.
I painted <corr type="miss text">somemore</corr>. After lunch we <corr type="spell err" aka="got a hotel">gote hotel hotel</corr><thing what="boat">dory</thing>- placed by the little dock for use of hotel guests- and rowed about a little Pieces of rope to hold the oars and such narrow blades on the oars <pen type="doodle">Doodle depicting two figures rowing a boat</pen>
After dinner <person name="OttoBehrend">Otto</person> drove us up the pretty
narrow road beyond the hotel.Very nice houses on both sides of the <corr type="spell err" aka="road">raod</corr>. I suppose they are summer residences for people from <place name="Oslo">Oslo</place>
or other places. At least some of them looked so Had the green duffle bag in and did a tall job <corr type="miss text" aka="repacking">repackin</corr></letter>
<letter n="5.2"><pen type="underlined"><place where="Bal">BALESTRAND</place></pen> TO <pen type="underlined"><place where="Stal">STALHEIM</place></pen><pen type="handwrit">/</pen><date when="1955-08-24">AUGUST" 24th</date>.
After another <corr type="spell err" aka="sumtuous">sumtous</corr> <corr type="overlap" what="k/f">breakffast</corr> we started off on the
10.30 ferry boat.The manager <corr type="spell err" aka="and">nad</corr> his wife were on the dock and waved <corr type="miss text" aka="goodbye">goodby</corr>.
A little 2 1/2 year old boy
was helping his father push a low cart up the incline to the hotel
<pen type="doodle">Doodle depicting a cart with a figure on either end.</pen>
Noticed again the orange salt water rock sea week along the edges of the <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjo yd</corr>.
13 car <corr type="spell err" aka="including">encluding</corr> one tank
truck on the ferry.Conversed with very nice person a Mrs Maxwell and her brother Mr Clothier.She from BrynMahr.
Arrived Grinde at 11.45.Drove along until we came to a little ferry- went across the water by aid of wire ropes.
We <corr type="overlap" what="u/l">couldn 't</corr> get on But <corr type="spell err" aka="it">ti</corr> came directly ba ck for us.
It was getting late for lunch but I had my coat pockets full of crackers from <corr type="spell err"><place where="Bal">Balestra nd</place></corr> breakfast tabl<corr type="miss text"/>
On trips everyone is advised to wear a <corr type="spell err" aka="coat">caot</corr> with big pockets for this purpose.
We drove
along the edge of the largest <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr>- like a big lake lake.It is also the deepest.About further to the sea.
About 3000 feet deep. Lots of sea gulls about.
Very few cars on the road. Drivers very polite</letter></root>

