<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="Letters.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <letter n="6"><pen type="handwrit"><place name="Unk">UNKIRK</place><place name="Bra">HOTEL
                BRAKANES</place>. (BOATS FOR HOTEL GUESTS. SWIMMING. TEMP. 66</pen> At breakfast I
        collected a little assortment of cracker for the trip this P.M.(as one never can be sure
        where we eat next on these trips.)We wandered down to the <corr type="miss text">dock</corr>
        and watched a lot of women buying fish from a fish <corr type="miss text">wag</corr> Bought
        myself a pair of scissors- and a straw basket to carry my paints in. Back to the <corr
            type="spell err" aka="hotel">hotell</corr> and Gail went swimming<corr type="miss text"
            >-tempture 66 </corr>Then we suddenly decided we might as well get off on the 12.30
            <corr type="spell err" aka="ferry instead">ferryinstead</corr> of waiting <corr
            type="miss text">fo</corr> the 5 o'clock which would only bring us into <corr
            type="miss text">so lat</corr> S we hustled around- Otto had let some shirts go to the
        laundry- but <corr type="spell err" aka="he">the</corr> rushed around and finished them. The
            <corr type="spell err" aka="ferry">feryy</corr> was the "Folgefonn" Very nice <corr
            type="spell err" aka="voyage">vayage</corr> of <corr type="miss text">les</corr> than an
        hour. Not many people on board and about eight cars. We rather hated to leave Ulrik. The
        hotel Brakanes is said to be the best in Norway.It was warm and lovely- people lying <corr
            type="spell err" aka="around">about</corr> on the grass-having tea etc. The re is a
        little bath shed with compartment and curtains along the edge of the terrace.All very casual
        and quite delighttul The drive was along the edge of the Hardanager Fjoud. The largest and
        deepst of them all.Some places were very rocky- the road being blasted out of the rock.
        Beautiful waterfalls- some tunnels to pass <corr type="miss text">thro</corr> Arrived <corr
            type="spell err" aka="at the">atthe</corr> Solfonn Hotel about 4.30 Wrote <corr
            type="spell err" aka="letters">lletters</corr> and rested, Dinner o fresh salmon
    </letter>
</root>
