<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../../../Downloads/Untitled3.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<root>
    <letter n="12"> Some shingles have the shape of diamonds or scallops. <pen type="doodle">(doodle
            in top left corner of shingles)</pen> The valley <corr type="spell err" aka="became"
            >becamr</corr> narrower- and we followed along the r.r. track.Looking back were the
        higher mountains with snow on the highest places. Suddenly we came into a narrow canyon,
        with high rocky sides- the tiny <corr type="spell err" aka="clusters">clusyers</corr> of
        houses way, <corr type="spell err" aka="way">wat</corr> below.Passed a very very tall
        waterfall.And then descended to a beautiful <corr type="spell err" aka="lush">luch</corr>
        green valley -around the edge of <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr> like a
        lake.White sheep in the pine woods. Many apple <corr type="spell err" aka="orchards"
            >archards</corr> and fruit trees.and also thickly wooded. The road went winding down
        into the village of <corr type="spell err" aka="Ulvik"><place name="Ulv"
            >Ulvick</place></corr>. To the Brakanes <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">Hotell</corr>
        directly on the <corr type="spell err" aka="fjord">fjoyd</corr>. With a marvelous outlook
        About 3.30Takes about 40 minutes to go 12 miles. This is a very modern Norwegian hotel
        Tastefully furnished. <corr type="spell err" aka="We">W</corr> each had a <corr
            type="spell err" aka="little">litttlr</corr>
        <corr type="spell err" aka="room with">roomwith</corr> big double windows to the floor.A
        bed, a closet, a bed stand a dressing table and seat. a table a trunk or <corr
            type="spell err" aka="suitcase">suit case</corr> rack and a wash stand with running
        water and double doors to the hallway.Also a scrap basket. The second floor lounge is a
        beautiful room. The large windows to the floor away across the room.and the Heavenly view
        beyond- the water and the "layers" of <corr type="spell err" aka="mountains in"
            >mountainsin</corr> the <corr type="spell err" aka="distance">distan ce</corr>. <pen
            type="handwrit">Dining room holey wood floor in a sort of herring bone pattern. Walls of
            pine placed along chairst comfortable with backs &amp; seats of grey-blue (illegible)
            pattern</pen>
        <pen type="handwrit"><person name="GailWilde">Gail</person> on a skinke</pen>
        <pen type="doodle">(doodle in bottom right cornner of "View as one enters hotel")</pen>
        <pen type="handwrit">View as one enters hotel</pen>
    </letter>
</root>
