<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>[<paper written="inform">Letter</paper>from <author name="Marian Baldwin">Marian
        Bladwin</author><date> June 30, 1917]</date> On Board <ship name="La Touraine">La
        Touraine</ship>, <month>>June</month><day> 30th</day>,<year> 1917.</year>
    <para1> Even now that we are out of <visibility>sight</visibility> of land, it seems impossible
        that I am actually off to <place country="France">France</place> and, for the first time in
        my life, traveling <independent>alone.</independent> Everything has happened so quickly
        since the <workplace organization="AFFW">American Fund for French Wounded </workplace>found
        an opening for me in <city country="france">Paris</city> that I suppose I am still somewhat
        dazed and bewildered. The fact that <blind>I don't know what it will all be like</blind> and
        that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the <current year="1917"
            >present.</current> Of course I have had a bit of a taste in <city>New York</city> of
        the work that the A. F. F. W. is doing but its Headquarters in Paris will be different in
        some ways I <feeling>fancy.</feeling>
    </para1>
    <para2> I can't get over how <feel positive="gratitude">lucky</feel> I am to have this chance
        for I realize how few girls of my age are getting across, and <feel positive="appreciation"
            >I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me</feel> on my great
        adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of <recent>late.</recent>
    </para2>
    <para3>As we drifted down the river, in the <sundown desc="glow">sunset glow </sundown>with two
        absurd tugs puffing alongside, I know that <sadness feeling="tears"> many eyes were
            moist</sadness> and that the same thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's
        company <wistfulness>will see that sky-line again!</wistfulness> It was very quiet, no one
        spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and <nigthfall>one star after
            another appeared.</nigthfall> I knew that <poetic>you would be looking at those same
            stars</poetic> down in Lakewood and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that
        filled my heart at that moment. <love affection="connection">Somehow distance does not
            separate, after all.</love></para3>
    <para4>We waited near the <architecture statue="neoclassical">Statue</architecture> of
            <freedom>Liberty</freedom> until midnight—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come
        on board. This <person>individual</person> was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when
        it was given out that the <group of="people">party</group> which had clambered aboard in the
        night was none other than the <historic>Italian Mission</historic>. Our spirits rose at once
        for, what with <diplomat>Frank Sayre</diplomat> on the boat and these distinguished Italian
        gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However,
        thus far <rule by="fear">we have but two destroyers following us</rule>. They can be seen
        distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side, and seem to be the same somber
        gray which all ships are affecting in this war. A sailor informed me this morning that we
        weren't in much danger for the first four or five days but that <increase in="danger">after
            that I might see some excitement</increase>. Here's hoping!</para4>
    <para5>I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a native of
        Haiti, <chatty>voluble</chatty> and very portly—has <hogging lots="space">four large pieces
            of baggage</hogging> in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a <childrens
            reading="book"><nostalgia>Mother Hubbard</nostalgia></childrens> and smokes countless
        thin cigarettes that smell like incense! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room
        for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with
        my belongings! She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me that she
        didn't think we would fight and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to join
        her <military>son</military> who has been fighting with the French since the beginning of
        the war but will never go back to the Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. She
        is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his fingers. </para5>
    <Source>: _Canteening Overseas_: 1917-1919, published 1920.</Source>
    <author name="Baccarat">Baccarat</author>, <month>July</month>
    <day>15th</day>,<year> 1918.</year>
    <para1>I am now working in the big new <project>canteen</project> at
            <workplace>Headquarters</workplace>, and believe me, it is one busy place. I'm on duty
        only <time amount="total">eight hours</time> a day but during that time I work like
            <hectic>mad and scarcely</hectic> have time to breathe. There is a line that files in
        and past our counter and then out through a farther door. That <endless repetitive="daily"
            >line never stops</endless> from the time we are open in the morning until it gets dark
        at night. <work until="exhausted">I am kept hopping like a grass-hopper</work> and bed looks
        pretty good to me at the end of the day. It's a fine life though, just work and food and
        sleep and <happy>I am thriving and growing fat on it</happy>!</para1>
    <para2>We are at present attached to the <place in="New York City">77th Division</place> which
        is, as you know, the New York drafted bunch. It is, I believe, a
            <entertaining>unique</entertaining> division and to me a most interesting one. It looks
        as though they had taken a cross section of New York City and divided it into
            <sections>Battalions, Regiments, Companies</sections> and all the different units and
        branches of the service which go to make up a division. The officers are almost entirely
        from the "four hundred" so called, and the enlisted men from the <town city="Manhattan"
            >lower East Side</town>, Italians, Polish Jews, Greeks, Serbs, in fact, representatives
        from most every country in the world. Many of them can't even speak English intelligibly and
        I have been thankful for my scraps of Italian, French and even German to make them
            <multilingual>understand me</multilingual>. They are a ferocious looking lot for the
        most part and always sure that I am trying to skin them. It's rather pathetic and <helping
            others="translating">I try to be patient</helping> and make them understand that the Y
        may have made mistakes unintentionally but that we are not in France to profiteer. It's a
        bit discouraging at the <exhausting>end of a long hot day</exhausting> to have some boy
        throw the change you have given him down on the counter and announce in a loud voice that
        the "Y girl" is trying to <increase in="price">cheat him</increase>. They haven't learned
        the <foreign>value of French money</foreign>, not having been over here long and are
        tremendously suspicious of what they call "that tin Chinese money" (the French have
        punctured their smaller coins in the center in order to save metal) and are always sure that
        you are trying to put something over on them. However, there are many who make up for the
        disagreeable ones. <attractive>Two or three Irish lads with merry blue eyes</attractive> and
        the most alluring of brogues are generally hanging over the end of the counter and are very
        much my friends. <helpful>They are always right on the spot</helpful> when there is a case
        of tobacco to be opened or heavy things to lift and have even helped me squeeze lemons! The
        work is a never ceasing joy to me on account of these bright spots and many others that turn
        up constantly to make me happier than I have ever been in my life. No one who hasn't tried
        it, knows what a satisfaction a long day's work can bring. <grateful>Thank God for the
            opportunity.</grateful></para2>
</root>
