<xml> [<letter number="1">Letter from Marian Baldwin</letter>, <date>June 30, 1917</date>] On Board
    La Touraine, <date> June 30th, 1917. </date> Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems
    impossible that I am actually off to <location>France</location> and, for the first time in my
    life, <action>traveling</action> alone. Everything has happened so quickly since the American
    Fund for French Wounded found an opening for me in <location>Paris</location> that I suppose I
    am still somewhat dazed and bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and
    that I can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have
    had a bit of a taste in New York of the work that the<abbrevi> A. F. F. W.</abbrevi> is doing
    but its Headquarters in <location>Paris</location> will be different in some ways I fancy. I
    can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how <people>few girls</people>
    of my age are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you encourage me on
    my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of late. As we <action
        destination="1">drifted</action> down the <location>river</location>, in the
        <time>sunset</time> glow with <boat>two absurd tugs</boat>
    <action>puffing</action> alongside, I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought
    was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! It was very
    quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after
    another appeared. I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in Lakewood and that
    your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that moment. Somehow distance
    does not separate, after all. We waited near <location>the Statue of Liberty </location>until
        <time>midnight</time>—a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on board. This
    individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the party
    which had <action>clambered</action> aboard in the <time>night</time> was none other than the
    Italian Mission. Our spirits rose at once for, what with <person>Frank Sayre</person> on the
        <ship num="1">boat</ship> and these distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be
    honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but<ship number="2">
        two destroyers</ship> following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the
        <side>horizon</side>, one on each side, and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships
    are affecting in this war. A <person>sailor</person> informed me this morning that we weren't in
    much danger for the first<time> four or five days</time> but that after that I might see some
        <action>excitement</action>. Here's hoping! I have a small inside cabin and my<person>
        room-mate</person> is <descrip>quite</descrip> a character. She is a native of Haiti,
    voluble and very portly—has four <luggage num="4">large pieces of baggage</luggage> in our
        <location number="2">tiny stateroom,</location> wears a costume which resembles a
        <person>Mother Hubbard </person>and <action>smokes</action> countless thin cigarettes that
    smell like <smell>incense</smell>! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for me
    but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was soon tucked into the <location>upper berth
    </location>with my belongings! She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me
    that she didn't think we would fight and from that time has beamed upon me! She is going over to
    join her son who has been fighting with the <people>French </people>since the beginning of the
    war but will never go back to the <where>Front</where> now, having lost some <bodypart>fingers
    </bodypart>off each <bodypart>hand</bodypart>. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost
    more than his<bodypart> fingers. </bodypart> [Source: _Canteening
    <location>Overseas</location>_: <time>1917-1919</time>, <date>published 1920.</date>] </xml>
