<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <infoHeader>
        <title>Collection of Letters from Marian Baldwin</title>
        <codedBy>Kayla Hopple</codedBy>
        <listLocations>
            <place xml:id="LT">
                <name>La Touraine</name>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Bord">
                <name>Bordeaux</name>
            </place>
            <place xml:id="Aix">
                <name>Aix</name>
            </place>
        </listLocations>
    </infoHeader>
    <LaTouraineLetter>[<metadata>Letter from Marian Baldwin, <date>June 30, 1917</date></metadata>]
            <setting>On Board La Touraine, <date>June 30th, 1917</date>.</setting>
        <section n="1">Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that
                <milestone destination="France">I am actually off to France and, for the first time
                in my life, traveling alone</milestone>. Everything has happened so quickly since
            the <event>American Fund for French Wounded found an opening for me in
                    <city>Paris</city></event> that I suppose I am still somewhat dazed and
            bewildered. The fact that <feeling>I don't know what it will all be like and that I
                can't look ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the
                <time>present</time></feeling>. <comparison>Of course I have had a bit of a taste in
                    <city>New York</city> of the work that the <organization>A. F. F.
                    W.</organization> is doing but its <location>Headquarters in
                    <city>Paris</city></location> will be different in some ways I
                fancy.</comparison>
            <feeling>I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how
                    <event>few girls of my age are getting across</event>, and I understood the grit
                and pluck which made you encourage me on my <endeavor destination="France">great
                    adventure</endeavor> and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of
                late.</feeling></section>
        <!-- 08-22-2023 kh: I find it fascinating that very few women of Marian's age traveled to another country to aid in war! -->
        <note by="kh">Beautiful descriptors!</note>
        <section n="2">As we drifted down the <location>river</location>, in the
                <timeDay>sunset</timeDay> glow with two absurd tugs puffing alongside, I know that
                <sensation>many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all our
                minds</sensation>. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! It
            was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky
            and one star after another appeared. <similarities>I knew that you would be looking at
                those same stars down in <location>Lakewood</location> and that your
                    <feeling>thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that
                    moment</feeling>.</similarities>
            <belief>Somehow distance does not separate, after all</belief>. We waited near the
                <location>Statue of Liberty</location> until <time>midnight</time>—a rumor had it
            that a "<person>personage</person>" was to come on board. This individual was shrouded
            in mystery until we put to sea when it was given out that the party which had clambered
            aboard in the night was none other than the <organization destination="boat">Italian
                Mission</organization>. Our spirits rose at once for, what with <person>Frank
                Sayre</person> on the <vehicle>boat</vehicle> and these distinguished Italian
            gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger <vehicle>convoy</vehicle> and so
            doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two <vehicle destination="horizon"
                >destroyers</vehicle> following us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the
            horizon, one on each side, and seem to be the same somber gray which all ships are
            affecting in this war. A sailor informed me this morning that <status>we weren't in much
                danger for the first four or five days</status> but that after that I might see some
            excitement. Here's hoping!</section>
        <section n="3">I have a <location>small inside cabin</location> and my
                <person>room-mate</person> is quite a character. <roommateCharacteristics>She is a
                native of <origin>Haiti</origin>, voluble and very
            portly</roommateCharacteristics>—has four large pieces of baggage in our tiny
            stateroom,wears a costume which resembles a Mother Hubbard and smokes countless thin
            cigarettes that smell like incense! When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room
            for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth
            with my belongings! She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me
            that <thought>she didn't think we would fight</thought> and from that time has beamed
            upon me! She is going over to <action destination="son">join her
                    <relative>son</relative></action> who has been fighting with the French since
            the beginning of the war but will never go back to the Front now, having <event>lost
                some fingers off each hand</event>. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't
            lost more than his fingers.</section>
        <!-- 08-22-2023 kh: I like how this account documents the events Marian discovered on her journey to France, and I like how she described what happened in each event like where she was and what she witnessed. -->
        <metadata>[Source:_<title>Canteening Overseas</title>_: <date>1917-1919, published
                1920</date>.</metadata>]</LaTouraineLetter>
    <BordeauxLetter><metadata><location>Bordeaux</location>, <date>December 27th,
            1917</date>.</metadata>
        <status>Such crowded busy hours as we have put in during the last few days. However, there
            will be a bit of a breathing spell now, as there are to be fewer <group
                status="on leave" return="New Year's">men</group> in on leave until <returnDate>New
                Year's</returnDate>.</status>
        <AuntT>This afternoon Aunt T. is <action destination="hideous little room">coming</action>
            to see my hideous little <location>room</location>. I have <action
                destination="fireplace">built</action> a fire that is much too large for my
            diminutive fire-place, and we are to have tea and cake! So you see it is to be a regular
            house warming.</AuntT>
        <apartment>I don't know whether I have written you about my sleeping apartment before. At
            any rate, <apartmentLocation>it is on the top floor of a tall thin
                house</apartmentLocation>. It was the only place I could get and so I have thought
            it wiser to <action destination="disadvantages">laugh</action> at its disadvantages.
                <disadvantages>There is no coal, and <object price="6 francs/8 pieces">wood costs
                        <price>six francs for eight pieces</price> so one just goes without except
                    on special occasions like to-day </object>. I generally <action from="canteen"
                    time="11:30 PM">get in from the canteen</action> about <time>11:30 P. M</time>.
                and then <stairs flights="4">my four flights seem a bit of a climb, but it is nice
                    to have a little spot of your own and I'm always so glad to get to the top of
                    the stairs</stairs>. <hotWaterBag>I still have struggles with my hot water bag,
                    for I can always see my <noun destination="room">breath</noun> in the room and I
                    think <comparison>"<landmark>old faithful</landmark>" has gotten a bit
                            <feeling>discouraged</feeling> and <thought>doesn't think it worth while
                            to keep warm in this damp penetrating
                    clime.</thought></comparison></hotWaterBag></disadvantages></apartment>
        <!-- 08-27-2023 kh: I find it a little unfortunate for her apartment to have all these problems. -->
        <roomCharacteristics><walls color="gold">The room is papered in a mud-colored tone of
                gold</walls>, <figures shape="beetle" distanceApart="2 inches">beetle-shaped figures
                scattered over it at intervals of two inches!</figures>
            <amenities>I have a black iron <object color="black" material="iron">bedstead</object>
                and a <object material="marble">fire-place and mantelpiece made of the black and
                    white mottled marble that is <literaryDevice type="hyperbole">used for
                        tombstones</literaryDevice></object></amenities>! <windows n="2">There are
                two windows, but unfortunately <windowCharacteristics colors="red and navy blue">one
                    can't look out as they are made of red and navy blue stained
                    glass</windowCharacteristics></windows>. <thought>However, I am very fond of my
                little room and to-day it wears a gay and festive look in anticipation of my
                party.</thought></roomCharacteristics> I have put all my photographs out and we are
        going to have a fine cozy time I know.</BordeauxLetter>
    <!-- 08-27-2023 kh: I like how she is getting used to her apartment despite the issues. -->
    <AixLetter><metadata><location>Aix</location>, <date>May 10th, 1918</date></metadata>. I've been
        very busy to-day <action>learning a new dance</action>. The <group origin="Paris">weekly
            vaudeville troop</group> arrived from Paris minus one number and as <person>Mr.
            Carrell</person> and I have danced on several <event>Stunt Night programs</event>, they
            <action>asked us to <task>fill in for the missing number</task></action>. So we are
            <status duration="1 week">on</status> for a week and <feeling>we were so thankful that
                <feelingReason>we had something that could be put right on to fill
                in</feelingReason></feeling>. <thought>This little taste of stage life under such
            delightful auspices, is great fun</thought>. I have a <place roomNumber="5">dressing
            room</place> all my own, <roomNumber>No. 5</roomNumber>, and <Alice>Alice has
                <characteristic>been an angel</characteristic>, <action>acts as maid and helps me
                change my costume between our two numbers</action>.</Alice> We are billed with the
        professionals all over town, "<people>Miss Baldwin &amp; Mr. Carrell.</people>" It looked
        too absurd. <stage><MarianAct after="'trained cats'">I come on right after the <act>"trained
                    cats"</act> and</MarianAct>, while waiting in the <section>wings</section>,
                <snakeCharmer>dodge the "snake charmer's" serpents! <snakes n="2" length="12 yards"
                    >She has two about twelve yards long apiece and they wriggle and glide around
                    behind the stage and appear suddenly in the most unexpected manner! The snake
                    charmer <action location="lunch basket">keeps</action> them between times rolled
                    up neatly in a <container>lunch basket</container> with a cloth drawn tightly
                    over the top!</snakes> One of the acrobats told me she doped them
            </snakeCharmer>. Sometimes I get so interested behind the scenes that I almost forget to
            go on when my turn comes. <vaudevilleArtists>These vaudeville artists are the most
                    <characteristic>kind-hearted</characteristic> of mortals and have been so good
                to me and <action>encouraged</action> me in the nicest way the first night, telling
                me to "<saying>keep smiling and not be scared.</saying>"</vaudevilleArtists>
            <comedian>One comedian has been especially good to me. -He <action destination="face"
                    >white-washes</action> his face and wears a <costume>green nose and a suit with
                    huge black and white checks</costume>!</comedian></stage></AixLetter>
    <!-- 08-27-2023 kh: That's a lot of fun performances! I'd like to see one of these! -->
</root>
