<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <para>
        <SubPara>The <year>mid-1970s</year> were a weird time for the automotive industry. Following
            the oil embargo and the subsequent sudden death of the muscle car, America’s car and
            truck manufacturers were at a bit of a loss.</SubPara>

        <SubPara>The iconic <brand>Ford</brand><type>Bronco</type> was also undergoing significant
            changes in the <year>1970s</year>. Automotive engineers at that time no longer had
            access to the previously unfathomable power reserves, and the lavish styling that highly
            defined the era was no longer fashionable. Things were quickly changing, and car
            manufacturers like <brand>General Motors</brand> had to adapt swiftly to remain
            relevant, although they experienced hard times trying to adapt. </SubPara>

        <SubPara><brand>General Motors</brand> experienced great success with best-selling cars and
            trucks from the <year>1950s</year> to the early <year>1970s</year>. Some people love
            classic cars and like to enjoy a smooth classic ride. <dealer>LaFontaine Classic
                Cars</dealer> is a top dealer selling reliable classic vehicles, including the
                <year>1973 to 1987</year><brand>General Motors</brand><sb>Square Body
            Trucks.</sb></SubPara>
    </para>

    <para>
        <SubPara><header>CLASSIC AMERICAN STYLING – <brand>CHEVY’S</brand><sb>SQUARE BODY</sb>
                YEARS</header> Why are these trucks called “<sb>square bodies</sb>,” yet
                <brand>General Motors</brand> had internally made reference to the third generation
                <WheelType>C/K</WheelType> as the “Rounded Line?”</SubPara>

        <SubPara>In <year>1973</year>, the automotive styling direction that <brand>GM</brand> had
            been accustomed to before the <year>1970s</year> could no longer apply. Members of the
            automotive press and truck lovers were behind the nickname “<sb>square body</sb>.” From
            casual observation, headlights, nothing was round about the “rounded line” other than
            the truck’s headlights. However, the <sb>square-body</sb> truck was designed as an
            aerodynamic model in a wind tunnel.</SubPara>

        <SubPara>The rounded line moniker is said to have been inspired by a windshield with round
            corners and a design focused on rounded-off corners with maximum use of airflow. The
            other <WheelType>C/K</WheelType> appearance was boxy ad straight, leading to the
                “<sb>square body</sb>” nickname.</SubPara>
    </para>

    <para>
        <SubPara><header>BUILDING A TRUE DAILY DRIVER TRUCK – <brand>CHEVY’S</brand><sb>SQUARE
                    BODY</sb> TRUCKS</header> By design, any modern pickup truck you see has four
            doors and a cab that looks more like a sedan than a utility vehicle. Americans are
            buying more pickup trucks than ever before, and the reason for this is evident. Taking
            children to school, towing off-road, and mainly truck interiors with elevated features
            are among the major reasons trucks are best-selling automobiles. However, the ultimate
            family vehicle is the modern truck that began with <brand>GM’s</brand>
            <sb>square-body</sb> car. </SubPara>

        <SubPara>The <sb>square-body</sb> truck was recognized for its iconic American styling.
            However, it was mainly known for combining the truck and the sedan in a unique way that
            no other <brand>General Motors</brand> vehicle had previously done. <brand>GM</brand>
            had begun integrating the truck and sedan worlds with the action series, but many
            changes were seen with the square-body car. </SubPara>

        <SubPara>From the previous <WheelType>C/K</WheelType> truck’s flat-faced dashboard, the
            design changed to a rounded look incorporating various materials and an advanced
            cushioned dash pad. There were also features like air conditioning, padded carpet air,
            and more on trim levels like the top-tier <type>Silverado and Cheyenne</type>.</SubPara>

        <SubPara>In <year>1978</year>, <brand>GM</brand> also included door locks and power windows
            on <type>Silverado</type> trims. By today’s standards, these features and more adapted
            in that era may be viewed as simple, but they were new inventions at that
            time.</SubPara>
    </para>

    <para>
        <SubPara><header>CUSTOMIZING EVERYTHING</header> The <sb>square-body</sb> truck is among the
            most captivating classic restoration options for buyers who wish to have a classic look
            and modern features. This truck body preference is because the number of available
            configurations for the square-body truck is mind-boggling. Some of the options available
            are: </SubPara>

        <SubPara>
            <step>Standard cab</step>
            <step>The four-door design</step>
            <step>Three wheelbase lengths</step>
            <step>Three distinct bed configurations</step>
        </SubPara>
        <SubPara>
            <WheelType>The <sb>square body</sb> trucks were marketed as <weight>1 ton</weight>,
                    <weight conver="0.5">1/2 ton</weight>, and <weight conver=".75">3/4 ton</weight>
                with the 2-wheel drive or the 4-wheel drive. C models are two-wheel drive, whereas K
                models are four-wheel drive. Every 2-wheel drive <sb>square body</sb> truck had a
                leaf spring rear suspension, an elevated steel frame, and a separate setup up front.
                The 4-wheel drive, on the other hand, had a different design.</WheelType>
        </SubPara>

        <SubPara>Some trim levels were the <type>Cheyenne, Cheyenne Super, and Custom</type>. The
                <type>Silverado</type> was introduced as the <WheelType>C/K’s</WheelType> top trim
            in <year>1975</year>, although it all began with the <sb>square body</sb>.</SubPara>
    </para>

    <para><header>LOSING ITS EDGE</header>
        <brand>Chevrolet and GMC</brand> made many minor changes to the <WheelType>C/K</WheelType>
        <sb>square body</sb> trucks throughout their time. These changes included sloping the hood,
        moving wiper locations, introducing side markers, and changing from egg-crate to split and
        two-level grilles. Most of these parts are interchangeable between years, with most of the
        changes occurring between <year>1981 and 1987</year>. </para>

    <para>
        <SubPara><header><year>1973-’87</year>
                <brand>CHEVROLET</brand> PICKUP BUYER’S GUIDE</header> Adding some finishing touches
            to the popular “<sb>square body</sb>” trucks. Recently, there has been a lot of interest
            in <year>1973-1987</year>
            <brand>Chevrolet</brand> light trucks, also known as “<sb>square bodies</sb>.” These
            trucks are readily available at low prices, making them popular. Acquiring
                <sb>square-body</sb> spare parts is also convenient, and the trucks are also easy to
            work on and are open for modifications. </SubPara>

        <SubPara><brand>Chevrolet’s</brand>
            <WheelType>C/K</WheelType> light trucks debuted for the <year>1973</year> model year
            with a new and more advanced profile, including a hood flush with the fenders’ tops and
            doors placed into the vehicle’s roofline. </SubPara>

        <SubPara>There were also changes from the <year>1967-72</year> series, which included a
            switch from the standard rear coil springs to leaf springs on the
                <WheelType>two-wheel-drive <weight conver="0.5">1/2 ton</weight> and <weight
                    conver=".75">3/4 ton</weight> trucks</WheelType>. In addition, changes included
            extended front leaf springs and a classic front stabilizer bar for the
                <WheelType>four-wheel drives</WheelType>. At the time, the <engine>v-8
                engine</engine> was first made available. The fuel tank was relocated from inside
            the cab to the outer part of the frame rails. Other modifications include:</SubPara>

        <SubPara><SubHeader> Body and Interior</SubHeader> The <year>new-for-73</year> trucks had a
            boxier look than the past ones, although they were sleeker. The cabs from <year>1973 to
                1981</year> were also bigger than their forebears, with 2.5 inches more passenger
            and driver hip room. Although there were some minor changes before, the first and only
            significant redesign of the trucks in their 14-year run occurred in <year>1981</year>,
            making room for front fenders, a sloped hood, and a front air dam. </SubPara>

        <SubPara><SubHeader>Chassis and Brakes</SubHeader> The chassis was redesigned to make these
            trucks more robust and stable than those before. Wheelbases were extended as axles and
            suspension bits were moved further outward while frames and tow hooks were advanced to
            accommodate the longer wheelbases. In addition, the outboard fuel tank’s weight and leaf
            spring configuration were redesigned. Other changes included staggered rear shocks and
            standardization of front disc brakes. </SubPara>
        <SubPara>
            <SubHeader>Engine and Transmission </SubHeader> From <year>1973 to 1987</year>, these
            trucks were available with <engines>various engines, including s Small-block, V-6,
                big-block, and diesel engines. You can still get the 350 and an updated
                454</engines> at <dealer>LaFontaine Classic Cars</dealer>. Transmission options are
                <trany>limited to three- and four-speed manuals and three- and four-speed
                automatics</trany>. The <trany>bulletproof SM465 four-speed manual
                transmission</trany> was frequently used in these <sb>square-body</sb> trucks. </SubPara>

        <SubPara><SubHeader>Differential and Transfer Case</SubHeader> A <brand>GM</brand>
            <axle>10- or 12-bolt axle</axle> is found at the rear of <brand>Chevrolet</brand>
            half-ton trucks from <year>1973 to 1987</year>. For the classic ride, get the
                <axle>10-bolt</axle> under trucks <year>1982</year> or a more recent one, and
                <axle>12-bolt</axle> under trucks <year>1981</year> or older. They are both good
            axles that are simple to rebuild and have many parts. Dana’s <year>70s</year> were used
            in dual-wheel trucks. Both <brand>GM</brand>
            <axle>14-bolt</axle> axles are built to last hundreds of thousands of miles of hauling
            and towing.</SubPara>
    </para>

    <para><header>IS <brand>CHEVY</brand> BRINGING BACK SQUARE-BODY IN <year>2024</year>?</header>
        The short answer is yes. Looking ahead, <brand>Chevrolet’s</brand> future includes an
        expansion of their truck lineup to include fully electric models. For a glimpse into what a
        future <brand>Chevy</brand> truck might entail, we have digital drawings created by Ben
        Wilkins, a creative designer at <brand>General Motors</brand>. These images showcase a fresh
        reinterpretation of <brand>Chevy’s</brand> truck design. The front fascia retains
        similarities to the current <type>Silverado</type>, but with notable distinctions such as a
        slightly larger grille, slimmer headlights, and extended LED daytime running lights. The
        sculpted bumper incorporates a silver protection element, hinting at a more
        off-road-inspired iteration of the <type>Silverado</type>.</para>

    <source>https://www.lafontaineclassiccars.com/blog/chevy-square-body-years-<year>1973-1987</year>/</source>

</root>
