<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root>
    <title>Leaves</title>
    <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>
    <birthDate >1941</birthDate>
    <stanza number="1"> 
        Every October it becomes important, no, necessary to see the leaves turning,
        to be surrounded by leaves turning; it's not just the symbolism, to confront in the
        <personification action="death">death of the year </personification>your death, one
        blazing farewell appearance, though the irony isn't lost on you that <personification
        action="seductive">nature is most seductive when it's about to die, flaunting the dazzle
        of its incipient exit,</personification> an ending that at least so far the effects of
        human progress (pollution, acid rain) have not yet frightened you enough to make you believe
        is real; that is, you know this ending is a deception because of course nature is always
        renewing itself— <personification action="pretend">the trees don't die, they just
        pretend</personification>, <repetition type="epimone">go out in style, and return in
        style: a new style.</repetition>
    </stanza>
    <stanza number="2"> 
        Is it deliberate how far they make you go especially if you live in the city
        to get far enough away from home to see <repetition type="antithesis">not just trees but
        only trees? </repetition>
        <!--Antithesis is setting off two ideas in a balanced (parallel) opposition, this creates more emphasis-->
        The boring highways, roadsigns, high speeds, 10-axle trucks passing you <simile
        type="comparison">as if they were </simile> in an even greater hurry than you to look at
        leaves: so you <hyperbole exaggeration="literal hours">drive in terror for literal
        hours</hyperbole> and it looks like rain, or snow, but it's probably just clouds (too
        cloudy to see any color?)and you wonder, given the poverty of your memory, which road had
        the most color last year, but it doesn't matter since you're probably too late anyway, or
        too early— whichever road you take will be the wrong one and <hyperbole
        exaggeration="nothing">you've probably come all this way for nothing.</hyperbole>
    </stanza>
    <stanza number="3"> 
        You'll be driving along depressed when suddenly a cloud will move and the
        <personification action="muscle">sun will muscle through</personification> and ignite
        the hills. <repetition type="anaphora">It may not last. Probably won't last.</repetition>
        <!--Anaphora is when the first word or a set of words are repeated in one sentence, clause or phrase-->
        <personification action="wakes">But for a moment the whole world comes to. Wakes
        up.</personification> Proves it lives. It lives— red, yellow, orange, brown, russet,
        ocher, vermilion, gold. <repetition type="epizeuxis">Flame and rust. Flame and
        rust,</repetition> the permutations of burning. <repetition type="anaphora">You're on
        fire. Your eyes are on fire.</repetition>
        <repetition type="antimetabole">It won't last, you don't want it to last.</repetition>
        <paradox type="contradiction">You can't stand any more. But you don't want it to stop. </paradox>
        <repetition type="epimone">It's what you've come for. It's what you'll come back
        for.</repetition> It won't stay with you, but you'll remember that <simile
        type="comparison">it felt like nothing else you've felt</simile> or something you've
        felt that also didn't last. 
    </stanza>
    <copyright> Copyright © <year>1992</year> by <author>Lloyd Schwartz.</author> From
            <title>Goodnight, Gracie</title> (<publisher>The University of Chicago
        Press</publisher>, <publisherYear>1992</publisherYear>). Appears courtesy of the author.
    </copyright>
</root>
