<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--exp means expression as in words that seem intense and poetic
human means words related closer to humans
nature means closer to natural elements-->

<!--I think capitalizing the exp element makes it pop out in a way that makes it seem more important or more valuable to be highlighted than the other elements, which I find a little jarring. I went and lowercased all instances of the exp element.-->
<root>

  <metadata>
    <title>Leaves</title>

    <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>
    <date>
      <year>1941 –</year>
    </date>
  </metadata>


  <poem>
    <stanza n="1">
      <stanzanum>1 </stanzanum>

      <line>Every October it becomes important, no, necessary</line>
      <line>to see the <title>leaves</title> turning, to be surrounded</line>
      <line>by <title><nature>leaves</nature></title> turning; it's not just the symbolism,</line>
      <line>to confront in the death of the year your death,</line>
      <line>one blazing farewell appearance, though the irony</line>
      <line>isn't lost on you that <nature>nature</nature> is most <exp>seductive</exp></line>
      <line>when it's about to <exp>die</exp>, <exp>flaunting</exp> the <exp>dazzle</exp> of
        its</line>
      <line>incipient exit, an ending that at least so far</line>
      <line>the effects of human progress (<human>pollution</human>, <human>acid
        rain</human>)</line>
      <line>have not yet frightened you enough to make you believe</line>
      <line>is real; that is, you know this ending is a <exp>deception</exp></line>
      <line>because of course <nature>nature</nature> is always renewing itself—</line>
      <line>the <nature>trees</nature> don't <exp>die</exp>, they just pretend,</line>
      <line>go out in style, and return in style: a new style.</line>
    </stanza>

    <!-- ChelseaQ. - Fall s my favorite season -->
    <!-- Mistie M. 09.16.23 - Fall is coming up soon! Just one more week :) -->


    <stanza n="2">
      <stanzanum>2</stanzanum>

      <line>Is it deliberate how far they make you go</line>
      <line> especially if you live in the <human>city</human> to get far </line>
      <line>enough away from home to see not just <nature>trees</nature>
      </line>
      <line>but only <nature>trees</nature>? The <exp>boring</exp>
        <human>highways</human>, <human>roadsigns</human>, high</line>
      <line><human>speeds</human>, <exp><human>10-axle trucks</human></exp> passing you as if they
        were </line>
      <line>in an even greater hurry than you to look at
        <title><nature>leaves</nature></title>:</line>
      <line>so you <human>drive</human> in <exp>terror</exp> for literal hours and it looks </line>
      <line>like <nature>rain</nature>, or <nature>snow</nature>, but it's probably just
          <nature>clouds</nature></line>
      <line>(too <nature>cloudy</nature> to see any color?) and you wonder, </line>
      <line>given the <exp>poverty</exp> of your memory, which <human>road</human> had the </line>
      <line>most color last year, but it doesn't matter since</line>
      <line>you're probably too late anyway, or too early—</line>
      <line>whichever <human>road</human> you take will be the wrong one</line>
      <line>and you've probably come all this way for nothing.</line>
    </stanza>




    <stanza n="3">
      <stanzanum>3</stanzanum>

      <line>You'll be <human>driving</human> along <exp>depressed</exp> when suddenly</line>
      <line>a <nature>cloud</nature> will move and the <nature>sun</nature> will <exp>muscle</exp>
        through</line>
      <line>and <exp>ignite</exp> the <nature>hills</nature>. It may not last. Probably</line>
      <line>won't last. But for a moment the whole <nature>world</nature></line>
      <line>comes to. Wakes up. Proves it lives. It lives—</line>
      <line> red, yellow, orange, brown, russet, ocher, vermilion,</line>
      <line>gold. <exp>Flame and rust</exp>. <exp>Flame and rust</exp>, the permutations</line>
      <line>of <exp>burning</exp>. You're on fire. <exp>Your eyes are on fire.</exp></line>
      <line>It won't last, you don't want it to last. You</line>
      <line>can't stand any more. But you don't want it to stop.</line>
      <line>It's what you've come for. It's what you'll</line>
      <line> come back for. It won't stay with you, but you'll </line>
      <line>remember that it felt like nothing else you've felt</line>
      <line>or something you've felt that also didn't last.</line>
    </stanza>
  </poem>

  <source>Copyright © <year>1992</year> by <author>Lloyd Schwartz</author>. From Goodnight, Gracie
    (The University of Chicago Press, <year>1992</year>). Appears courtesy of the author.</source>
</root>
