<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Key: PoI - Place of Interest. CoI - Character of Interest.-->
<root>
    <!-- herschell - I took a look over the file. Good job! -->
    <Letter L="1">[Letter from <CoI>Marian Baldwin</CoI>, June 30, 1917] On Board La Touraine,
            <date>June 30th, 1917.</date><!-- Royal Navy destroyer HMS Cheerful struck a mine and sank in the Atlantic Ocean with the loss of 40 of her 62 crew on this day in 1917 -->
        <Para p="1">Even now that we are out of sight of land, it seems impossible that I am
            actually off to <PoI>France</PoI> and, for the first time in my life, traveling alone.
            Everything has happened so quickly since the American Fund for French Wounded found an
            opening for me in <PoI>Paris</PoI> that I suppose I am still somewhat dazed and
            bewildered. The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and that I can't look
            ahead makes it easier to be happy and live in the present. Of course I have had a bit of
            a taste in <PoI>New York</PoI> of the work that the A. F. F. W. is doing but its
            Headquarters in Paris will be different in some ways I fancy.</Para>
        <Para p="2">I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance for I realize how few girls
            of my age are getting across, and I understood the grit and pluck which made you
            encourage me on my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so
            dangerous of late.</Para>
        <Para p="3">As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs puffing
            alongside, I know that many eyes were moist and that the same thought was in all our
            minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line again! It was very quiet,
            no one spoke much, and, little by little, the glow faded from the sky and one star after
            another appeared. I knew that you would be looking at those same stars down in Lakewood
            and that your thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that moment.
            Somehow distance does not separate, after all.</Para>
        <Para p="4">We waited near the Statue of Liberty until midnight—a rumor had it that a
            "personage" was to come on board. This individual was shrouded in mystery until we put
            to sea when it was given out that the party which had clambered aboard in the night was
            none other than the Italian Mission. Our spirits rose at once for, what with <CoI>Frank
                Sayre
                <!-- Frank Sayre was the assitant district attorny for New York County --></CoI> on
            the boat and these distinguished Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a
            bigger convoy and so doubly safe. However, thus far we have but two destroyers following
            us. They can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side, and seem
            to be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this war. A sailor informed
            me this morning that we weren't in much danger for the first four or five days but that
            after that I might see some excitement. Here's hoping!</Para>
        <Para p="5">I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character. She is a
            native of Haiti, voluble and very portly—has four large pieces of baggage in our tiny
            stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a <CoI>Mother
                Hubbard<!-- Mother Hubbard is an english nursary rhyme which origin is still disputed --></CoI>
            and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense! When I appeared, there
            didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I am small, and I was soon
            tucked into the upper berth with my belongings! She really isn't bad and after looking
            me over carefully told me that she didn't think we would fight and from that time has
            beamed upon me! She is going over to join her son who has been fighting with the French
            since the beginning of the war but will never go back to the Front now, having lost some
            fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says, that he hasn't lost more than his
            fingers. </Para> [Source:_Canteening Overseas_: 1917-1919, published 1920.] </Letter>

    <Letter L="2"> Aix, <date>May 10th, 1918.</date><!-- Battle of Kaniów – Around 8,000 troops with the Polish II Corps in Russia
        under command of Józef Haller were surprised and encircled by a larger Imperial German Army of 12,000 soldiers near Kaniów, Ukraine.[46]-->
        <Para p="6">I've been very busy to-day learning a new dance. The weekly vaudeville troop arrived
            from Paris minus one number and as <CoI>Mr. Carrell</CoI> and I have danced on several
            Stunt Night programs, they asked us to fill in for the missing number. So we are on for
            a week and we were so thankful that we had something that could be put right on to fill
            in. This little taste of stage life under such delightful auspices, is great fun. I have
            a dressing room all my own, No. 5, and <CoI>Alice</CoI> has been an angel, acts as maid
            and helps me change my costume between our two numbers. We are billed with the
            professionals all over town, "<CoI>Miss Baldwin</CoI> &amp; Mr. Carrell." It looked too
            absurd. I come on right after the "trained cats" and, while waiting in the wings, dodge
            the "snake charmer's" serpents! She has two about twelve yards long apiece and they
            wriggle and glide around behind the stage and appear suddenly in the most unexpected
            manner! The snake charmer keeps them between times rolled up neatly in a lunch basket
            with a cloth drawn tightly over the top! <FF>
                <!-- Snake charmers usually remove the snakes fangs aswell which naturally stops it
                    from biting but also makes it harder to eat.--></FF> Sometimes I
            get so interested behind the scenes that I almost forget to go on when my turn comes.
            These vaudeville artists are the most kind-hearted of mortals and have been so good to
            me and encouraged me in the nicest way the first night, telling me to "keep smiling and
            not be scared." One comedian has been especially good to me. -He white-washes his face
            and wears a green nose and a suit with huge black and white checks!</Para></Letter>

    <Letter L="3"> Baccarat, <Date>July 15th, 1918.</Date><!-- Second Battle of the Marne – Germany launched a major offensive against the Allies on the Western Front,
        with 52 German divisions attacking 44 French divisions east and west of Reims, France. -->
        <Para p="7">I am now working in the big new canteen at Headquarters, and believe me, it is one
            busy place. I'm on duty only eight hours a day but during that time I work like mad and
            scarcely have time to breathe. There is a line that files in and past our counter and
            then out through a farther door. That line never stops from the time we are open in the
            morning until it gets dark at night. I am kept hopping like a grass-hopper and bed looks
            pretty good to me at the end of the day. It's a fine life though, just work and food and
            sleep and I am thriving and growing fat on it! We are at present attached to the <CoI>77th
            Division</CoI> which is, as you know, the New York drafted bunch. It is, I believe, a unique
            division and to me a most interesting one. It looks as though they had taken a cross
            section of New York City and divided it into Battalions, Regiments, Companies and all
            the different units and branches of the service which go to make up a division. The
            officers are almost entirely from the <CoI>"four hundred"</CoI> so called, and the enlisted men
            from the lower East Side, Italians, Polish Jews, Greeks, Serbs, in fact, representatives
            from most every country in the world. Many of them can't even speak English intelligibly
            and I have been thankful for my scraps of Italian, French and even German to make them
            understand me. They are a ferocious looking lot for the most part and always sure that I
            am trying to skin them. It's rather pathetic and I try to be patient and make them
            understand that the Y may have made mistakes unintentionally but that we are not in
            France to profiteer. It's a bit discouraging at the end of a long hot day to have some
            boy throw the change you have given him down on the counter and announce in a loud voice
            that the "Y girl" is trying to cheat him. They haven't learned the value of French
            money, not having been over here long and are tremendously suspicious of what they call
            "that tin Chinese money" (the French have punctured their smaller coins in the center in
            order to save metal) and are always sure that you are trying to put something over on
            them. However, there are many who make up for the disagreeable ones. Two or three Irish
            lads with merry blue eyes and the most alluring of brogues are generally hanging over
            the end of the counter and are very much my friends. They are always right on the spot
            when there is a case of tobacco to be opened or heavy things to lift and have even
            helped me squeeze lemons! The work is a never ceasing joy to me on account of these
            bright spots and many others that turn up constantly to make me happier than I have ever
            been in my life. No one who hasn't tried it, knows what a satisfaction a long day's work
            can bring. Thank God for the opportunity. </Para>
    </Letter>
</root>
