<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--[Letter from Marian Baldwin-->
<letters>
    <L1>
        <title>On Board La Touraine</title>
        <info type="stat">1917-06-30</info>
        <p n="1">Even now that we are out of sight of land, <opinion attd="neg">it seems impossible</opinion>
            that I am actually off to <location type="country"> france </location> and, <info
                type="personal">for the first time in my life, traveling alone.</info><opinion
                attd="neg">Everything has happened so quickly</opinion>since<info type="external"
                >the <world_force>American Fund for French Wounded</world_force> found an opening
                for me in Paris</info> that <opinion attd="neg">I suppose I am still somewhat dazed
                and bewildered.</opinion> The fact that I don't know what it will all be like and
            that I can't look ahead <opinion attd="pos">makes it easier to be happy and live in the
                present</opinion>. Of course I have had a bit of a taste in New York of the work
            that the <world_force>A. F. F. W.</world_force> is doing but <opinion attd="pos">its
                Headquarters in <location type="city">Paris</location> will be different in some
                ways I fancy.</opinion></p>
            <!--Note: the AFFW is an acronym for the "American Fund for French Wounded" which was an organization that was founded by american women to help hospitals in france and work closely with the red cross as well-->
        <p n="2"><opinion attd="pos">I can't get over how lucky I am to have this chance</opinion>
            for <info type="external">I realize how few girls of my age are getting across</info>,
            and I understood the grit and pluck which <info type="personal">made you encourage me on
                my great adventure and send me along a path which has proved so dangerous of
                late.</info></p>
        <p n="3">As we drifted down the river, in the sunset glow with two absurd tugs puffing
            alongside, <opinion attd="neg">I know that many eyes were moist and that the same
                thought was in all our minds. How many of this ship's company will see that sky-line
                again!</opinion> It was very quiet, no one spoke much, and, little by little, the
            glow faded from the sky and one star after another appeared. <opinion attd="pos">I knew
                that you would be looking at those same stars down in Lakewood and that your
                thoughts and prayers were the same that filled my heart at that moment. Somehow
                distance does not separate, after all.</opinion></p>
        <p n="4">We waited near <location type="atraction">the Statue of Liberty</location> until
                midnight—<info type="external">a rumor had it that a "personage" was to come on
                board.</info> This individual was shrouded in mystery until we put to sea when it
            was given out that the party which had clambered aboard in the night was none other than
            the <world_force>Italian Mission.</world_force>
            <opinion attd="positive">Our spirits rose at once</opinion> for, what with <character
                importance="high">Frank Sayre</character> on the boat and these distinguished
            Italian gentlemen, we shall doubtless be honored by a bigger convoy and so doubly safe.
                However,<info type="external">thus far we have but two destroyers following us. They
                can be seen distinctly outlined against the horizon, one on each side, and seem to
                be the same somber gray which all ships are affecting in this war.</info><info
                type="personal">A sailor informed me this morning that we weren't in much danger for
                the first four or five days but that after that I might see some excitement.
                    <opinion attd="pos">Here's hoping!</opinion></info>
            <!--Note:the word mission does not mean a goal or objective, rather just informing the readers that this group is mormon-->
        </p>
        <paragraph number="5">I have a small inside cabin and my room-mate is quite a character.
                <info type="personal">She is a native of Haiti, voluble and very portly—has four
                large pieces of baggage in our tiny stateroom, wears a costume which resembles a
                Mother Hubbard and smokes countless thin cigarettes that smell like incense!</info>
            When I appeared, there didn't seem to be much room for me but, as she says, luckily I am
            small, and I was soon tucked into the upper berth with my belongings!<opinion
                attitude="positive">She really isn't bad and after looking me over carefully told me
                that she didn't think we would fight and from that time has beamed upon
                me!</opinion><info type="personal">She is going over to join her son who has been
                fighting with the French since the beginning of the war but will never go back to
                the Front now, having lost some fingers off each hand. She is so thankful, she says,
                that he hasn't lost more than his fingers.</info></paragraph>
        <!--Note: voluble means talkative and energetic while portly means stout or fat-->
        <citation rend="squarebracket">Source: <title type="book">Canteening Overseas:
                1917-1919</title>, published 1920</citation>
    </L1>
    <L2>
        <info type="stat">July 8th, 1917</info>
        <entry n="1"><info type="personal">Friday night we entered the war zone at seven
                o'clock</info> but you would never know it. Aside from boat-drills and sleeping on
            deck people act as usual. The officers on the boat are very particular about the drills;
            several times the alarm has sounded and we have been taught just what to do in case we
            are hit. <opinion attd="pos">It's very funny to see the people rush below for their
                valuables, strapping on their life preservers as they go</opinion> (which we always
            have near at hand wherever we are -on deck or in the saloon). In about five minutes we
            are lined up, divided into groups in front of our own particular life-boats which have
            been swung out over the sea ready to lower. Every one is checked off and each man is
            told what woman he is to save. <opinion type="pos">(Great excitement at this point as no
                one of the men wants to save the lady detailed to him, but some one in another
                boat!)</opinion> We all stand about looking too absurd and bumping into each other's
            life preservers on the crowded upper deck. Finally the signal is given which releases
            us, and we all file down again to take off the clumsy heavy jackets of safety and regale
            ourselves with various amusements on the deck.</entry>
        <!--she seems to be amused by the men picking favorites but tbh if I was in her position I would be so mad, like why are you not saving me? its your job and im dying-->
        <entry n="2"><info type="external">Rumor has it that two ships have been sunk, one in the
                course ahead of where we were yesterday and the other about an hour behind
                us.</info> No one knows how many lives were lost. <opinion type="neg">Perhaps those
                three submarines were more fact than fiction after all.</opinion></entry>
        <entry n="3">It is thought that <info type="external">we should make Bordeaux by Tuesday
                morning if all goes well and that the convoy which should have met us days ago will
                be with us to-night.</info></entry>
        <entry n="4">This being Sunday, the boys on board are very much dressed up, that is to say
            they are wearing clean shirts and have their hair brushed! <opinion type="pos">It's a
                perfect day, warm and cloudless, and I've been lying in the sun adding to my coat of
                tan.</opinion><opinion type="neg">We all feel quite sad that the voyage is so nearly
                over -it has been such loads of fun and I shall hate saying good-by to every
                one.</opinion></entry>
        <location type="boat">La Touraine</location>
    </L2>
    <L3>
        <info type="external">En route from Bordeaux to Paris</info>
        <info type="stat">July 18th, 1917</info>
        <entry n="1">On landing yesterday I went straight to the <location type="attracion">Hôtel de
                France</location> and it certainly was good to have room to turn around in: <opinion
                attd="pos">as for a bed with real springs I greeted it with enthusiasm! Towards
                evening <character importance="high">Frank</character> and I took a long walk about
                the city. <info type="personal">A port town always interests me</info> and we saw it
                all at the loveliest time of day. The harbor was full of fishing smacks and small
                craft of all kinds and exquisite tones in the sails and rigging. The last rays of
                the sun cast a rosy hue over everything, making one think at once of <location
                    type="city">Venice</location> and the days before the war. Later we wandered
                through some of the oldest parts of Bordeaux and I really felt that I was abroad
                again! The narrow winding streets and cobblestones, with here and there an ancient
                façade or doorway and everywhere, in the poorest alleys, a bit of a vine or potted
                plant in the windows. How do they manage to make it all so picturesque and
                alluring?</opinion></entry>
        <entry n="2">The women and the old men are doing everything and it is surprising to see the
            lady conductors. <info type="personal">On this train they use women entirely, even in
                the dining car.</info> The war hasn't robbed them of vivacity or their beautiful
            complexions and <opinion attd="pos">I believe they are even prettier in their simple
                black working clothes than before.</opinion></entry>
        <entry n="3"><location type="atraction">We are at present passing through the famous
                vineyards</location> and I have never seen the country look so beautiful. The crops
            seem in perfect condition, thanks to the patient labor of these wonderful women, and the
            grain waves in profusion everywhere. I have longed for you at every turn, how you would
            enjoy it all. The poppies are in their prime and, as the train whirls by, they look like
            immense splashes of red -almost like stains of blood against the gold of the
            wheat.</entry>
        <entry n="4"><opinion attd="pos">I have just come in from a very excellent meal in the
                dining car</opinion> -the food was served promptly by two French girls of the
            peasant type and with a speed that was wonderful, the car holding over thirty
            persons.</entry>
        <location type="city">Paris</location>
        <!--"of the peasant type" what did she mean by this?-->
    </L3>
</letters>
<!--the reason I like making the letter number element sandwhich the whole letter is because its a lot easier on the eyes than the default format -->
