<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<recipe>About this recipe Healthiness : (71 votes) View a modern version of this recipe <para><!--ebb: Hey Anthony! Don't you want to use <para>?  -->
        <!--Hi This is a comment -->
        <!--type your comment and I'm not done yet-->
        <!--Here's my comment again--> The Georgians loved rich, sweet food. Sugar had become much
        more easily available (mostly because of the Transatlantic Slave Trade) and was fast
        replacing honey as the main food sweetener.</para>
    <para>This version of the syllabub recipe was by <name type="person">Eliza Acton</name>, who
        lived in <timePeriod>18th century</timePeriod>. There are <altRecipe>plenty of earlier
            versions but they are more likely to curdle as they contain cider</altRecipe>. This
        version was very modern and fashionable in its day and is easy to manage: <blockQuote>Take a
            quart of cream, a pint of sack, juice of a lemon, whip it, as the froth flies take it
            off with a spoon and lay it in glasses: but first you must sweeten and stir some white
            wine into your glasses, and gently lay on your froth. Set them by and do not make them
            long before you use them.</blockQuote>
    </para>
    <para>Sugar and sherry (known as sack) were still expensive ingredients and dishes like this
        would have been eaten in the houses of the richer merchants who would be able to afford
        sugar, lemons, new salad vegetables and sack.</para>
    <para>We have added a non-alcoholic lemon syllabub for you to try too.</para>
    <para>For images of the cooking process see our Syllabub Pictures.</para>
    <para type="credits">With thanks to <name type="person">Ian Pycroft</name> of <name
            type="organization">Black Knight Historical</name> and to <name type="organization">The
            Georgian House, <name type="place">Bristol</name></name>.</para>
    <section kind="ingred">
        <heading>Ingredients</heading>
        <list><item quant="1" unit="fruit">1 <ingred>lemon</ingred></item>
            <item quant=".25" unit="pint">1/4 pint <ingred>sack</ingred> (pale or dark)</item>
            <item quantLow="2" quantHigh="3" unit="ounce">2-3 oz <ingred>caster
                sugar</ingred></item>
            <item quant=".5" unit="pint">1/2 pint <ingred>double cream</ingred></item>
            <item quantLow="4" quantHigh="6" unit="Tb">4-6 tablespoons <ingred>sweet/dessert white
                    wine</ingred>
            </item>
        </list>
    </section>
    <section kind="equip">
        <heading>Equipment</heading>
        <list>
            <item>Knife</item>
            <item>Grater</item>
            <item>Chopping board</item>
            <item>Mixing bowl</item>
            <item>Jug</item>
            <item>Tablespoon</item>
        </list>
    </section>
    <section kind="process">
        <heading>Making and cooking it</heading>
        <listStep>
            <step num="1">Always <action>wash</action> your hands before preparing food</step>
            <step num="2"><action>Grate</action> half the peel, <action>pare off</action> the rest
                in fine strips</step>
            <step num="3">Place sherry, grated peel, lemon juice and sugar in bowl and
                    <action>soak</action> for 2 hours</step>
            <step num="4"><action>Whip</action> the cream until semi-stiff</step>
            <step num="5"><action>Add</action> sherry gradually</step>
            <step num="6"><action>Spoon</action> a little wine into glass and spoon on whipped
                cream</step>
            <step num="7"><action>Decorate</action> the top with lemon peel sticks</step>
            <step num="8"><action>Serve</action> with Shrewsberry cakes</step>
        </listStep>
    </section>
</recipe>
