<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Travel Journal Excerpt</title>
            <author>John Norton</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>xml manuscript, encoded in TEI, 2025</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcription of a personal travel narrative describing a voyage to Ireland, Wales,
               and Liverpool.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text>
      <body>
       <div type="letter"> <p> I received particular joy at seeing, within the smell of the land, an Old Yorkshire man
            of foreseer who had left his son a merchant in New York, to breathe his last in his
            native land; far from the continued storms we met &amp; feeble situation he was in from
            sea sickness I had been apprehensive we should have lost him on the passage. </p>

         <p> Coasting the Southwest shore of Ireland on that 18th in the evening we made Cork, where
            we were <choice>
               <sic>where</sic>
               <corr>were</corr>
            </choice> becalmed – we met there a ship we had seen two days before at a distance, she
            was an armed vessel of Liverpool, that had been at Barbados, and was now returning, she
            had on board the Governor, and suite of a Dutch settlement in the West Indies, lately
            taken by the British troops – There is not much appearance of verdure yet on shore – or
            it might in some respect afford a beautiful prospect – but they have a disagreeable way
            of decorating their coasts with 
            <choice>
               <sic>gibbets</sic>
               <corr>jibbets</corr>
            </choice> here and there – Is it not surprising, that a people so enlightened, so humane
            and so polite should have it so arranged, that the first object striking the view of the
            strangers, who approach their shore should be an emblem of the severity of their laws
            and depravity of some of their people. </p>

         <p> Telegraphs were also to be seen on every eminence – this is a late invention to
            communicate intelligence of the approach of an enemy or to give orders to the ships of
            the Navy – they are on a line of communication within distinct view of each other –
            certain figures are put up which are repeated from one <pb n="35"/> to the other without
            being understood by any but those from whom the orders issue and the commanders of
            Posts. We there learnt, by the boats which came from the shore, that all was as yet
            tranquil, that they had only heard of the threats of Bonaparte which it was not likely,
            he would be able to put in execution. </p>

         <p> After night a fair wind springing up, we made sail, and next morning, we were abreast
            of Wicklow Mountains, the land is high and elevated, but we were at too great a distance
            to distinctly view it – On the 21st we sailed along the Welsh Coast and passed Holyhead
            – here is elevated land &amp; lofty mountains, whose tops are covered with snow, which
            although they do not prepossess you with an idea of the fertility of the country, yet
            the natural Majestic grandeur of the asylum of the descendants of ancient Britons
            strikes the mind with veneration at the magnanimity and unfortunate valor of their
            ancestors who preferred breathing the air of freedom on Rocky Mountains, to remaining in
            subjection on their native fertile plains, and calls a sigh for their hero the gallant
            Caractacus. </p>

         <p> In the evening a Pilot comes on board and next day we arrive safe in dock here, the
            pleasure we felt on the occasion can not well be imagined by any but those, who have
            made a long sea voyage. Altho’ this was Sunday and business lulled at rest, yet
            sufficient was to be seen to give a stranger some conception of the magnitude of the
            trade carried on at this place – the many store houses, the multitude of ships, the
            inland canals and docks all denote wealth &amp; exertion, these last are of two kind wet
            and dry, the latter are to receive vessels to be repaired; the former are for <pb n="36"
            /> ships to unload and load in; they are made by digging spaces to such a level as to be
            of sufficient depth for the vessels that are to enter the gates of these docks at which
            the vessels, and flow of the tide are received, are shut in the ebb tide by which means
            the water is retained that keeps the ships afloat – were it not for these constructions
            the lading and unlading would be performed with great inconvenience at this port which
            is not naturally well calculated, the River being amazing shallow at low water, and its
            entry rendered difficult from a number of sand banks. </p>

         <p> But the approximate situation of this place to several manufacturing towns renders it
            the great emporium of commerce to the West – It is here that are deposited the stuffs of
            Manchester, the cutlery of Birmingham and the woolen cloths of Yorkshire, as are also
            the produce of the west for which they are bartered – it is considered next to London
            for importance in trade: that of Africa however is a branch that is carried on here to
            some extent and is not honorable to the human species; for it is a barter of their
            fellow creatures – you must not by this imagine, that the slaves are brought here, no,
            for none would be slaves after they had breathed the British air – they are bought in
            Africa for coarse clothes, arms, spirits &amp; taken to the West Indies and sold for the
            produce of these Islands, which is brought to this place &amp; from it taken to
            different parts of the country. </p></div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
