<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to <persName role="recipient" type="letter"><forename>Mary</forename>
                  <surname>Behrend</surname>, typed and sent by <persName role="sender"
                     type="letter"><forename>Irvin</forename>
                     <surname>Kochel</surname></persName>
                  <date when="1955-06-13"/></persName></title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Standar size piece of <material type="OnionPaper">onion paper</material> from <date
               when="1955">1955</date>, printed front and back, single sheet.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <p>Letter from a series of letters between <persName>Mary Behrend</persName> and
                  <persName>Irvin Kochel</persName>.</p>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note><persName role="Admin">Irvin Kochel</persName> was the Administrative Head for
                  <placeName role="College">Penn State Behrend</placeName> (Previously known as the
               Behrend Center). He coresponded with <persName role="Landowner">Mary
                  Behrend</persName>, who was the owner of the land <placeName role="College">Penn
                  State Behrend</placeName> was built on.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Thin piece of <material type="OnionPaper">onion paper</material> typed with a
                  <objectType>type writer</objectType>, front and back. Left side of the paper is
                  <damage type="crumpled">crumpled</damage> a bit. Text can be seen through the
               page.</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p style="Formal"><persName xml:id="Mary_Behrend">Mrs. <forename>Mary</forename> B.
                  <surname>Behrend</surname></persName>
            <address>
               <name type="street">21 West Putnam Avenue</name>
               <name type="city">Greenwich</name>
               <name type="state">Conn</name>
            </address>
         </p>
         <p>Dear <persName>Mrs. <surname>Behrend</surname></persName>: In reference to your recent
            letters, I offer the following comments-- We would be most pleased to have <persName
               role="gardener">Mr. <forename>Paul</forename>
               <surname>Laver</surname></persName> from the Cemetery do certain planting around the
            entrance to the <placeName xml:id="behrend">Behrend Center</placeName> campus. We
            understand that this planting will be done by utilizing the existing shrubery in the
            formal gardens. It is also my understanding that you will reimburse <persName
               role="gardener">Mr. <surname>Laven</surname></persName> for his labors only for the
            planting around the entrance and for no other plant- ing. If you have not already done
            so, I would suggest that you contact <persName>Mr. Day</persName> infomring him of your
            desures to have <persName role="gardener">Mr. Laver</persName> do the above mentioned
            work. </p>
         <p>Insofar as the new building is concerned, we do not plant to proceed with this project
            this <date when="1955">year</date>. We have not as yet heard from <name role="Company"
               type="Electrical">General Electric</name> as to their intention of us doing their
            training program <date when="1955">this fall</date>. It will be impossible at this late
            date to complete any building arrangments for the Fall term, con- sequently we have
            delayed any action on a new building for this present year. We do, however, plan to
            spend approcimately <num type="USD">$25,000.00</num> completing the other half of the
            barn for utilisation as classrooms. </p>
         <p>We have located some of the lights for the living room which are in need of repair. At
            the present time we will investigate the repair of these lights and I will re- port to
            you at a later date as to whether or not they can be effectively repaired. </p>
         <p>We are making arrangments to erect a wrough iron rail around the case in which the <name
               type="Ship">Niagra</name> is displayed. Quite a few people have commented about the
            ship and have visited us with the express purpose of viewing it. Under separate cover we
            are sending you the <objectType>television films</objectType> of the presentation of the
            Flagship. These <objectType>films</objectType> can be shown on a standard
               <objectType>16mm. projector</objectType>. </p>
         <p>In refrence to the heating of the <placeName role="aquatics">swimming pool</placeName>,
            I have talked on two different occasions with <persName role="contactor">Mr.
                  <surname>Scobell</surname></persName> about completing the project. As yet he has
            done nothing to heat the pool with the exception of having ordered a piece of equip-
            ment that is needed to put the <objectType>furnace</objectType> in operating order. You
            might write Mr. Scobell asking him what progress he is making on this project.This may
            timu- late him to do something in the immediate future to complete it. </p>
         <p>In reference to the scholarships, as a result of our last <name role="advising"
               type="academic">Advisory Board</name> meeting, <persName>Mr. Nick</persName>
            appointed a new <name role="scholarships" type="monetary">Scholarship Committee</name>,
            consisting of <persName>Jerry Stokes</persName>, Chair- man, <persName role="chairman"
                  ><forename>William</forename>
               <surname>Hamilton</surname></persName> and <persName><forename>John</forename>
               <surname>Zurn</surname></persName>. I have had one meeting with <persName>Mr.
               Stokes</persName> and we are planning to arrange for a number of scholarships which
            will be available <pb/> -2- by <date when="1996">September 1956</date>. Our scholarship
            fund at <time>present</time> has been consumed <damage type="creased">so that</damage>
            there is only <num>$650.00</num> remaining in this fund. We havegiven one scholar<damage
               type="crease">ship</damage> to a <placeName>McDowell High School</placeName> student
            for <date when="1955">September 1955</date>. The scholarship fund has not been generally
            advertised this year because of the small amount of money available. We have not in the
            past had scholarships that were spec<damage type="crease">ifically</damage> designated
            as Protestant scholarships. Inasmuch as we are a state university we do not feel that it
            would be ethical to differentiate as to religion or race in the issuance of scholarship.
            I will keep you informed of the activ<damage type="crease">ities</damage> of this
            committee and what programs they make. I am quite sure that we will <damage
               type="crease">be</damage> building the scholarship fund to the point where at least
            one scholarship wi<damage type="crease">ll</damage> be available to all eleven of the
            area high school each year. Generally s<damage type="crease">peak</damage>- ing
            scholarships are in the amount of <num>$100.00</num> per <time>year</time>, per student. </p>
         <p><persName><forename>Ross</forename> P. <surname>Wright</surname></persName> of
               <placeName role="manufacturing">Reed Mfg. Company</placeName> has sent us several
            copies of letters tha<damage type="crease">t</damage> were supposedly writted by
               <persName>Commodore Perry</persName> on the deck of the <name>Ship Niagra</name> on
            the afternoon of his victory. We plan to have these copies framed and placed in
               <placeName xml:id="erie">Erie Hall</placeName> along with the Flagship. I hope this
            letter finds you in good health and enjoying the summer. Please give my kindest regards
            to Gail. Our family is well and in good health. </p>
         <p>Cordially yours, <persName role="head" type="administration" xml:id="Irvin_Kochel"
                  ><forename>Irvin</forename> H. <surname>Kochel</surname></persName> Administrative
            Head </p>
         <p>P.S. Thanks very much for the <name type="literature">London Illustrated News</name>. We
            will put these to good use in the Library at <placeName>Behrend Center</placeName>.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
