<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <letter xml:id="copenhagen-1955-07-28">
            <hand>Thus</hand>
            <hand><date when="1955-07-28">July 28</date>. uruet vilt oer cae c<u>otto</u> oei deierr
                <u>THURSDAY</u></hand>
        <typeWritten>
            <p n="1"> Did letter and left the <placeName>Astoria</placeName> with <persName>Otto</persName> and the <transport>ford
                    car</transport>- our new car and driver for our jaunt. Went to Bang and looked at
                fur jackets.And then to <persName>jensens</persName> where <persName>Gail</persName> made a purchase. To
                <placeName>Weavers embroidery shop</placeName>. Then to <placeName>Oscar Davidson's</placeName> where the
                Menu is s<x rw="e">e</x>veral yards long- all open faced
                    sadnwhiches. Didn't think so much of this place. Then to the
                    <placeName>Permente</placeName> again and <merge where="upline">then bac<x
                         rw="k">k</x> to the astoria to pack up our
                    things</merge> and left for the <placeName><u>Palace Hotel</u></placeName> where
                we had a rather nice room etc. Then we rushed out to the <placeName>Rosenborg
                    Palace</placeName> to see the jewels etc. It was close in about half an hour so
                didn't have too much time.After this we drove out to the <placeName>Roya<x
                        rw="L">l</x>
                    <u>Deer Park</u></placeName>. A large building in a park- open fields with many
                herds of deer roaming about </p>
            <p n="2"> In the evening we were invited to <persName>Mr Dessau's</persName> f or
                dinner. his son <persName>William</persName> came in to get us. Very nice and
                friendly. Almost everyone seems to speak English. They get a terrific lot of it in
                the schools. <persName>Mrs Dessau</persName> looks very young Had another son
                    there-<persName>ROul</persName>- and his very sweet bride of a few months. She
                was born in <placeName>Mexico</placeName> and in fact IS
                    Mexican but lived a long time in
                    <placeName>Texas</placeName>. Does notnSpeak Danish. After
                meeting them all <persName>Mr Dessau</persName> Asked us to see his
                    <placeName>garden</placeName>. He had several hundred
                    parakets in a huge cage- like a b<x rw="ig">ig</x>
                <u>room</u>- and arranged so they could fly in and out. Then he
                showed us his special pets Two tame Kangaroo!! They hopped out of
                their enclosure and like to me patted. Very tame. He has had them several years. T
                gave <persName>Mrs Dessau</persName> one of my little trimmed
                    Christmas trees And to the bride a little "shelf" which was
                really Mexican and I had trimmed it over and remade it
                They werre very pleqsed. had a nice evening and enjoyed
                them all. Also we LIKE the Toborg beer better than ant other kind!! </p>
        </typeWritten>
    </letter>
</xml>
