<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
  <letter xml:id="Manoir-1955-07"> 
      <intro>
          Phone, <placeName>Azay-le-Rideau</placeName> 46
          <placeName>Manoir De Bécheron</placeName>
          Saché
          <placeName>Indre-et-Loire</placeName>
      </intro>
     
      <figure>
          <graphic url="images/Manoir.jpg"/>
          <caption>A description of a Manoir de Becheron</caption>
      </figure>
      <note resp="jep">We think this letter must be written before they leave, but after the others we have encoded. We speculate the date must be before <date when="1955-07-29">July 29, 1955</date>.</note>
      <p>
          <placeName>The Manoir de Bécheron</placeName> is a private home which welcomes a few paying guests. It is a rambling <timePeriod>15th-16th Century</timePeriod> house 
    situated in the peaceful valley of the<placeName> Indre</placeName> in the heart of the <placeName>Chateaux de la Loire region</placeName>. The air of Old World charm
    with modern comfort. The cuisine is French, meals are 'en famille', except for breakfast, which is served in your room 
    or if you choose, in the gardens.
    You are one of us when we go visiting our French and American neighbors. Among them are such famous artists as <persName>Alexander 
    Calder</persName>, <persName>Max Ernst</persName> and <persName>A. Ozenfant.</persName>
    Bécheron is 25 kilometers from Tours, which can be reached by rail from <placeName>Paris</placeName> in about two and half hours. Of course we
    meet you at the station.
    The rate in high-season <date>(June 15</date>-<date>August 31</date>) is $15 a day or $100 a week per person all inclusive (room, bath, 3 meals, 
    wines, liqueurs, coffee and service). This includes the local excursions around <placeName>Bécheron</placeName> such as <placeName>Saché,</placeName> <placeName>Azay-le-Rideau,</placeName>
    Tours, <placeName>Langeais.</placeName> <placeName>The Saché Museum </placeName>now houses a permanent exhibit of the sculpture of my father, <persName>Jo Davidson.</persName> The off-season
    rate <date>(March 1</date>-<date>June 14</date>; <date>Sept. 1</date>-<date>October 31)</date> is $10 a day or $65 a week per person. Contrary to the usual continental practice
    there are no extra charges at Bécheron.
    My French wife and I have two children,<persName> Eva</persName> age 12 and <persName>Laurent</persName> who is 5; we can and do care for children, and you will find 
    they are never underfoot. If you should want a place where you can safetly leave yours while touring <placeName>Europe, Bécheron</placeName> is 
    the place you are looking for. Our children were born in the <placeName>United States</placeName> and speak French and English as of course we do.
    A week in <placeName>Bécheron</placeName> is over before you realize it! You won't want to miss the thrilling sight of the illuminated chateaux;
    they alone are worth the trip. The <placeName>"Sleeping Beauty" castle of Usse</placeName>, <placeName>Azay-le-Rideau</placeName>, famous Chenonceau and Chambord are but 
    a few of the fabulous palaces which surround us.
    During one of your outings we will picnic in the <placeName>Forêt de Loches</placeName> near a circular <timePeriod>12th Century</timePeriod> chapel, or on the banks of the
    Loire across from <placeName>Mme. de Pompadour's palace at Ménars</placeName>. We will also take you to one of the outstanding restaurants of Tours 
    on a picturesque medieval square.
    We are looking forward with pleasure to meeting you, with or without your children. We'll be glad to answer any specific questions
    you may have. 
    Write for us.</p>
      

   
   <p n="2"> Cordially yours, 
    (signiture)
   <persName> Jacques Davidson </persName></p>
    </letter>
   
</xml>
