<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schema/schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <letter xml:id="Greenwich-1955-07-18">
        <figure>
            <graphic url="images/noon.julyimage.jpg"/>
            <caption>July 18th, 1955</caption>
        </figure>
        <dateLine><placeName>Departure. On Queen Elizabeth.</placeName><time> At Noon</time>, <date when="1955-07-18">July 18, 1955.</date></dateLine>
     <p n="1">   We got on board about <time>10</time>
    <persName>Harriet</persName> had stayed in <placeName>Greenwich</placeName> over night so went in town with us. <misspelling word="We">Wm</misspelling> drove the <transport>station wagon</transport> with our 
    bags. Very cleverlym selected as we had two s<x rw="ii">uu</x>t cases each and a "bottle bag and the typewriter-plus
    a very unhealthy looking green duffle bag(reserved for purchases. THIS folded up on thebbottem of a suit case for future use!
        State room gay with flowers and champagne. We had a send of party. <persName>Billy</persName> was hiding behind a curtain and was a HUGE
    surprise'<persName>Caryl</persName> had arranged it this way <persName>Gail's</persName> mother and a friend- <persName>Dale</persName> and <persName>Kissy</persName> got to the <placeName>dock</placeName> just after <time>10.30 </time>
    and were not allowed to come on board. Too bad.
        <transport>Huge ship</transport>. Like a section of the <placeName>Waldorf- the Reacock Alley</placeName> plus several of the <placeName>dining</placeName> rooms- afloat Streams of 
    PEOPLE nulling about.

        We had a table in the <placeName>dining</placeName> room with 5 other femal ladies. Thought it would divert us. The one man looked us over and
        next meal he wasn't there. So we <misspelling word="drew">dr4ew</misspelling> <misspelling word="an">ano</misspelling> anoother lady. It all proved to be amusing. We exchange addresses and werephotographed
        to-gether. 
    Voyage very smooth all way over. We took in the <placeName>movies</placeName> and <placeName>pools</placeName>. I won a few dollars on a pool.
        A <persName>Mr and Mrs Andeson</persName>, very nice friends of <persName>H.</persName> and <persName>Caryls</persName> asked us for cocktails one evening. Then there
        were the parties of the Captain and the Purser Also <persName>Esther Boyer</persName> was on board with a party of eight in cabin class, she 
        was to steer (ab??) over <placeName>Europe</placeName>. She came up and has tea with us one day.
        The <persName>Captain</persName> and <persName>Purser</persName> both were on the <placeName>Franconia</placeName> about years ago- as under officers- on a world cruise wer were on.
        Both exptremely cordial. 
        Took <transport>train</transport> around <time>noon</time> for <placeName>Paris</placeName>. Hot as blazes. and stuffy besides. Had lunch en route. Quite good.
        <placeName>Paris</placeName> and piled our belongings intoo a <transport>cab</transport> and landed at <placeName>Le Br istol</placeName>- a rather smallish hotel were diplomats go- white marble 
        and mirrors. We had an oval white panelled round sitting room. (which we didn't need and later gave up.)
        Very weary and after some refreshing tub baths went over to the <placeName>Crenailliere</placeName>(nearby) where we had a very delicious dinner.</p>
   </letter>

    
    
</xml>
